James

1
2
3
4
5

The Letter from James

1

1 James, a servant of God and of the Lord Jesus Christ,[*] to the twelve tribes which are in the Dispersion: Greetings.

2 Count it all joy, my brothers,[†] when you fall into various temptations, 3 knowing that the testing of your faith produces endurance. 4 Let endurance have its perfect work, that you may be perfect and complete, lacking in nothing.

5 But if any of you lacks wisdom, let him ask of God, who gives to all liberally and without reproach, and it will be given to him. 6 But let him ask in faith, without any doubting, for he who doubts is like a wave of the sea, driven by the wind and tossed. 7 For that man shouldn’t think that he will receive anything from the Lord. 8 He is a double-minded man, unstable in all his ways.

9 Let the brother in humble circumstances glory in his high position; 10 and the rich, in that he is made humble, because like the flower in the grass, he will pass away. 11 For the sun arises with the scorching wind and withers the grass; and the flower in it falls, and the beauty of its appearance perishes. So the rich man will also fade away in his pursuits.

12 Blessed is a person who endures temptation, for when he has been approved, he will receive the crown of life which the Lord promised to those who love him.

13 Let no man say when he is tempted, “I am tempted by God,” for God can’t be tempted by evil, and he himself tempts no one. 14 But each one is tempted when he is drawn away by his own lust and enticed. 15 Then the lust, when it has conceived, bears sin. The sin, when it is full grown, produces death. 16 Don’t be deceived, my beloved brothers. 17 Every good gift and every perfect gift is from above, coming down from the Father of lights, with whom can be no variation nor turning shadow. 18 Of his own will he gave birth to us by the word of truth, that we should be a kind of first fruits of his creatures.

19 So, then, my beloved brothers, let every man be swift to hear, slow to speak, and slow to anger; 20 for the anger of man doesn’t produce the righteousness of God. 21 Therefore, putting away all filthiness and overflowing of wickedness, receive with humility the implanted word, which is able to save your souls.[‡]

22 But be doers of the word, and not only hearers, deluding your own selves. 23 For if anyone is a hearer of the word and not a doer, he is like a man looking at his natural face in a mirror; 24 for he sees himself, and goes away, and immediately forgets what kind of man he was. 25 But he who looks into the perfect law of freedom and continues, not being a hearer who forgets but a doer of the work, this man will be blessed in what he does.

26 If anyone among you thinks himself to be religious while he doesn’t bridle his tongue, but deceives his heart, this man’s religion is worthless. 27 Pure religion and undefiled before our God and Father is this: to visit the fatherless and widows in their affliction, and to keep oneself unstained by the world.

2

1 My brothers, don’t hold the faith of our glorious Lord Jesus Christ with partiality. 2 For if a man with a gold ring, in fine clothing, comes into your synagogue,[*] and a poor man in filthy clothing also comes in, 3 and you pay special attention to him who wears the fine clothing and say, “Sit here in a good place;” and you tell the poor man, “Stand there,” or “Sit by my footstool” 4 haven’t you shown partiality among yourselves, and become judges with evil thoughts? 5 Listen, my beloved brothers. Didn’t God choose those who are poor in this world to be rich in faith and heirs of the Kingdom which he promised to those who love him? 6 But you have dishonored the poor man. Don’t the rich oppress you and personally drag you before the courts? 7 Don’t they blaspheme the honorable name by which you are called?

8 However, if you fulfill the royal law according to the Scripture, “You shall love your neighbor as yourself,”[✡] you do well. 9 But if you show partiality, you commit sin, being convicted by the law as transgressors. 10 For whoever keeps the whole law, and yet stumbles in one point, he has become guilty of all. 11 For he who said, “Do not commit adultery,”[✡] also said, “Do not commit murder.”[✡] Now if you do not commit adultery but do murder, you have become a transgressor of the law. 12 So speak and so do as men who are to be judged by the law of freedom. 13 For judgment is without mercy to him who has shown no mercy. Mercy triumphs over judgment.

14 What good is it, my brothers, if a man says he has faith, but has no works? Can faith save him? 15 And if a brother or sister is naked and in lack of daily food, 16 and one of you tells them, “Go in peace. Be warmed and filled;” yet you didn’t give them the things the body needs, what good is it? 17 Even so faith, if it has no works, is dead in itself. 18 Yes, a man will say, “You have faith, and I have works.” Show me your faith without works, and I will show you my faith by my works.

19 You believe that God is one. You do well. The demons also believe—and shudder. 20 But do you want to know, vain man, that faith apart from works is dead? 21 Wasn’t Abraham our father justified by works, in that he offered up Isaac his son on the altar? 22 You see that faith worked with his works, and by works faith was perfected. 23 So the Scripture was fulfilled which says, “Abraham believed God, and it was accounted to him as righteousness,”[✡] and he was called the friend of God. 24 You see then that by works a man is justified, and not only by faith. 25 In the same way, wasn’t Rahab the prostitute also justified by works when she received the messengers and sent them out another way? 26 For as the body apart from the spirit is dead, even so faith apart from works is dead.

3

1 Let not many of you be teachers, my brothers, knowing that we will receive heavier judgment. 2 For we all stumble in many things. Anyone who doesn’t stumble in word is a perfect person, able to bridle the whole body also. 3 Indeed, we put bits into the horses’ mouths so that they may obey us, and we guide their whole body. 4 Behold,[*] the ships also, though they are so big and are driven by fierce winds, are yet guided by a very small rudder, wherever the pilot desires. 5 So the tongue is also a little member, and boasts great things. See how a small fire can spread to a large forest! 6 And the tongue is a fire. The world of iniquity among our members is the tongue, which defiles the whole body, and sets on fire the course of nature, and is set on fire by Gehenna.[†] 7 For every kind of animal, bird, creeping thing, and sea creature is tamed, and has been tamed by mankind; 8 but nobody can tame the tongue. It is a restless evil, full of deadly poison. 9 With it we bless our God and Father, and with it we curse men who are made in the image of God. 10 Out of the same mouth comes blessing and cursing. My brothers, these things ought not to be so. 11 Does a spring send out from the same opening fresh and bitter water? 12 Can a fig tree, my brothers, yield olives, or a vine figs? Thus no spring yields both salt water and fresh water.

13 Who is wise and understanding among you? Let him show by his good conduct that his deeds are done in gentleness of wisdom. 14 But if you have bitter jealousy and selfish ambition in your heart, don’t boast and don’t lie against the truth. 15 This wisdom is not that which comes down from above, but is earthly, sensual, and demonic. 16 For where jealousy and selfish ambition are, there is confusion and every evil deed. 17 But the wisdom that is from above is first pure, then peaceful, gentle, reasonable, full of mercy and good fruits, without partiality, and without hypocrisy. 18 Now the fruit of righteousness is sown in peace by those who make peace.

4

1 Where do wars and fightings among you come from? Don’t they come from your pleasures that war in your members? 2 You lust, and don’t have. You murder and covet, and can’t obtain. You fight and make war. You don’t have, because you don’t ask. 3 You ask, and don’t receive, because you ask with wrong motives, so that you may spend it on your pleasures. 4 You adulterers and adulteresses, don’t you know that friendship with the world is hostility toward God? Whoever therefore wants to be a friend of the world makes himself an enemy of God. 5 Or do you think that the Scripture says in vain, “The Spirit who lives in us yearns jealously”? 6 But he gives more grace. Therefore it says, “God resists the proud, but gives grace to the humble.”[✡] 7 Be subject therefore to God. Resist the devil, and he will flee from you. 8 Draw near to God, and he will draw near to you. Cleanse your hands, you sinners. Purify your hearts, you double-minded. 9 Lament, mourn, and weep. Let your laughter be turned to mourning and your joy to gloom. 10 Humble yourselves in the sight of the Lord, and he will exalt you.

11 Don’t speak against one another, brothers. He who speaks against a brother and judges his brother, speaks against the law and judges the law. But if you judge the law, you are not a doer of the law but a judge. 12 Only one is the lawgiver, who is able to save and to destroy. But who are you to judge another?

13 Come now, you who say, “Today or tomorrow let’s go into this city and spend a year there, trade, and make a profit.” 14 Yet you don’t know what your life will be like tomorrow. For what is your life? For you are a vapor that appears for a little time and then vanishes away. 15 For you ought to say, “If the Lord wills, we will both live, and do this or that.” 16 But now you glory in your boasting. All such boasting is evil. 17 To him therefore who knows to do good and doesn’t do it, to him it is sin.

5

1 Come now, you rich, weep and howl for your miseries that are coming on you. 2 Your riches are corrupted and your garments are moth-eaten. 3 Your gold and your silver are corroded, and their corrosion will be for a testimony against you and will eat your flesh like fire. You have laid up your treasure in the last days. 4 Behold, the wages of the laborers who mowed your fields, which you have kept back by fraud, cry out; and the cries of those who reaped have entered into the ears of the Lord of Armies.[*] 5 You have lived in luxury on the earth, and taken your pleasure. You have nourished your hearts as in a day of slaughter. 6 You have condemned and you have murdered the righteous one. He doesn’t resist you.

7 Be patient therefore, brothers, until the coming of the Lord. Behold, the farmer waits for the precious fruit of the earth, being patient over it, until it receives the early and late rain. 8 You also be patient. Establish your hearts, for the coming of the Lord is at hand.

9 Don’t grumble, brothers, against one another, so that you won’t be judged. Behold, the judge stands at the door. 10 Take, brothers, for an example of suffering and of perseverance, the prophets who spoke in the name of the Lord. 11 Behold, we call them blessed who endured. You have heard of the perseverance of Job and have seen the Lord in the outcome, and how the Lord is full of compassion and mercy.

12 But above all things, my brothers, don’t swear— not by heaven, or by the earth, or by any other oath; but let your “yes” be “yes”, and your “no”, “no”, so that you don’t fall into hypocrisy.[†]

13 Is any among you suffering? Let him pray. Is any cheerful? Let him sing praises. 14 Is any among you sick? Let him call for the elders of the assembly, and let them pray over him, anointing him with oil in the name of the Lord; 15 and the prayer of faith will heal him who is sick, and the Lord will raise him up. If he has committed sins, he will be forgiven. 16 Confess your sins to one another and pray for one another, that you may be healed. The insistent prayer of a righteous person is powerfully effective. 17 Elijah was a man with a nature like ours, and he prayed earnestly that it might not rain, and it didn’t rain on the earth for three years and six months. 18 He prayed again, and the sky gave rain, and the earth produced its fruit.

19 Brothers, if any among you wanders from the truth and someone turns him back, 20 let him know that he who turns a sinner from the error of his way will save a soul from death and will cover a multitude of sins.

* 1:1 “Christ” means “Anointed One”.

† 1:2 The word for “brothers” here and where context allows may also be correctly translated “brothers and sisters” or “siblings.”

‡ 1:21 or, preserve your life.

* 2:2 or, meeting

✡ 2:8 Leviticus 19:18

✡ 2:11 Exodus 20:14; Deuteronomy 5:18

✡ 2:11 Exodus 20:13; Deuteronomy 5:17

✡ 2:23 Genesis 15:6

* 3:4 “Behold”, from “ἰδοὺ”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.

† 3:6 or, Hell

✡ 4:6 Proverbs 3:34

* 5:4 Greek: Sabaoth (for Hebrew: Tze’va’ot)

† 5:12 TR reads “under judgment” instead of “into hypocrisy”

Job

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10

11
12
13
14
15
16
17
18
19
20

21
22
23
24
25
26
27
28
29
30

31
32
33
34
35
36
37
38
39
40

41
42

The Book of

Job

1

1 There was a man in the land of Uz, whose name was Job. That man was blameless and upright, and one who feared God,[*] and turned away from evil. 2 There were born to him seven sons and three daughters. 3 His possessions also were seven thousand sheep, three thousand camels, five hundred yoke of oxen, five hundred female donkeys, and a very great household; so that this man was the greatest of all the children of the east. 4 His sons went and held a feast in the house of each one on his birthday; and they sent and called for their three sisters to eat and to drink with them. 5 It was so, when the days of their feasting had run their course, that Job sent and sanctified them, and rose up early in the morning, and offered burnt offerings according to the number of them all. For Job said, “It may be that my sons have sinned, and renounced God in their hearts.” Job did so continually.

6 Now on the day when God’s sons came to present themselves before Yahweh,[†] Satan also came among them. 7 Yahweh said to Satan, “Where have you come from?”

Then Satan answered Yahweh, and said, “From going back and forth in the earth, and from walking up and down in it.”

8 Yahweh said to Satan, “Have you considered my servant, Job? For there is no one like him in the earth, a blameless and an upright man, one who fears God, and turns away from evil.”

9 Then Satan answered Yahweh, and said, “Does Job fear God for nothing? 10 Haven’t you made a hedge around him, and around his house, and around all that he has, on every side? You have blessed the work of his hands, and his substance is increased in the land. 11 But stretch out your hand now, and touch all that he has, and he will renounce you to your face.”

12 Yahweh said to Satan, “Behold,[‡] all that he has is in your power. Only on himself don’t stretch out your hand.”

So Satan went out from the presence of Yahweh. 13 It fell on a day when his sons and his daughters were eating and drinking wine in their oldest brother’s house, 14 that a messenger came to Job, and said, “The oxen were plowing, and the donkeys feeding beside them, 15 and the Sabeans attacked, and took them away. Yes, they have killed the servants with the edge of the sword, and I alone have escaped to tell you.”

16 While he was still speaking, another also came and said, “The fire of God has fallen from the sky, and has burned up the sheep and the servants, and consumed them, and I alone have escaped to tell you.”

17 While he was still speaking, another also came and said, “The Chaldeans made three bands, and swept down on the camels, and have taken them away, yes, and killed the servants with the edge of the sword; and I alone have escaped to tell you.”

18 While he was still speaking, there came also another, and said, “Your sons and your daughters were eating and drinking wine in their oldest brother’s house, 19 and behold, there came a great wind from the wilderness, and struck the four corners of the house, and it fell on the young men, and they are dead. I alone have escaped to tell you.”

20 Then Job arose, and tore his robe, and shaved his head, and fell down on the ground, and worshiped. 21 He said, “Naked I came out of my mother’s womb, and naked will I return there. Yahweh gave, and Yahweh has taken away. Blessed be Yahweh’s name.” 22 In all this, Job didn’t sin, nor charge God with wrongdoing.

2

1 Again, on the day when God’s sons came to present themselves before Yahweh, Satan came also among them to present himself before Yahweh. 2 Yahweh said to Satan, “Where have you come from?”

Satan answered Yahweh, and said, “From going back and forth in the earth, and from walking up and down in it.”

3 Yahweh said to Satan, “Have you considered my servant Job? For there is no one like him in the earth, a blameless and an upright man, one who fears God, and turns away from evil. He still maintains his integrity, although you incited me against him, to ruin him without cause.”

4 Satan answered Yahweh, and said, “Skin for skin. Yes, all that a man has he will give for his life. 5 But stretch out your hand now, and touch his bone and his flesh, and he will renounce you to your face.”

6 Yahweh said to Satan, “Behold, he is in your hand. Only spare his life.”

7 So Satan went out from the presence of Yahweh, and struck Job with painful sores from the sole of his foot to his head. 8 He took for himself a potsherd to scrape himself with, and he sat among the ashes. 9 Then his wife said to him, “Do you still maintain your integrity? Renounce God, and die.”

10 But he said to her, “You speak as one of the foolish women would speak. What? Shall we receive good at the hand of God, and shall we not receive evil?”

In all this Job didn’t sin with his lips. 11 Now when Job’s three friends heard of all this evil that had come on him, they each came from his own place: Eliphaz the Temanite, Bildad the Shuhite, and Zophar the Naamathite; and they made an appointment together to come to sympathize with him and to comfort him. 12 When they lifted up their eyes from a distance, and didn’t recognize him, they raised their voices, and wept; and they each tore his robe, and sprinkled dust on their heads toward the sky. 13 So they sat down with him on the ground seven days and seven nights, and no one spoke a word to him, for they saw that his grief was very great.

3

1 After this Job opened his mouth, and cursed the day of his birth. 2 Job answered:

3 “Let the day perish in which I was born,

the night which said, ‘There is a boy conceived.’

4 Let that day be darkness.

Don’t let God from above seek for it,

neither let the light shine on it.

5 Let darkness and the shadow of death claim it for their own.

Let a cloud dwell on it.

Let all that makes the day black terrify it.

6 As for that night, let thick darkness seize on it.

Let it not rejoice among the days of the year.

Let it not come into the number of the months.

7 Behold, let that night be barren.

Let no joyful voice come therein.

8 Let them curse it who curse the day,

who are ready to rouse up leviathan.

9 Let the stars of its twilight be dark.

Let it look for light, but have none,

neither let it see the eyelids of the morning,

10 because it didn’t shut up the doors of my mother’s womb,

nor did it hide trouble from my eyes.

11 “Why didn’t I die from the womb?

Why didn’t I give up the spirit when my mother bore me?

12 Why did the knees receive me?

Or why the breast, that I should nurse?

13 For now I should have lain down and been quiet.

I should have slept, then I would have been at rest,

14 with kings and counselors of the earth,

who built up waste places for themselves;

15 or with princes who had gold,

who filled their houses with silver;

16 or as a hidden untimely birth I had not been,

as infants who never saw light.

17 There the wicked cease from troubling.

There the weary are at rest.

18 There the prisoners are at ease together.

They don’t hear the voice of the taskmaster.

19 The small and the great are there.

The servant is free from his master.

20 “Why is light given to him who is in misery,

life to the bitter in soul,

21 who long for death, but it doesn’t come;

and dig for it more than for hidden treasures,

22 who rejoice exceedingly,

and are glad, when they can find the grave?

23 Why is light given to a man whose way is hidden,

whom God has hedged in?

24 For my sighing comes before I eat.

My groanings are poured out like water.

25 For the thing which I fear comes on me,

that which I am afraid of comes to me.

26 I am not at ease, neither am I quiet, neither do I have rest;

but trouble comes.”

4

1 Then Eliphaz the Temanite answered,

2 “If someone ventures to talk with you, will you be grieved?

But who can withhold himself from speaking?

3 Behold, you have instructed many,

you have strengthened the weak hands.

4 Your words have supported him who was falling,

you have made the feeble knees firm.

5 But now it has come to you, and you faint.

It touches you, and you are troubled.

6 Isn’t your piety your confidence?

Isn’t the integrity of your ways your hope?

7 “Remember, now, whoever perished, being innocent?

Or where were the upright cut off?

8 According to what I have seen, those who plow iniquity

and sow trouble, reap the same.

9 By the breath of God they perish.

By the blast of his anger are they consumed.

10 The roaring of the lion,

and the voice of the fierce lion,

the teeth of the young lions, are broken.

11 The old lion perishes for lack of prey.

The cubs of the lioness are scattered abroad.

12 “Now a thing was secretly brought to me.

My ear received a whisper of it.

13 In thoughts from the visions of the night,

when deep sleep falls on men,

14 fear came on me, and trembling,

which made all my bones shake.

15 Then a spirit passed before my face.

The hair of my flesh stood up.

16 It stood still, but I couldn’t discern its appearance.

A form was before my eyes.

Silence, then I heard a voice, saying,

17 ‘Shall mortal man be more just than God?

Shall a man be more pure than his Maker?

18 Behold, he puts no trust in his servants.

He charges his angels with error.

19 How much more those who dwell in houses of clay,

whose foundation is in the dust,

who are crushed before the moth!

20 Between morning and evening they are destroyed.

They perish forever without any regarding it.

21 Isn’t their tent cord plucked up within them?

They die, and that without wisdom.’

5

1 “Call now; is there any who will answer you?

To which of the holy ones will you turn?

2 For resentment kills the foolish man,

and jealousy kills the simple.

3 I have seen the foolish taking root,

but suddenly I cursed his habitation.

4 His children are far from safety.

They are crushed in the gate.

Neither is there any to deliver them,

5 whose harvest the hungry eat up,

and take it even out of the thorns.

The snare gapes for their substance.

6 For affliction doesn’t come out of the dust,

neither does trouble spring out of the ground;

7 but man is born to trouble,

as the sparks fly upward.

8 “But as for me, I would seek God.

I would commit my cause to God,

9 who does great things that can’t be fathomed,

marvelous things without number;

10 who gives rain on the earth,

and sends waters on the fields;

11 so that he sets up on high those who are low,

those who mourn are exalted to safety.

12 He frustrates the plans of the crafty,

so that their hands can’t perform their enterprise.

13 He takes the wise in their own craftiness;

the counsel of the cunning is carried headlong.

14 They meet with darkness in the day time,

and grope at noonday as in the night.

15 But he saves from the sword of their mouth,

even the needy from the hand of the mighty.

16 So the poor has hope,

and injustice shuts her mouth.

17 “Behold, happy is the man whom God corrects.

Therefore do not despise the chastening of the Almighty.

18 For he wounds and binds up.

He injures and his hands make whole.

19 He will deliver you in six troubles;

yes, in seven no evil will touch you.

20 In famine he will redeem you from death;

in war, from the power of the sword.

21 You will be hidden from the scourge of the tongue,

neither will you be afraid of destruction when it comes.

22  You will laugh at destruction and famine,

neither will you be afraid of the animals of the earth.

23 For you will be allied with the stones of the field.

The animals of the field will be at peace with you.

24 You will know that your tent is in peace.

You will visit your fold, and will miss nothing.

25 You will know also that your offspring[*] will be great,

your offspring as the grass of the earth.

26 You will come to your grave in a full age,

like a shock of grain comes in its season.

27 Behold, we have researched it. It is so.

Hear it, and know it for your good.”

6

1 Then Job answered,

2 “Oh that my anguish were weighed,

and all my calamity laid in the balances!

3 For now it would be heavier than the sand of the seas,

therefore my words have been rash.

4 For the arrows of the Almighty are within me.

My spirit drinks up their poison.

The terrors of God set themselves in array against me.

5 Does the wild donkey bray when he has grass?

Or does the ox low over his fodder?

6 Can that which has no flavor be eaten without salt?

Or is there any taste in the white of an egg?

7 My soul refuses to touch them.

They are as loathsome food to me.

8 “Oh that I might have my request,

that God would grant the thing that I long for,

9 even that it would please God to crush me;

that he would let loose his hand, and cut me off!

10 Let it still be my consolation,

yes, let me exult in pain that doesn’t spare,

that I have not denied the words of the Holy One.

11 What is my strength, that I should wait?

What is my end, that I should be patient?

12 Is my strength the strength of stones?

Or is my flesh of bronze?

13 Isn’t it that I have no help in me,

that wisdom is driven away from me?

14 “To him who is ready to faint, kindness should be shown from his friend;

even to him who forsakes the fear of the Almighty.

15 My brothers have dealt deceitfully as a brook,

as the channel of brooks that pass away;

16 which are black by reason of the ice,

in which the snow hides itself.

17 In the dry season, they vanish.

When it is hot, they are consumed out of their place.

18 The caravans that travel beside them turn away.

They go up into the waste, and perish.

19 The caravans of Tema looked.

The companies of Sheba waited for them.

20 They were distressed because they were confident.

They came there, and were confounded.

21 For now you are nothing.

You see a terror, and are afraid.

22 Did I ever say, ‘Give to me?’

or, ‘Offer a present for me from your substance?’

23 or, ‘Deliver me from the adversary’s hand?’

or, ‘Redeem me from the hand of the oppressors?’

24 “Teach me, and I will hold my peace.

Cause me to understand my error.

25 How forcible are words of uprightness!

But your reproof, what does it reprove?

26 Do you intend to reprove words,

since the speeches of one who is desperate are as wind?

27 Yes, you would even cast lots for the fatherless,

and make merchandise of your friend.

28 Now therefore be pleased to look at me,

for surely I will not lie to your face.

29 Please return.

Let there be no injustice.

Yes, return again.

My cause is righteous.

30 Is there injustice on my tongue?

Can’t my taste discern mischievous things?

7

1 “Isn’t a man forced to labor on earth?

Aren’t his days like the days of a hired hand?

2 As a servant who earnestly desires the shadow,

as a hireling who looks for his wages,

3 so I am made to possess months of misery,

wearisome nights are appointed to me.

4 When I lie down, I say,

‘When will I arise, and the night be gone?’

I toss and turn until the dawning of the day.

5 My flesh is clothed with worms and clods of dust.

My skin closes up, and breaks out afresh.

6 My days are swifter than a weaver’s shuttle,

and are spent without hope.

7 Oh remember that my life is a breath.

My eye will no more see good.

8 The eye of him who sees me will see me no more.

Your eyes will be on me, but I will not be.

9 As the cloud is consumed and vanishes away,

so he who goes down to Sheol[*] will come up no more.

10 He will return no more to his house,

neither will his place know him any more.

11 “Therefore I will not keep silent.

I will speak in the anguish of my spirit.

I will complain in the bitterness of my soul.

12 Am I a sea, or a sea monster,

that you put a guard over me?

13 When I say, ‘My bed will comfort me.

My couch will ease my complaint,’

14 then you scare me with dreams

and terrify me through visions,

15 so that my soul chooses strangling,

death rather than my bones.

16 I loathe my life.

I don’t want to live forever.

Leave me alone, for my days are but a breath.

17 What is man, that you should magnify him,

that you should set your mind on him,

18 that you should visit him every morning,

and test him every moment?

19 How long will you not look away from me,

nor leave me alone until I swallow down my spittle?

20 If I have sinned, what do I do to you, you watcher of men?

Why have you set me as a mark for you,

so that I am a burden to myself?

21 Why do you not pardon my disobedience, and take away my iniquity?

For now will I lie down in the dust.

You will seek me diligently, but I will not be.”

8

1 Then Bildad the Shuhite answered,

2 “How long will you speak these things?

Shall the words of your mouth be a mighty wind?

3 Does God pervert justice?

Or does the Almighty pervert righteousness?

4 If your children have sinned against him,

he has delivered them into the hand of their disobedience.

5 If you want to seek God diligently,

make your supplication to the Almighty.

6 If you were pure and upright,

surely now he would awaken for you,

and make the habitation of your righteousness prosperous.

7 Though your beginning was small,

yet your latter end would greatly increase.

8 “Please inquire of past generations.

Find out about the learning of their fathers.

9 (For we are but of yesterday, and know nothing,

because our days on earth are a shadow.)

10 Shall they not teach you, tell you,

and utter words out of their heart?

11 “Can the papyrus grow up without mire?

Can the rushes grow without water?

12 While it is yet in its greenness, not cut down,

it withers before any other reed.

13 So are the paths of all who forget God.

The hope of the godless man will perish,

14 whose confidence will break apart,

whose trust is a spider’s web.

15 He will lean on his house, but it will not stand.

He will cling to it, but it will not endure.

16 He is green before the sun.

His shoots go out along his garden.

17 His roots are wrapped around the rock pile.

He sees the place of stones.

18 If he is destroyed from his place,

then it will deny him, saying, ‘I have not seen you.’

19 Behold, this is the joy of his way.

Out of the earth, others will spring.

20 “Behold, God will not cast away a blameless man,

neither will he uphold the evildoers.

21 He will still fill your mouth with laughter,

your lips with shouting.

22 Those who hate you will be clothed with shame.

The tent of the wicked will be no more.”

9

1 Then Job answered,

2 “Truly I know that it is so,

but how can man be just with God?

3 If he is pleased to contend with him,

he can’t answer him one time in a thousand.

4 God is wise in heart, and mighty in strength.

Who has hardened himself against him and prospered?

5 He removes the mountains, and they don’t know it,

when he overturns them in his anger.

6 He shakes the earth out of its place.

Its pillars tremble.

7 He commands the sun and it doesn’t rise,

and seals up the stars.

8 He alone stretches out the heavens,

and treads on the waves of the sea.

9 He makes the Bear, Orion, and the Pleiades,

and the rooms of the south.

10 He does great things past finding out;

yes, marvelous things without number.

11 Behold, he goes by me, and I don’t see him.

He passes on also, but I don’t perceive him.

12 Behold, he snatches away.

Who can hinder him?

Who will ask him, ‘What are you doing?’

13 “God will not withdraw his anger.

The helpers of Rahab stoop under him.

14 How much less will I answer him,

and choose my words to argue with him?

15 Though I were righteous, yet I wouldn’t answer him.

I would make supplication to my judge.

16 If I had called, and he had answered me,

yet I wouldn’t believe that he listened to my voice.

17 For he breaks me with a storm,

and multiplies my wounds without cause.

18 He will not allow me to catch my breath,

but fills me with bitterness.

19 If it is a matter of strength, behold, he is mighty!

If of justice, ‘Who,’ says he, ‘will summon me?’

20 Though I am righteous, my own mouth will condemn me.

Though I am blameless, it will prove me perverse.

21 I am blameless.

I don’t respect myself.

I despise my life.

22 “It is all the same.

Therefore I say he destroys the blameless and the wicked.

23 If the scourge kills suddenly,

he will mock at the trial of the innocent.

24 The earth is given into the hand of the wicked.

He covers the faces of its judges.

If not he, then who is it?

25 “Now my days are swifter than a runner.

They flee away. They see no good.

26 They have passed away as the swift ships,

as the eagle that swoops on the prey.

27 If I say, ‘I will forget my complaint,

I will put off my sad face, and cheer up,’

28 I am afraid of all my sorrows.

I know that you will not hold me innocent.

29 I will be condemned.

Why then do I labor in vain?

30 If I wash myself with snow,

and cleanse my hands with lye,

31 yet you will plunge me in the ditch.

My own clothes will abhor me.

32 For he is not a man, as I am, that I should answer him,

that we should come together in judgment.

33 There is no umpire between us,

that might lay his hand on us both.

34 Let him take his rod away from me.

Let his terror not make me afraid;

35 then I would speak, and not fear him,

for I am not so in myself.

10

1 “My soul is weary of my life.

I will give free course to my complaint.

I will speak in the bitterness of my soul.

2 I will tell God, ‘Do not condemn me.

Show me why you contend with me.

3 Is it good to you that you should oppress,

that you should despise the work of your hands,

and smile on the counsel of the wicked?

4 Do you have eyes of flesh?

Or do you see as man sees?

5 Are your days as the days of mortals,

or your years as man’s years,

6 that you inquire after my iniquity,

and search after my sin?

7 Although you know that I am not wicked,

there is no one who can deliver out of your hand.

8 “ ‘Your hands have framed me and fashioned me altogether,

yet you destroy me.

9 Remember, I beg you, that you have fashioned me as clay.

Will you bring me into dust again?

10 Haven’t you poured me out like milk,

and curdled me like cheese?

11 You have clothed me with skin and flesh,

and knit me together with bones and sinews.

12 You have granted me life and loving kindness.

Your visitation has preserved my spirit.

13 Yet you hid these things in your heart.

I know that this is with you:

14 if I sin, then you mark me.

You will not acquit me from my iniquity.

15 If I am wicked, woe to me.

If I am righteous, I still will not lift up my head,

being filled with disgrace,

and conscious of my affliction.

16 If my head is held high, you hunt me like a lion.

Again you show yourself powerful to me.

17 You renew your witnesses against me,

and increase your indignation on me.

Changes and warfare are with me.

18 “ ‘Why, then, have you brought me out of the womb?

I wish I had given up the spirit, and no eye had seen me.

19 I should have been as though I had not been.

I should have been carried from the womb to the grave.

20 Aren’t my days few?

Stop!

Leave me alone, that I may find a little comfort,

21 before I go where I will not return from,

to the land of darkness and of the shadow of death;

22 the land dark as midnight,

of the shadow of death,

without any order,

where the light is as midnight.’ ”

11

1 Then Zophar, the Naamathite, answered,

2 “Shouldn’t the multitude of words be answered?

Should a man full of talk be justified?

3 Should your boastings make men hold their peace?

When you mock, will no man make you ashamed?

4 For you say, ‘My doctrine is pure.

I am clean in your eyes.’

5 But oh that God would speak,

and open his lips against you,

6 that he would show you the secrets of wisdom!

For true wisdom has two sides.

Know therefore that God exacts of you less than your iniquity deserves.

7 “Can you fathom the mystery of God?

Or can you probe the limits of the Almighty?

8 They are high as heaven. What can you do?

They are deeper than Sheol.[*] What can you know?

9 Its measure is longer than the earth,

and broader than the sea.

10 If he passes by, or confines,

or convenes a court, then who can oppose him?

11 For he knows false men.

He sees iniquity also, even though he doesn’t consider it.

12 An empty-headed man becomes wise

when a man is born as a wild donkey’s colt.

13 “If you set your heart aright,

stretch out your hands toward him.

14 If iniquity is in your hand, put it far away.

Don’t let unrighteousness dwell in your tents.

15 Surely then you will lift up your face without spot.

Yes, you will be steadfast, and will not fear,

16 for you will forget your misery.

You will remember it like waters that have passed away.

17 Life will be clearer than the noonday.

Though there is darkness, it will be as the morning.

18 You will be secure, because there is hope.

Yes, you will search, and will take your rest in safety.

19 Also you will lie down, and no one will make you afraid.

Yes, many will court your favor.

20 But the eyes of the wicked will fail.

They will have no way to flee.

Their hope will be the giving up of the spirit.”

12

1 Then Job answered,

2 “No doubt, but you are the people,

and wisdom will die with you.

3 But I have understanding as well as you;

I am not inferior to you.

Yes, who doesn’t know such things as these?

4 I am like one who is a joke to his neighbor,

I, who called on God, and he answered.

The just, the blameless man is a joke.

5 In the thought of him who is at ease there is contempt for misfortune.

It is ready for them whose foot slips.

6 The tents of robbers prosper.

Those who provoke God are secure,

who carry their god in their hands.

7 “But ask the animals now, and they will teach you;

the birds of the sky, and they will tell you.

8 Or speak to the earth, and it will teach you.

The fish of the sea will declare to you.

9 Who doesn’t know that in all these,

Yahweh’s hand has done this,

10 in whose hand is the life of every living thing,

and the breath of all mankind?

11 Doesn’t the ear try words,

even as the palate tastes its food?

12 With aged men is wisdom,

in length of days understanding.

13 “With God is wisdom and might.

He has counsel and understanding.

14 Behold, he breaks down, and it can’t be built again.

He imprisons a man, and there can be no release.

15 Behold, he withholds the waters, and they dry up.

Again, he sends them out, and they overturn the earth.

16 With him is strength and wisdom.

The deceived and the deceiver are his.

17 He leads counselors away stripped.

He makes judges fools.

18 He loosens the bond of kings.

He binds their waist with a belt.

19 He leads priests away stripped,

and overthrows the mighty.

20 He removes the speech of those who are trusted,

and takes away the understanding of the elders.

21 He pours contempt on princes,

and loosens the belt of the strong.

22 He uncovers deep things out of darkness,

and brings out to light the shadow of death.

23 He increases the nations, and he destroys them.

He enlarges the nations, and he leads them captive.

24 He takes away understanding from the chiefs of the people of the earth,

and causes them to wander in a wilderness where there is no way.

25 They grope in the dark without light.

He makes them stagger like a drunken man.

13

1 “Behold, my eye has seen all this.

My ear has heard and understood it.

2 What you know, I know also.

I am not inferior to you.

3 “Surely I would speak to the Almighty.

I desire to reason with God.

4 But you are forgers of lies.

You are all physicians of no value.

5 Oh that you would be completely silent!

Then you would be wise.

6 Hear now my reasoning.

Listen to the pleadings of my lips.

7 Will you speak unrighteously for God,

and talk deceitfully for him?

8 Will you show partiality to him?

Will you contend for God?

9 Is it good that he should search you out?

Or as one deceives a man, will you deceive him?

10 He will surely reprove you

if you secretly show partiality.

11 Won’t his majesty make you afraid

and his dread fall on you?

12 Your memorable sayings are proverbs of ashes.

Your defenses are defenses of clay.

13 “Be silent!

Leave me alone, that I may speak.

Let come on me what will.

14 Why should I take my flesh in my teeth,

and put my life in my hand?

15 Behold, he will kill me.

I have no hope.

Nevertheless, I will maintain my ways before him.

16 This also will be my salvation,

that a godless man will not come before him.

17 Listen carefully to my speech.

Let my declaration be in your ears.

18 See now, I have set my cause in order.

I know that I am righteous.

19 Who is he who will contend with me?

For then would I hold my peace and give up the spirit.

20 “Only don’t do two things to me,

then I will not hide myself from your face:

21 withdraw your hand far from me,

and don’t let your terror make me afraid.

22 Then call, and I will answer,

or let me speak, and you answer me.

23 How many are my iniquities and sins?

Make me know my disobedience and my sin.

24 Why do you hide your face,

and consider me your enemy?

25 Will you harass a driven leaf?

Will you pursue the dry stubble?

26 For you write bitter things against me,

and make me inherit the iniquities of my youth.

27 You also put my feet in the stocks,

and mark all my paths.

You set a bound to the soles of my feet,

28 though I am decaying like a rotten thing,

like a garment that is moth-eaten.

14

1 “Man, who is born of a woman,

is of few days, and full of trouble.

2 He grows up like a flower, and is cut down.

He also flees like a shadow, and doesn’t continue.

3 Do you open your eyes on such a one,

and bring me into judgment with you?

4 Who can bring a clean thing out of an unclean?

Not one.

5 Seeing his days are determined,

the number of his months is with you,

and you have appointed his bounds that he can’t pass.

6 Look away from him, that he may rest,

until he accomplishes, as a hireling, his day.

7 “For there is hope for a tree if it is cut down,

that it will sprout again,

that the tender branch of it will not cease.

8 Though its root grows old in the earth,

and its stock dies in the ground,

9 yet through the scent of water it will bud,

and sprout boughs like a plant.

10 But man dies, and is laid low.

Yes, man gives up the spirit, and where is he?

11 As the waters fail from the sea,

and the river wastes and dries up,

12 so man lies down and doesn’t rise.

Until the heavens are no more, they will not awake,

nor be roused out of their sleep.

13 “Oh that you would hide me in Sheol,[*]

that you would keep me secret until your wrath is past,

that you would appoint me a set time and remember me!

14 If a man dies, will he live again?

I would wait all the days of my warfare,

until my release should come.

15 You would call, and I would answer you.

You would have a desire for the work of your hands.

16 But now you count my steps.

Don’t you watch over my sin?

17 My disobedience is sealed up in a bag.

You fasten up my iniquity.

18 “But the mountain falling comes to nothing.

The rock is removed out of its place.

19 The waters wear the stones.

The torrents of it wash away the dust of the earth.

So you destroy the hope of man.

20 You forever prevail against him, and he departs.

You change his face, and send him away.

21 His sons come to honor, and he doesn’t know it.

They are brought low, but he doesn’t perceive it of them.

22 But his flesh on him has pain,

and his soul within him mourns.”

15

1 Then Eliphaz the Temanite answered,

2 “Should a wise man answer with vain knowledge,

and fill himself with the east wind?

3 Should he reason with unprofitable talk,

or with speeches with which he can do no good?

4 Yes, you do away with fear,

and hinder devotion before God.

5 For your iniquity teaches your mouth,

and you choose the language of the crafty.

6 Your own mouth condemns you, and not I.

Yes, your own lips testify against you.

7 “Are you the first man who was born?

Or were you brought out before the hills?

8 Have you heard the secret counsel of God?

Do you limit wisdom to yourself?

9 What do you know that we don’t know?

What do you understand which is not in us?

10 With us are both the gray-headed and the very aged men,

much older than your father.

11 Are the consolations of God too small for you,

even the word that is gentle toward you?

12 Why does your heart carry you away?

Why do your eyes flash,

13 that you turn your spirit against God,

and let such words go out of your mouth?

14 What is man, that he should be clean?

What is he who is born of a woman, that he should be righteous?

15 Behold, he puts no trust in his holy ones.

Yes, the heavens are not clean in his sight;

16 how much less one who is abominable and corrupt,

a man who drinks iniquity like water!

17 “I will show you, listen to me;

that which I have seen I will declare

18 (which wise men have told by their fathers,

and have not hidden it;

19 to whom alone the land was given,

and no stranger passed among them):

20 the wicked man writhes in pain all his days,

even the number of years that are laid up for the oppressor.

21 A sound of terrors is in his ears.

In prosperity the destroyer will come on him.

22 He doesn’t believe that he will return out of darkness.

He is waited for by the sword.

23 He wanders abroad for bread, saying, ‘Where is it?’

He knows that the day of darkness is ready at his hand.

24 Distress and anguish make him afraid.

They prevail against him, as a king ready to the battle.

25 Because he has stretched out his hand against God,

and behaves himself proudly against the Almighty,

26 he runs at him with a stiff neck,

with the thick shields of his bucklers,

27 because he has covered his face with his fatness,

and gathered fat on his thighs.

28 He has lived in desolate cities,

in houses which no one inhabited,

which were ready to become heaps.

29 He will not be rich, neither will his substance continue,

neither will their possessions be extended on the earth.

30 He will not depart out of darkness.

The flame will dry up his branches.

He will go away by the breath of God’s mouth.

31 Let him not trust in emptiness, deceiving himself,

for emptiness will be his reward.

32 It will be accomplished before his time.

His branch will not be green.

33 He will shake off his unripe grape as the vine,

and will cast off his flower as the olive tree.

34 For the company of the godless will be barren,

and fire will consume the tents of bribery.

35 They conceive mischief and produce iniquity.

Their heart prepares deceit.”

16

1 Then Job answered,

2 “I have heard many such things.

You are all miserable comforters!

3 Shall vain words have an end?

Or what provokes you that you answer?

4 I also could speak as you do.

If your soul were in my soul’s place,

I could join words together against you,

and shake my head at you,

5 but I would strengthen you with my mouth.

The solace of my lips would relieve you.

6 “Though I speak, my grief is not subsided.

Though I forbear, what am I eased?

7 But now, God, you have surely worn me out.

You have made all my company desolate.

8 You have shriveled me up. This is a witness against me.

My leanness rises up against me.

It testifies to my face.

9 He has torn me in his wrath and persecuted me.

He has gnashed on me with his teeth.

My adversary sharpens his eyes on me.

10 They have gaped on me with their mouth.

They have struck me on the cheek reproachfully.

They gather themselves together against me.

11 God delivers me to the ungodly,

and casts me into the hands of the wicked.

12 I was at ease, and he broke me apart.

Yes, he has taken me by the neck, and dashed me to pieces.

He has also set me up for his target.

13 His archers surround me.

He splits my kidneys apart, and does not spare.

He pours out my bile on the ground.

14 He breaks me with breach on breach.

He runs at me like a giant.

15 I have sewed sackcloth on my skin,

and have thrust my horn in the dust.

16 My face is red with weeping.

Deep darkness is on my eyelids,

17 although there is no violence in my hands,

and my prayer is pure.

18 “Earth, don’t cover my blood.

Let my cry have no place to rest.

19 Even now, behold, my witness is in heaven.

He who vouches for me is on high.

20 My friends scoff at me.

My eyes pour out tears to God,

21 that he would maintain the right of a man with God,

of a son of man with his neighbor!

22 For when a few years have come,

I will go the way of no return.

17

1 “My spirit is consumed.

My days are extinct

and the grave is ready for me.

2 Surely there are mockers with me.

My eye dwells on their provocation.

3 “Now give a pledge. Be collateral for me with yourself.

Who is there who will strike hands with me?

4 For you have hidden their heart from understanding,

therefore you will not exalt them.

5 He who denounces his friends for plunder,

even the eyes of his children will fail.

6 “But he has made me a byword of the people.

They spit in my face.

7 My eye also is dim by reason of sorrow.

All my members are as a shadow.

8 Upright men will be astonished at this.

The innocent will stir himself up against the godless.

9 Yet the righteous will hold to his way.

He who has clean hands will grow stronger and stronger.

10 But as for you all, come back.

I will not find a wise man among you.

11 My days are past.

My plans are broken off,

as are the thoughts of my heart.

12 They change the night into day,

saying ‘The light is near’ in the presence of darkness.

13 If I look for Sheol[*] as my house,

if I have spread my couch in the darkness,

14 if I have said to corruption, ‘You are my father,’

and to the worm, ‘My mother,’ and ‘My sister,’

15 where then is my hope?

As for my hope, who will see it?

16 Shall it go down with me to the gates of Sheol,[†]

or descend together into the dust?”

18

1 Then Bildad the Shuhite answered,

2 “How long will you hunt for words?

Consider, and afterwards we will speak.

3 Why are we counted as animals,

which have become unclean in your sight?

4 You who tear yourself in your anger,

will the earth be forsaken for you?

Or will the rock be removed out of its place?

5 “Yes, the light of the wicked will be put out.

The spark of his fire won’t shine.

6 The light will be dark in his tent.

His lamp above him will be put out.

7 The steps of his strength will be shortened.

His own counsel will cast him down.

8 For he is cast into a net by his own feet,

and he wanders into its mesh.

9 A snare will take him by the heel.

A trap will catch him.

10 A noose is hidden for him in the ground,

a trap for him on the path.

11 Terrors will make him afraid on every side,

and will chase him at his heels.

12 His strength will be famished.

Calamity will be ready at his side.

13 The members of his body will be devoured.

The firstborn of death will devour his members.

14 He will be rooted out of the security of his tent.

He will be brought to the king of terrors.

15 There will dwell in his tent that which is none of his.

Sulfur will be scattered on his habitation.

16 His roots will be dried up beneath.

His branch will be cut off above.

17 His memory will perish from the earth.

He will have no name in the street.

18 He will be driven from light into darkness,

and chased out of the world.

19 He will have neither son nor grandson among his people,

nor any remaining where he lived.

20 Those who come after will be astonished at his day,

as those who went before were frightened.

21 Surely such are the dwellings of the unrighteous.

This is the place of him who doesn’t know God.”

19

1 Then Job answered,

2 “How long will you torment me,

and crush me with words?

3 You have reproached me ten times.

You aren’t ashamed that you attack me.

4 If it is true that I have erred,

my error remains with myself.

5 If indeed you will magnify yourselves against me,

and plead against me my reproach,

6 know now that God has subverted me,

and has surrounded me with his net.

7 “Behold, I cry out of wrong, but I am not heard.

I cry for help, but there is no justice.

8 He has walled up my way so that I can’t pass,

and has set darkness in my paths.

9 He has stripped me of my glory,

and taken the crown from my head.

10 He has broken me down on every side, and I am gone.

He has plucked my hope up like a tree.

11 He has also kindled his wrath against me.

He counts me among his adversaries.

12 His troops come on together,

build a siege ramp against me,

and encamp around my tent.

13 “He has put my brothers far from me.

My acquaintances are wholly estranged from me.

14 My relatives have gone away.

My familiar friends have forgotten me.

15 Those who dwell in my house and my maids consider me a stranger.

I am an alien in their sight.

16 I call to my servant, and he gives me no answer.

I beg him with my mouth.

17 My breath is offensive to my wife.

I am loathsome to the children of my own mother.

18 Even young children despise me.

If I arise, they speak against me.

19 All my familiar friends abhor me.

They whom I loved have turned against me.

20 My bones stick to my skin and to my flesh.

I have escaped by the skin of my teeth.

21 “Have pity on me. Have pity on me, you my friends,

for the hand of God has touched me.

22 Why do you persecute me as God,

and are not satisfied with my flesh?

23 “Oh that my words were now written!

Oh that they were inscribed in a book!

24 That with an iron pen and lead

they were engraved in the rock forever!

25 But as for me, I know that my Redeemer lives.

In the end, he will stand upon the earth.

26 After my skin is destroyed,

then I will see God in my flesh,

27 whom I, even I, will see on my side.

My eyes will see, and not as a stranger.

“My heart is consumed within me.

28 If you say, ‘How we will persecute him!’

because the root of the matter is found in me,

29 be afraid of the sword,

for wrath brings the punishments of the sword,

that you may know there is a judgment.”

20

1 Then Zophar the Naamathite answered,

2 “Therefore my thoughts answer me,

even by reason of my haste that is in me.

3 I have heard the reproof which puts me to shame.

The spirit of my understanding answers me.

4 Don’t you know this from old time,

since man was placed on earth,

5 that the triumphing of the wicked is short,

the joy of the godless but for a moment?

6 Though his height mount up to the heavens,

and his head reach to the clouds,

7 yet he will perish forever like his own dung.

Those who have seen him will say, ‘Where is he?’

8 He will fly away as a dream, and will not be found.

Yes, he will be chased away like a vision of the night.

9 The eye which saw him will see him no more,

neither will his place see him any more.

10 His children will seek the favor of the poor.

His hands will give back his wealth.

11 His bones are full of his youth,

but youth will lie down with him in the dust.

12 “Though wickedness is sweet in his mouth,

though he hide it under his tongue,

13 though he spare it, and will not let it go,

but keep it still within his mouth,

14 yet his food in his bowels is turned.

It is cobra venom within him.

15 He has swallowed down riches, and he will vomit them up again.

God will cast them out of his belly.

16 He will suck cobra venom.

The viper’s tongue will kill him.

17 He will not look at the rivers,

the flowing streams of honey and butter.

18  He will restore that for which he labored, and will not swallow it down.

He will not rejoice according to the substance that he has gotten.

19 For he has oppressed and forsaken the poor.

He has violently taken away a house, and he will not build it up.

20 “Because he knew no quietness within him,

he will not save anything of that in which he delights.

21 There was nothing left that he didn’t devour,

therefore his prosperity will not endure.

22 In the fullness of his sufficiency, distress will overtake him.

The hand of everyone who is in misery will come on him.

23 When he is about to fill his belly, God will cast the fierceness of his wrath on him.

It will rain on him while he is eating.

24 He will flee from the iron weapon.

The bronze arrow will strike him through.

25 He draws it out, and it comes out of his body.

Yes, the glittering point comes out of his liver.

Terrors are on him.

26 All darkness is laid up for his treasures.

An unfanned fire will devour him.

It will consume that which is left in his tent.

27 The heavens will reveal his iniquity.

The earth will rise up against him.

28 The increase of his house will depart.

They will rush away in the day of his wrath.

29 This is the portion of a wicked man from God,

the heritage appointed to him by God.”

21

1 Then Job answered,

2 “Listen diligently to my speech.

Let this be your consolation.

3 Allow me, and I also will speak.

After I have spoken, mock on.

4 As for me, is my complaint to man?

Why shouldn’t I be impatient?

5 Look at me, and be astonished.

Lay your hand on your mouth.

6 When I remember, I am troubled.

Horror takes hold of my flesh.

7 “Why do the wicked live,

become old, yes, and grow mighty in power?

8 Their child is established with them in their sight,

their offspring before their eyes.

9 Their houses are safe from fear,

neither is the rod of God upon them.

10 Their bulls breed without fail.

Their cows calve, and don’t miscarry.

11 They send out their little ones like a flock.

Their children dance.

12 They sing to the tambourine and harp,

and rejoice at the sound of the pipe.

13 They spend their days in prosperity.

In an instant they go down to Sheol.[*]

14 They tell God, ‘Depart from us,

for we don’t want to know about your ways.

15 What is the Almighty, that we should serve him?

What profit should we have, if we pray to him?’

16 Behold, their prosperity is not in their hand.

The counsel of the wicked is far from me.

17 “How often is it that the lamp of the wicked is put out,

that their calamity comes on them,

that God distributes sorrows in his anger?

18 How often is it that they are as stubble before the wind,

as chaff that the storm carries away?

19 You say, ‘God lays up his iniquity for his children.’

Let him recompense it to himself, that he may know it.

20 Let his own eyes see his destruction.

Let him drink of the wrath of the Almighty.

21 For what does he care for his house after him,

when the number of his months is cut off?

22 “Shall any teach God knowledge,

since he judges those who are high?

23 One dies in his full strength,

being wholly at ease and quiet.

24 His pails are full of milk.

The marrow of his bones is moistened.

25 Another dies in bitterness of soul,

and never tastes of good.

26 They lie down alike in the dust.

The worm covers them.

27 “Behold, I know your thoughts,

the plans with which you would wrong me.

28 For you say, ‘Where is the house of the prince?

Where is the tent in which the wicked lived?’

29 Haven’t you asked wayfaring men?

Don’t you know their evidences,

30 that the evil man is reserved to the day of calamity,

that they are led out to the day of wrath?

31 Who will declare his way to his face?

Who will repay him what he has done?

32 Yet he will be borne to the grave.

Men will keep watch over the tomb.

33 The clods of the valley will be sweet to him.

All men will draw after him,

as there were innumerable before him.

34 So how can you comfort me with nonsense,

because in your answers there remains only falsehood?”

22

1 Then Eliphaz the Temanite answered,

2 “Can a man be profitable to God?

Surely he who is wise is profitable to himself.

3 Is it any pleasure to the Almighty that you are righteous?

Or does it benefit him that you make your ways perfect?

4 Is it for your piety that he reproves you,

that he enters with you into judgment?

5 Isn’t your wickedness great?

Neither is there any end to your iniquities.

6 For you have taken pledges from your brother for nothing,

and stripped the naked of their clothing.

7 You haven’t given water to the weary to drink,

and you have withheld bread from the hungry.

8 But as for the mighty man, he had the earth.

The honorable man, he lived in it.

9 You have sent widows away empty,

and the arms of the fatherless have been broken.

10 Therefore snares are around you.

Sudden fear troubles you,

11 or darkness, so that you can not see,

and floods of waters cover you.

12 “Isn’t God in the heights of heaven?

See the height of the stars, how high they are!

13 You say, ‘What does God know?

Can he judge through the thick darkness?

14 Thick clouds are a covering to him, so that he doesn’t see.

He walks on the vault of the sky.’

15 Will you keep the old way,

which wicked men have trodden,

16 who were snatched away before their time,

whose foundation was poured out as a stream,

17 who said to God, ‘Depart from us!’

and, ‘What can the Almighty do for us?’

18 Yet he filled their houses with good things,

but the counsel of the wicked is far from me.

19 The righteous see it, and are glad.

The innocent ridicule them,

20 saying, ‘Surely those who rose up against us are cut off.

The fire has consumed their remnant.’

21 “Acquaint yourself with him now, and be at peace.

By it, good will come to you.

22 Please receive instruction from his mouth,

and lay up his words in your heart.

23 If you return to the Almighty, you will be built up,

if you put away unrighteousness far from your tents.

24 Lay your treasure in the dust,

the gold of Ophir among the stones of the brooks.

25 The Almighty will be your treasure,

and precious silver to you.

26 For then you will delight yourself in the Almighty,

and will lift up your face to God.

27 You will make your prayer to him, and he will hear you.

You will pay your vows.

28 You will also decree a thing, and it will be established to you.

Light will shine on your ways.

29 When they cast down, you will say, ‘be lifted up.’

He will save the humble person.

30 He will even deliver him who is not innocent.

Yes, he will be delivered through the cleanness of your hands.”

23

1 Then Job answered,

2 “Even today my complaint is rebellious.

His hand is heavy in spite of my groaning.

3 Oh that I knew where I might find him!

That I might come even to his seat!

4 I would set my cause in order before him,

and fill my mouth with arguments.

5 I would know the words which he would answer me,

and understand what he would tell me.

6 Would he contend with me in the greatness of his power?

No, but he would listen to me.

7 There the upright might reason with him,

so I should be delivered forever from my judge.

8 “If I go east, he is not there.

If I go west, I can’t find him.

9 He works to the north, but I can’t see him.

He turns south, but I can’t catch a glimpse of him.

10 But he knows the way that I take.

When he has tried me, I will come out like gold.

11 My foot has held fast to his steps.

I have kept his way, and not turned away.

12 I haven’t gone back from the commandment of his lips.

I have treasured up the words of his mouth more than my necessary food.

13 But he stands alone, and who can oppose him?

What his soul desires, even that he does.

14 For he performs that which is appointed for me.

Many such things are with him.

15 Therefore I am terrified at his presence.

When I consider, I am afraid of him.

16 For God has made my heart faint.

The Almighty has terrified me.

17 Because I was not cut off before the darkness,

neither did he cover the thick darkness from my face.

24

1 “Why aren’t times laid up by the Almighty?

Why don’t those who know him see his days?

2 There are people who remove the landmarks.

They violently take away flocks, and feed them.

3 They drive away the donkey of the fatherless,

and they take the widow’s ox for a pledge.

4 They turn the needy out of the way.

The poor of the earth all hide themselves.

5 Behold, as wild donkeys in the desert,

they go out to their work, seeking diligently for food.

The wilderness yields them bread for their children.

6 They cut their food in the field.

They glean the vineyard of the wicked.

7 They lie all night naked without clothing,

and have no covering in the cold.

8 They are wet with the showers of the mountains,

and embrace the rock for lack of a shelter.

9 There are those who pluck the fatherless from the breast,

and take a pledge of the poor,

10 so that they go around naked without clothing.

Being hungry, they carry the sheaves.

11 They make oil within the walls of these men.

They tread wine presses, and suffer thirst.

12 From out of the populous city, men groan.

The soul of the wounded cries out,

yet God doesn’t regard the folly.

13 “These are of those who rebel against the light.

They don’t know its ways,

nor stay in its paths.

14 The murderer rises with the light.

He kills the poor and needy.

In the night he is like a thief.

15 The eye also of the adulterer waits for the twilight,

saying, ‘No eye will see me.’

He disguises his face.

16 In the dark they dig through houses.

They shut themselves up in the daytime.

They don’t know the light.

17 For the morning is to all of them like thick darkness,

for they know the terrors of the thick darkness.

18 “They are foam on the surface of the waters.

Their portion is cursed in the earth.

They don’t turn into the way of the vineyards.

19 Drought and heat consume the snow waters,

so does Sheol[*] those who have sinned.

20 The womb will forget him.

The worm will feed sweetly on him.

He will be no more remembered.

Unrighteousness will be broken as a tree.

21 He devours the barren who don’t bear.

He shows no kindness to the widow.

22 Yet God preserves the mighty by his power.

He rises up who has no assurance of life.

23 God gives them security, and they rest in it.

His eyes are on their ways.

24 They are exalted; yet a little while, and they are gone.

Yes, they are brought low, they are taken out of the way as all others,

and are cut off as the tops of the ears of grain.

25 If it isn’t so now, who will prove me a liar,

and make my speech worth nothing?”

25

1 Then Bildad the Shuhite answered,

2 “Dominion and fear are with him.

He makes peace in his high places.

3 Can his armies be counted?

On whom does his light not arise?

4 How then can man be just with God?

Or how can he who is born of a woman be clean?

5 Behold, even the moon has no brightness,

and the stars are not pure in his sight;

6 How much less man, who is a worm,

and the son of man, who is a worm!”

26

1 Then Job answered,

2 “How have you helped him who is without power!

How have you saved the arm that has no strength!

3 How have you counseled him who has no wisdom,

and plentifully declared sound knowledge!

4 To whom have you uttered words?

Whose spirit came out of you?

5 “The departed spirits tremble,

those beneath the waters and all that live in them.

6 Sheol[*] is naked before God,

and Abaddon[†] has no covering.

7 He stretches out the north over empty space,

and hangs the earth on nothing.

8 He binds up the waters in his thick clouds,

and the cloud is not burst under them.

9 He encloses the face of his throne,

and spreads his cloud on it.

10 He has described a boundary on the surface of the waters,

and to the confines of light and darkness.

11 The pillars of heaven tremble

and are astonished at his rebuke.

12 He stirs up the sea with his power,

and by his understanding he strikes through Rahab.

13 By his Spirit the heavens are garnished.

His hand has pierced the swift serpent.

14 Behold, these are but the outskirts of his ways.

How small a whisper do we hear of him!

But the thunder of his power who can understand?”

27

1 Job again took up his parable, and said,

2 “As God lives, who has taken away my right,

the Almighty, who has made my soul bitter

3 (for the length of my life is still in me,

and the spirit of God is in my nostrils);

4 surely my lips will not speak unrighteousness,

neither will my tongue utter deceit.

5 Far be it from me that I should justify you.

Until I die I will not put away my integrity from me.

6 I hold fast to my righteousness, and will not let it go.

My heart will not reproach me so long as I live.

7 “Let my enemy be as the wicked.

Let him who rises up against me be as the unrighteous.

8 For what is the hope of the godless, when he is cut off,

when God takes away his life?

9 Will God hear his cry when trouble comes on him?

10 Will he delight himself in the Almighty,

and call on God at all times?

11 I will teach you about the hand of God.

I will not conceal that which is with the Almighty.

12 Behold, all of you have seen it yourselves;

why then have you become altogether vain?

13 “This is the portion of a wicked man with God,

the heritage of oppressors, which they receive from the Almighty.

14 If his children are multiplied, it is for the sword.

His offspring will not be satisfied with bread.

15 Those who remain of him will be buried in death.

His widows will make no lamentation.

16 Though he heap up silver as the dust,

and prepare clothing as the clay;

17 he may prepare it, but the just will put it on,

and the innocent will divide the silver.

18 He builds his house as the moth,

as a booth which the watchman makes.

19 He lies down rich, but he will not do so again.

He opens his eyes, and he is not.

20 Terrors overtake him like waters.

A storm steals him away in the night.

21 The east wind carries him away, and he departs.

It sweeps him out of his place.

22 For it hurls at him, and does not spare,

as he flees away from his hand.

23 Men will clap their hands at him,

and will hiss him out of his place.

28

1 “Surely there is a mine for silver,

and a place for gold which they refine.

2 Iron is taken out of the earth,

and copper is smelted out of the ore.

3 Man sets an end to darkness,

and searches out, to the furthest bound,

the stones of obscurity and of thick darkness.

4 He breaks open a shaft away from where people live.

They are forgotten by the foot.

They hang far from men, they swing back and forth.

5 As for the earth, out of it comes bread.

Underneath it is turned up as it were by fire.

6 Sapphires come from its rocks.

It has dust of gold.

7 That path no bird of prey knows,

neither has the falcon’s eye seen it.

8 The proud animals have not trodden it,

nor has the fierce lion passed by there.

9 He puts his hand on the flinty rock,

and he overturns the mountains by the roots.

10 He cuts out channels among the rocks.

His eye sees every precious thing.

11 He binds the streams that they don’t trickle.

The thing that is hidden he brings out to light.

12 “But where will wisdom be found?

Where is the place of understanding?

13 Man doesn’t know its price,

and it isn’t found in the land of the living.

14 The deep says, ‘It isn’t in me.’

The sea says, ‘It isn’t with me.’

15 It can’t be gotten for gold,

neither will silver be weighed for its price.

16 It can’t be valued with the gold of Ophir,

with the precious onyx, or the sapphire.[*]

17 Gold and glass can’t equal it,

neither will it be exchanged for jewels of fine gold.

18 No mention will be made of coral or of crystal.

Yes, the price of wisdom is above rubies.

19 The topaz of Ethiopia will not equal it.

It won’t be valued with pure gold.

20 Where then does wisdom come from?

Where is the place of understanding?

21 Seeing it is hidden from the eyes of all living,

and kept close from the birds of the sky.

22 Destruction and Death say,

‘We have heard a rumor of it with our ears.’

23 “God understands its way,

and he knows its place.

24 For he looks to the ends of the earth,

and sees under the whole sky.

25 He establishes the force of the wind.

Yes, he measures out the waters by measure.

26 When he made a decree for the rain,

and a way for the lightning of the thunder,

27 then he saw it, and declared it.

He established it, yes, and searched it out.

28 To man he said,

‘Behold, the fear of the Lord,[†] that is wisdom.

To depart from evil is understanding.’ ”

29

1 Job again took up his parable, and said,

2 “Oh that I were as in the months of old,

as in the days when God watched over me;

3 when his lamp shone on my head,

and by his light I walked through darkness,

4 as I was in my prime,

when the friendship of God was in my tent,

5 when the Almighty was yet with me,

and my children were around me,

6 when my steps were washed with butter,

and the rock poured out streams of oil for me,

7 when I went out to the city gate,

when I prepared my seat in the street.

8 The young men saw me and hid themselves.

The aged rose up and stood.

9 The princes refrained from talking,

and laid their hand on their mouth.

10 The voice of the nobles was hushed,

and their tongue stuck to the roof of their mouth.

11 For when the ear heard me, then it blessed me,

and when the eye saw me, it commended me,

12 because I delivered the poor who cried,

and the fatherless also, who had no one to help him,

13 the blessing of him who was ready to perish came on me,

and I caused the widow’s heart to sing for joy.

14 I put on righteousness, and it clothed me.

My justice was as a robe and a diadem.

15 I was eyes to the blind,

and feet to the lame.

16 I was a father to the needy.

I researched the cause of him whom I didn’t know.

17 I broke the jaws of the unrighteous

and plucked the prey out of his teeth.

18 Then I said, ‘I will die in my own house,

I will count my days as the sand.

19 My root is spread out to the waters.

The dew lies all night on my branch.

20 My glory is fresh in me.

My bow is renewed in my hand.’

21 “Men listened to me, waited,

and kept silence for my counsel.

22 After my words they didn’t speak again.

My speech fell on them.

23 They waited for me as for the rain.

Their mouths drank as with the spring rain.

24 I smiled on them when they had no confidence.

They didn’t reject the light of my face.

25 I chose out their way, and sat as chief.

I lived as a king in the army,

as one who comforts the mourners.

30

1 “But now those who are younger than I have me in derision,

whose fathers I considered unworthy to put with my sheep dogs.

2 Of what use is the strength of their hands to me,

men in whom ripe age has perished?

3 They are gaunt from lack and famine.

They gnaw the dry ground, in the gloom of waste and desolation.

4 They pluck salt herbs by the bushes.

The roots of the broom tree are their food.

5 They are driven out from among men.

They cry after them as after a thief,

6 so that they live in frightful valleys,

and in holes of the earth and of the rocks.

7 They bray among the bushes.

They are gathered together under the nettles.

8 They are children of fools, yes, children of wicked men.

They were flogged out of the land.

9 “Now I have become their song.

Yes, I am a byword to them.

10 They abhor me, they stand aloof from me,

and don’t hesitate to spit in my face.

11 For he has untied his cord, and afflicted me;

and they have thrown off restraint before me.

12 On my right hand rise the rabble.

They thrust aside my feet.

They cast their ways of destruction up against me.

13 They mar my path.

They promote my destruction

without anyone’s help.

14 As through a wide breach they come.

They roll themselves in amid the ruin.

15 Terrors have turned on me.

They chase my honor as the wind.

My welfare has passed away as a cloud.

16 “Now my soul is poured out within me.

Days of affliction have taken hold of me.

17 In the night season my bones are pierced in me,

and the pains that gnaw me take no rest.

18 My garment is disfigured by great force.

It binds me about as the collar of my tunic.

19 He has cast me into the mire.

I have become like dust and ashes.

20 I cry to you, and you do not answer me.

I stand up, and you gaze at me.

21 You have turned to be cruel to me.

With the might of your hand you persecute me.

22 You lift me up to the wind, and drive me with it.

You dissolve me in the storm.

23 For I know that you will bring me to death,

to the house appointed for all living.

24 “However doesn’t one stretch out a hand in his fall?

Or in his calamity therefore cry for help?

25 Didn’t I weep for him who was in trouble?

Wasn’t my soul grieved for the needy?

26 When I looked for good, then evil came.

When I waited for light, darkness came.

27 My heart is troubled, and doesn’t rest.

Days of affliction have come on me.

28 I go mourning without the sun.

I stand up in the assembly, and cry for help.

29 I am a brother to jackals,

and a companion to ostriches.

30 My skin grows black and peels from me.

My bones are burned with heat.

31 Therefore my harp has turned to mourning,

and my pipe into the voice of those who weep.

31

1 “I made a covenant with my eyes;

how then should I look lustfully at a young woman?

2 For what is the portion from God above,

and the heritage from the Almighty on high?

3 Is it not calamity to the unrighteous,

and disaster to the workers of iniquity?

4 Doesn’t he see my ways,

and count all my steps?

5 “If I have walked with falsehood,

and my foot has hurried to deceit

6 (let me be weighed in an even balance,

that God may know my integrity);

7 if my step has turned out of the way,

if my heart walked after my eyes,

if any defilement has stuck to my hands,

8 then let me sow, and let another eat.

Yes, let the produce of my field be rooted out.

9 “If my heart has been enticed to a woman,

and I have laid wait at my neighbor’s door,

10 then let my wife grind for another,

and let others sleep with her.

11 For that would be a heinous crime.

Yes, it would be an iniquity to be punished by the judges,

12 for it is a fire that consumes to destruction,

and would root out all my increase.

13 “If I have despised the cause of my male servant

or of my female servant,

when they contended with me,

14 what then will I do when God rises up?

When he visits, what will I answer him?

15 Didn’t he who made me in the womb make him?

Didn’t one fashion us in the womb?

16 “If I have withheld the poor from their desire,

or have caused the eyes of the widow to fail,

17 or have eaten my morsel alone,

and the fatherless has not eaten of it

18 (no, from my youth he grew up with me as with a father,

I have guided her from my mother’s womb);

19 if I have seen any perish for want of clothing,

or that the needy had no covering;

20 if his heart hasn’t blessed me,

if he hasn’t been warmed with my sheep’s fleece;

21 if I have lifted up my hand against the fatherless,

because I saw my help in the gate;

22 then let my shoulder fall from the shoulder blade,

and my arm be broken from the bone.

23 For calamity from God is a terror to me.

Because of his majesty, I can do nothing.

24 “If I have made gold my hope,

and have said to the fine gold, ‘You are my confidence;’

25 If I have rejoiced because my wealth was great,

and because my hand had gotten much;

26 if I have seen the sun when it shined,

or the moon moving in splendor,

27 and my heart has been secretly enticed,

and my hand threw a kiss from my mouth;

28 this also would be an iniquity to be punished by the judges,

for I should have denied the God who is above.

29 “If I have rejoiced at the destruction of him who hated me,

or lifted up myself when evil found him

30 (I have certainly not allowed my mouth to sin

by asking his life with a curse);

31 if the men of my tent have not said,

‘Who can find one who has not been filled with his meat?’

32 (the foreigner has not camped in the street,

but I have opened my doors to the traveler);

33 if like Adam I have covered my transgressions,

by hiding my iniquity in my heart,

34 because I feared the great multitude,

and the contempt of families terrified me,

so that I kept silence, and didn’t go out of the door—

35 oh that I had one to hear me!

Behold, here is my signature! Let the Almighty answer me!

Let the accuser write my indictment!

36 Surely I would carry it on my shoulder,

and I would bind it to me as a crown.

37 I would declare to him the number of my steps.

I would go near to him like a prince.

38 If my land cries out against me,

and its furrows weep together;

39 if I have eaten its fruits without money,

or have caused its owners to lose their life,

40 let briers grow instead of wheat,

and stinkweed instead of barley.”

The words of Job are ended.

32

1 So these three men ceased to answer Job, because he was righteous in his own eyes. 2 Then the wrath of Elihu the son of Barachel, the Buzite, of the family of Ram, was kindled against Job. His wrath was kindled because he justified himself rather than God. 3 Also his wrath was kindled against his three friends, because they had found no answer, and yet had condemned Job. 4 Now Elihu had waited to speak to Job, because they were elder than he. 5 When Elihu saw that there was no answer in the mouth of these three men, his wrath was kindled.

6 Elihu the son of Barachel the Buzite answered,

“I am young, and you are very old.

Therefore I held back, and didn’t dare show you my opinion.

7 I said, ‘Days should speak,

and multitude of years should teach wisdom.’

8 But there is a spirit in man,

and the Spirit[*] of the Almighty gives them understanding.

9 It is not the great who are wise,

nor the aged who understand justice.

10 Therefore I said, ‘Listen to me;

I also will show my opinion.’

11 “Behold, I waited for your words,

and I listened for your reasoning,

while you searched out what to say.

12 Yes, I gave you my full attention,

but there was no one who convinced Job,

or who answered his words, among you.

13 Beware lest you say, ‘We have found wisdom.

God may refute him, not man;’

14 for he has not directed his words against me;

neither will I answer him with your speeches.

15 “They are amazed. They answer no more.

They don’t have a word to say.

16 Shall I wait, because they don’t speak,

because they stand still, and answer no more?

17 I also will answer my part,

and I also will show my opinion.

18 For I am full of words.

The spirit within me constrains me.

19 Behold, my breast is as wine which has no vent;

like new wineskins it is ready to burst.

20 I will speak, that I may be refreshed.

I will open my lips and answer.

21 Please don’t let me respect any man’s person,

neither will I give flattering titles to any man.

22 For I don’t know how to give flattering titles,

or else my Maker would soon take me away.

33

1 “However, Job, please hear my speech,

and listen to all my words.

2 See now, I have opened my mouth.

My tongue has spoken in my mouth.

3 My words will utter the uprightness of my heart.

That which my lips know they will speak sincerely.

4 The Spirit of God has made me,

and the breath of the Almighty gives me life.

5 If you can, answer me.

Set your words in order before me, and stand up.

6 Behold, I am toward God even as you are.

I am also formed out of the clay.

7 Behold, my terror will not make you afraid,

neither will my pressure be heavy on you.

8 “Surely you have spoken in my hearing,

I have heard the voice of your words, saying,

9 ‘I am clean, without disobedience.

I am innocent, neither is there iniquity in me.

10 Behold, he finds occasions against me.

He counts me for his enemy.

11 He puts my feet in the stocks.

He marks all my paths.’

12 “Behold, I will answer you. In this you are not just,

for God is greater than man.

13 Why do you strive against him,

because he doesn’t give account of any of his matters?

14 For God speaks once,

yes twice, though man pays no attention.

15 In a dream, in a vision of the night,

when deep sleep falls on men,

in slumbering on the bed,

16 then he opens the ears of men,

and seals their instruction,

17 that he may withdraw man from his purpose,

and hide pride from man.

18 He keeps back his soul from the pit,

and his life from perishing by the sword.

19 “He is chastened also with pain on his bed,

with continual strife in his bones,

20 so that his life abhors bread,

and his soul dainty food.

21 His flesh is so consumed away that it can’t be seen.

His bones that were not seen stick out.

22 Yes, his soul draws near to the pit,

and his life to the destroyers.

23 “If there is beside him an angel,

an interpreter, one among a thousand,

to show to man what is right for him,

24 then God is gracious to him, and says,

‘Deliver him from going down to the pit,

I have found a ransom.’

25 His flesh will be fresher than a child’s.

He returns to the days of his youth.

26 He prays to God, and he is favorable to him,

so that he sees his face with joy.

He restores to man his righteousness.

27 He sings before men, and says,

‘I have sinned, and perverted that which was right,

and it didn’t profit me.

28 He has redeemed my soul from going into the pit.

My life will see the light.’

29 “Behold, God does all these things,

twice, yes three times, with a man,

30 to bring back his soul from the pit,

that he may be enlightened with the light of the living.

31 Mark well, Job, and listen to me.

Hold your peace, and I will speak.

32 If you have anything to say, answer me.

Speak, for I desire to justify you.

33 If not, listen to me.

Hold your peace, and I will teach you wisdom.”

34

1 Moreover Elihu answered,

2 “Hear my words, you wise men.

Give ear to me, you who have knowledge.

3 For the ear tries words,

as the palate tastes food.

4 Let us choose for us that which is right.

Let us know among ourselves what is good.

5 For Job has said, ‘I am righteous,

God has taken away my right.

6 Notwithstanding my right I am considered a liar.

My wound is incurable, though I am without disobedience.’

7 What man is like Job,

who drinks scorn like water,

8 who goes in company with the workers of iniquity,

and walks with wicked men?

9 For he has said, ‘It profits a man nothing

that he should delight himself with God.’

10 “Therefore listen to me, you men of understanding:

far be it from God, that he should do wickedness,

from the Almighty, that he should commit iniquity.

11 For the work of a man he will render to him,

and cause every man to find according to his ways.

12 Yes surely, God will not do wickedly,

neither will the Almighty pervert justice.

13 Who put him in charge of the earth?

Or who has appointed him over the whole world?

14 If he set his heart on himself,

if he gathered to himself his spirit and his breath,

15 all flesh would perish together,

and man would turn again to dust.

16 “If now you have understanding, hear this.

Listen to the voice of my words.

17 Should even one who hates justice govern?

Will you condemn him who is righteous and mighty,

18 who says to a king, ‘Vile!’

or to nobles, ‘Wicked!’?

19 He doesn’t respect the persons of princes,

nor respect the rich more than the poor,

for they all are the work of his hands.

20 In a moment they die, even at midnight.

The people are shaken and pass away.

The mighty are taken away without a hand.

21 “For his eyes are on the ways of a man.

He sees all his goings.

22 There is no darkness, nor thick gloom,

where the workers of iniquity may hide themselves.

23 For he doesn’t need to consider a man further,

that he should go before God in judgment.

24 He breaks mighty men in pieces in ways past finding out,

and sets others in their place.

25 Therefore he takes knowledge of their works.

He overturns them in the night, so that they are destroyed.

26 He strikes them as wicked men

in the open sight of others;

27 because they turned away from following him,

and wouldn’t pay attention to any of his ways,

28 so that they caused the cry of the poor to come to him.

He heard the cry of the afflicted.

29 When he gives quietness, who then can condemn?

When he hides his face, who then can see him?

He is over a nation or a man alike,

30 that the godless man may not reign,

that there be no one to ensnare the people.

31 “For has any said to God,

‘I am guilty, but I will not offend any more.

32 Teach me that which I don’t see.

If I have done iniquity, I will do it no more’?

33 Shall his recompense be as you desire, that you refuse it?

For you must choose, and not I.

Therefore speak what you know.

34 Men of understanding will tell me,

yes, every wise man who hears me:

35 ‘Job speaks without knowledge.

His words are without wisdom.’

36 I wish that Job were tried to the end,

because of his answering like wicked men.

37 For he adds rebellion to his sin.

He claps his hands among us,

and multiplies his words against God.”

35

1 Moreover Elihu answered,

2 “Do you think this to be your right,

or do you say, ‘My righteousness is more than God’s,’

3 that you ask, ‘What advantage will it be to you?

What profit will I have, more than if I had sinned?’

4 I will answer you,

and your companions with you.

5 Look to the skies, and see.

See the skies, which are higher than you.

6 If you have sinned, what effect do you have against him?

If your transgressions are multiplied, what do you do to him?

7 If you are righteous, what do you give him?

Or what does he receive from your hand?

8 Your wickedness may hurt a man as you are,

and your righteousness may profit a son of man.

9 “By reason of the multitude of oppressions they cry out.

They cry for help by reason of the arm of the mighty.

10 But no one says, ‘Where is God my Maker,

who gives songs in the night,

11 who teaches us more than the animals of the earth,

and makes us wiser than the birds of the sky?’

12 There they cry, but no one answers,

because of the pride of evil men.

13 Surely God will not hear an empty cry,

neither will the Almighty regard it.

14 How much less when you say you don’t see him.

The cause is before him, and you wait for him!

15 But now, because he has not visited in his anger,

neither does he greatly regard arrogance,

16 therefore Job opens his mouth with empty talk,

and he multiplies words without knowledge.”

36

1 Elihu also continued, and said,

2 “Bear with me a little, and I will show you;

for I still have something to say on God’s behalf.

3 I will get my knowledge from afar,

and will ascribe righteousness to my Maker.

4 For truly my words are not false.

One who is perfect in knowledge is with you.

5 “Behold, God is mighty, and doesn’t despise anyone.

He is mighty in strength of understanding.

6 He doesn’t preserve the life of the wicked,

but gives justice to the afflicted.

7 He doesn’t withdraw his eyes from the righteous,

but with kings on the throne,

he sets them forever, and they are exalted.

8 If they are bound in fetters,

and are taken in the cords of afflictions,

9 then he shows them their work,

and their transgressions, that they have behaved themselves proudly.

10 He also opens their ears to instruction,

and commands that they return from iniquity.

11 If they listen and serve him,

they will spend their days in prosperity,

and their years in pleasures.

12 But if they don’t listen, they will perish by the sword;

they will die without knowledge.

13 “But those who are godless in heart lay up anger.

They don’t cry for help when he binds them.

14 They die in youth.

Their life perishes among the unclean.

15 He delivers the afflicted by their affliction,

and opens their ear in oppression.

16 Yes, he would have allured you out of distress,

into a wide place, where there is no restriction.

That which is set on your table would be full of fatness.

17 “But you are full of the judgment of the wicked.

Judgment and justice take hold of you.

18 Don’t let riches entice you to wrath,

neither let the great size of a bribe turn you aside.

19 Would your wealth sustain you in distress,

or all the might of your strength?

20 Don’t desire the night,

when people are cut off in their place.

21 Take heed, don’t regard iniquity;

for you have chosen this rather than affliction.

22 Behold, God is exalted in his power.

Who is a teacher like him?

23 Who has prescribed his way for him?

Or who can say, ‘You have committed unrighteousness?’

24 “Remember that you magnify his work,

about which men have sung.

25 All men have looked on it.

Man sees it afar off.

26 Behold, God is great, and we don’t know him.

The number of his years is unsearchable.

27 For he draws up the drops of water,

which distill in rain from his vapor,

28 which the skies pour down

and which drop on man abundantly.

29 Indeed, can anyone understand the spreading of the clouds

and the thunderings of his pavilion?

30 Behold, he spreads his light around him.

He covers the bottom of the sea.

31 For by these he judges the people.

He gives food in abundance.

32 He covers his hands with the lightning,

and commands it to strike the mark.

33 Its noise tells about him,

and the livestock also, concerning the storm that comes up.

37

1 “Yes, at this my heart trembles,

and is moved out of its place.

2 Hear, oh, hear the noise of his voice,

the sound that goes out of his mouth.

3 He sends it out under the whole sky,

and his lightning to the ends of the earth.

4 After it a voice roars.

He thunders with the voice of his majesty.

He doesn’t hold back anything when his voice is heard.

5 God thunders marvelously with his voice.

He does great things, which we can’t comprehend.

6 For he says to the snow, ‘Fall on the earth,’

likewise to the shower of rain,

and to the showers of his mighty rain.

7 He seals up the hand of every man,

that all men whom he has made may know it.

8 Then the animals take cover,

and remain in their dens.

9 Out of its room comes the storm,

and cold out of the north.

10 By the breath of God, ice is given,

and the width of the waters is frozen.

11 Yes, he loads the thick cloud with moisture.

He spreads abroad the cloud of his lightning.

12 It is turned around by his guidance,

that they may do whatever he commands them

on the surface of the habitable world,

13 whether it is for correction, or for his land,

or for loving kindness, that he causes it to come.

14 “Listen to this, Job.

Stand still, and consider the wondrous works of God.

15 Do you know how God controls them,

and causes the lightning of his cloud to shine?

16 Do you know the workings of the clouds,

the wondrous works of him who is perfect in knowledge?

17 You whose clothing is warm

when the earth is still by reason of the south wind?

18 Can you, with him, spread out the sky,

which is strong as a cast metal mirror?

19 Teach us what we will tell him,

for we can’t make our case by reason of darkness.

20 Will it be told him that I would speak?

Or should a man wish that he were swallowed up?

21 Now men don’t see the light which is bright in the skies,

but the wind passes, and clears them.

22 Out of the north comes golden splendor.

With God is awesome majesty.

23 We can’t reach the Almighty.

He is exalted in power.

In justice and great righteousness, he will not oppress.

24 Therefore men revere him.

He doesn’t regard any who are wise of heart.”

38

1 Then Yahweh answered Job out of the whirlwind,

2 “Who is this who darkens counsel

by words without knowledge?

3 Brace yourself like a man,

for I will question you, then you answer me!

4 “Where were you when I laid the foundations of the earth?

Declare, if you have understanding.

5 Who determined its measures, if you know?

Or who stretched the line on it?

6 What were its foundations fastened on?

Or who laid its cornerstone,

7 when the morning stars sang together,

and all the sons of God shouted for joy?

8 “Or who shut up the sea with doors,

when it broke out of the womb,

9 when I made clouds its garment,

and wrapped it in thick darkness,

10 marked out for it my bound,

set bars and doors,

11 and said, ‘You may come here, but no further.

Your proud waves shall be stopped here’?

12 “Have you commanded the morning in your days,

and caused the dawn to know its place,

13 that it might take hold of the ends of the earth,

and shake the wicked out of it?

14 It is changed as clay under the seal,

and presented as a garment.

15 From the wicked, their light is withheld.

The high arm is broken.

16 “Have you entered into the springs of the sea?

Or have you walked in the recesses of the deep?

17 Have the gates of death been revealed to you?

Or have you seen the gates of the shadow of death?

18 Have you comprehended the earth in its width?

Declare, if you know it all.

19 “What is the way to the dwelling of light?

As for darkness, where is its place,

20 that you should take it to its bound,

that you should discern the paths to its house?

21 Surely you know, for you were born then,

and the number of your days is great!

22 Have you entered the storehouses of the snow,

or have you seen the storehouses of the hail,

23 which I have reserved against the time of trouble,

against the day of battle and war?

24 By what way is the lightning distributed,

or the east wind scattered on the earth?

25 Who has cut a channel for the flood water,

or the path for the thunderstorm,

26 to cause it to rain on a land where there is no man,

on the wilderness, in which there is no man,

27 to satisfy the waste and desolate ground,

to cause the tender grass to grow?

28 Does the rain have a father?

Or who fathers the drops of dew?

29 Whose womb did the ice come out of?

Who has given birth to the gray frost of the sky?

30 The waters become hard like stone,

when the surface of the deep is frozen.

31 “Can you bind the cluster of the Pleiades,

or loosen the cords of Orion?

32 Can you lead the constellations out in their season?

Or can you guide the Bear with her cubs?

33 Do you know the laws of the heavens?

Can you establish its dominion over the earth?

34 “Can you lift up your voice to the clouds,

that abundance of waters may cover you?

35 Can you send out lightnings, that they may go?

Do they report to you, ‘Here we are’?

36 Who has put wisdom in the inward parts?

Or who has given understanding to the mind?

37 Who can count the clouds by wisdom?

Or who can pour out the containers of the sky,

38 when the dust runs into a mass,

and the clods of earth stick together?

39 “Can you hunt the prey for the lioness,

or satisfy the appetite of the young lions,

40 when they crouch in their dens,

and lie in wait in the thicket?

41 Who provides for the raven his prey,

when his young ones cry to God,

and wander for lack of food?

39

1 “Do you know the time when the mountain goats give birth?

Do you watch when the doe bears fawns?

2 Can you count the months that they fulfill?

Or do you know the time when they give birth?

3 They bow themselves. They bear their young.

They end their labor pains.

4 Their young ones become strong.

They grow up in the open field.

They go out, and don’t return again.

5 “Who has set the wild donkey free?

Or who has loosened the bonds of the swift donkey,

6 whose home I have made the wilderness,

and the salt land his dwelling place?

7 He scorns the tumult of the city,

neither does he hear the shouting of the driver.

8 The range of the mountains is his pasture.

He searches after every green thing.

9 “Will the wild ox be content to serve you?

Or will he stay by your feeding trough?

10 Can you hold the wild ox in the furrow with his harness?

Or will he till the valleys after you?

11 Will you trust him, because his strength is great?

Or will you leave to him your labor?

12 Will you confide in him, that he will bring home your seed,

and gather the grain of your threshing floor?

13 “The wings of the ostrich wave proudly,

but are they the feathers and plumage of love?

14 For she leaves her eggs on the earth,

warms them in the dust,

15 and forgets that the foot may crush them,

or that the wild animal may trample them.

16 She deals harshly with her young ones, as if they were not hers.

Though her labor is in vain, she is without fear,

17 because God has deprived her of wisdom,

neither has he imparted to her understanding.

18 When she lifts up herself on high,

she scorns the horse and his rider.

19 “Have you given the horse might?

Have you clothed his neck with a quivering mane?

20 Have you made him to leap as a locust?

The glory of his snorting is awesome.

21 He paws in the valley, and rejoices in his strength.

He goes out to meet the armed men.

22 He mocks at fear, and is not dismayed,

neither does he turn back from the sword.

23 The quiver rattles against him,

the flashing spear and the javelin.

24 He eats up the ground with fierceness and rage,

neither does he stand still at the sound of the trumpet.

25 As often as the trumpet sounds he snorts, ‘Aha!’

He smells the battle afar off,

the thunder of the captains, and the shouting.

26 “Is it by your wisdom that the hawk soars,

and stretches her wings toward the south?

27 Is it at your command that the eagle mounts up,

and makes his nest on high?

28 On the cliff he dwells and makes his home,

on the point of the cliff and the stronghold.

29 From there he spies out the prey.

His eyes see it afar off.

30 His young ones also suck up blood.

Where the slain are, there he is.”

40

1 Moreover Yahweh answered Job,

2 “Shall he who argues contend with the Almighty?

He who argues with God, let him answer it.”

3 Then Job answered Yahweh,

4 “Behold, I am of small account. What will I answer you?

I lay my hand on my mouth.

5 I have spoken once, and I will not answer;

Yes, twice, but I will proceed no further.”

6 Then Yahweh answered Job out of the whirlwind:

7 “Now brace yourself like a man.

I will question you, and you will answer me.

8 Will you even annul my judgment?

Will you condemn me, that you may be justified?

9 Or do you have an arm like God?

Can you thunder with a voice like him?

10 “Now deck yourself with excellency and dignity.

Array yourself with honor and majesty.

11 Pour out the fury of your anger.

Look at everyone who is proud, and bring him low.

12 Look at everyone who is proud, and humble him.

Crush the wicked in their place.

13 Hide them in the dust together.

Bind their faces in the hidden place.

14 Then I will also admit to you

that your own right hand can save you.

15 “See now behemoth, which I made as well as you.

He eats grass as an ox.

16 Look now, his strength is in his thighs.

His force is in the muscles of his belly.

17 He moves his tail like a cedar.

The sinews of his thighs are knit together.

18 His bones are like tubes of bronze.

His limbs are like bars of iron.

19 He is the chief of the ways of God.

He who made him gives him his sword.

20 Surely the mountains produce food for him,

where all the animals of the field play.

21 He lies under the lotus trees,

in the covert of the reed, and the marsh.

22 The lotuses cover him with their shade.

The willows of the brook surround him.

23 Behold, if a river overflows, he doesn’t tremble.

He is confident, though the Jordan swells even to his mouth.

24 Shall any take him when he is on the watch,

or pierce through his nose with a snare?

41

1 “Can you draw out Leviathan[*] with a fish hook,

or press down his tongue with a cord?

2 Can you put a rope into his nose,

or pierce his jaw through with a hook?

3 Will he make many petitions to you,

or will he speak soft words to you?

4 Will he make a covenant with you,

that you should take him for a servant forever?

5 Will you play with him as with a bird?

Or will you bind him for your girls?

6 Will traders barter for him?

Will they part him among the merchants?

7 Can you fill his skin with barbed irons,

or his head with fish spears?

8 Lay your hand on him.

Remember the battle, and do so no more.

9 Behold, the hope of him is in vain.

Won’t one be cast down even at the sight of him?

10 None is so fierce that he dare stir him up.

Who then is he who can stand before me?

11 Who has first given to me, that I should repay him?

Everything under the heavens is mine.

12 “I will not keep silence concerning his limbs,

nor his mighty strength, nor his goodly frame.

13 Who can strip off his outer garment?

Who will come within his jaws?

14 Who can open the doors of his face?

Around his teeth is terror.

15 Strong scales are his pride,

shut up together with a close seal.

16 One is so near to another,

that no air can come between them.

17 They are joined to one another.

They stick together, so that they can’t be pulled apart.

18 His sneezing flashes out light.

His eyes are like the eyelids of the morning.

19 Out of his mouth go burning torches.

Sparks of fire leap out.

20 Out of his nostrils a smoke goes,

as of a boiling pot over a fire of reeds.

21 His breath kindles coals.

A flame goes out of his mouth.

22 There is strength in his neck.

Terror dances before him.

23 The flakes of his flesh are joined together.

They are firm on him.

They can’t be moved.

24 His heart is as firm as a stone,

yes, firm as the lower millstone.

25 When he raises himself up, the mighty are afraid.

They retreat before his thrashing.

26 If one attacks him with the sword, it can’t prevail;

nor the spear, the dart, nor the pointed shaft.

27 He counts iron as straw,

and bronze as rotten wood.

28 The arrow can’t make him flee.

Sling stones are like chaff to him.

29 Clubs are counted as stubble.

He laughs at the rushing of the javelin.

30 His undersides are like sharp potsherds,

leaving a trail in the mud like a threshing sledge.

31 He makes the deep to boil like a pot.

He makes the sea like a pot of ointment.

32 He makes a path shine after him.

One would think the deep had white hair.

33 On earth there is not his equal,

that is made without fear.

34 He sees everything that is high.

He is king over all the sons of pride.”

42

1 Then Job answered Yahweh:

2 “I know that you can do all things,

and that no purpose of yours can be restrained.

3 You asked, ‘Who is this who hides counsel without knowledge?’

therefore I have uttered that which I didn’t understand,

things too wonderful for me, which I didn’t know.

4 You said, ‘Listen, now, and I will speak;

I will question you, and you will answer me.’

5 I had heard of you by the hearing of the ear,

but now my eye sees you.

6 Therefore I abhor myself,

and repent in dust and ashes.”

7 It was so, that after Yahweh had spoken these words to Job, Yahweh said to Eliphaz the Temanite, “My wrath is kindled against you, and against your two friends; for you have not spoken of me the thing that is right, as my servant Job has. 8 Now therefore, take to yourselves seven bulls and seven rams, and go to my servant Job, and offer up for yourselves a burnt offering; and my servant Job shall pray for you, for I will accept him, that I not deal with you according to your folly. For you have not spoken of me the thing that is right, as my servant Job has.”

9 So Eliphaz the Temanite and Bildad the Shuhite and Zophar the Naamathite went and did what Yahweh commanded them, and Yahweh accepted Job.

10 Yahweh restored Job’s prosperity when he prayed for his friends. Yahweh gave Job twice as much as he had before. 11 Then all his brothers, all his sisters, and all those who had been of his acquaintance before, came to him and ate bread with him in his house. They comforted him, and consoled him concerning all the evil that Yahweh had brought on him. Everyone also gave him a piece of money,[*] and everyone a ring of gold.

12 So Yahweh blessed the latter end of Job more than his beginning. He had fourteen thousand sheep, six thousand camels, one thousand yoke of oxen, and a thousand female donkeys. 13 He had also seven sons and three daughters. 14 He called the name of the first, Jemimah; and the name of the second, Keziah; and the name of the third, Keren Happuch. 15 In all the land were no women found so beautiful as the daughters of Job. Their father gave them an inheritance among their brothers. 16 After this Job lived one hundred forty years, and saw his sons, and his sons’ sons, to four generations. 17 So Job died, being old and full of days.

* 1:1 The Hebrew word rendered “God” is “אֱלֹהִ֑ים” (Elohim).

† 1:6 “Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

‡ 1:12 “Behold”, from “הִנֵּה”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.

* 5:25 or, seed

* 7:9 Sheol is the place of the dead.

* 11:8 Sheol is the place of the dead.

* 14:13 Sheol is the place of the dead.

* 17:13 Sheol is the place of the dead.

† 17:16 Sheol is the place of the dead.

* 21:13 Sheol is the place of the dead.

* 24:19 Sheol is the place of the dead.

* 26:6 Sheol is the place of the dead.

† 26:6 Abaddon means Destroyer.

* 28:16 or, lapis lazuli

† 28:28 The word translated “Lord” is “Adonai.”

* 32:8 or, breath

* 41:1 Leviathan is a name for a crocodile or similar creature.

* 42:11 literally, kesitah, a unit of money, probably silver

Joel

1
2
3

The Book of

Joel

1

1 Yahweh’s[*] word that came to Joel, the son of Pethuel.

2 Hear this, you elders,

And listen, all you inhabitants of the land!

Has this ever happened in your days,

or in the days of your fathers?

3 Tell your children about it,

and have your children tell their children,

and their children, another generation.

4 What the swarming locust has left, the great locust has eaten.

What the great locust has left, the grasshopper has eaten.

What the grasshopper has left, the caterpillar has eaten.

5 Wake up, you drunkards, and weep!

Wail, all you drinkers of wine, because of the sweet wine,

for it is cut off from your mouth.

6 For a nation has come up on my land, strong, and without number.

His teeth are the teeth of a lion,

and he has the fangs of a lioness.

7 He has laid my vine waste,

and stripped my fig tree.

He has stripped its bark, and thrown it away.

Its branches are made white.

8 Mourn like a virgin dressed in sackcloth

for the husband of her youth!

9 The meal offering and the drink offering are cut off from Yahweh’s house.

The priests, Yahweh’s ministers, mourn.

10 The field is laid waste.

The land mourns, for the grain is destroyed,

The new wine has dried up,

and the oil languishes.

11 Be confounded, you farmers!

Wail, you vineyard keepers,

for the wheat and for the barley;

for the harvest of the field has perished.

12 The vine has dried up, and the fig tree withered—

the pomegranate tree, the palm tree also, and the apple tree,

even all of the trees of the field are withered;

for joy has withered away from the sons of men.

13 Put on sackcloth and mourn, you priests!

Wail, you ministers of the altar.

Come, lie all night in sackcloth, you ministers of my God,[†]

for the meal offering and the drink offering are withheld from your God’s house.

14 Sanctify a fast.

Call a solemn assembly.

Gather the elders and all the inhabitants of the land to the house of Yahweh, your God,

and cry to Yahweh.

15 Alas for the day!

For the day of Yahweh is at hand,

and it will come as destruction from the Almighty.

16 Isn’t the food cut off before our eyes,

joy and gladness from the house of our God?

17 The seeds rot under their clods.

The granaries are laid desolate.

The barns are broken down, for the grain has withered.

18 How the animals groan!

The herds of livestock are perplexed, because they have no pasture.

Yes, the flocks of sheep are made desolate.

19 Yahweh, I cry to you,

for the fire has devoured the pastures of the wilderness,

and the flame has burned all the trees of the field.

20 Yes, the animals of the field pant to you,

for the water brooks have dried up,

and the fire has devoured the pastures of the wilderness.

2

1 Blow the trumpet in Zion,

and sound an alarm in my holy mountain!

Let all the inhabitants of the land tremble,

for the day of Yahweh comes,

for it is close at hand:

2 A day of darkness and gloominess,

a day of clouds and thick darkness.

As the dawn spreading on the mountains,

a great and strong people;

there has never been the like,

neither will there be any more after them,

even to the years of many generations.

3 A fire devours before them,

and behind them, a flame burns.

The land is as the garden of Eden before them,

and behind them, a desolate wilderness.

Yes, and no one has escaped them.

4 Their appearance is as the appearance of horses,

and they run as horsemen.

5 Like the noise of chariots on the tops of the mountains, they leap,

like the noise of a flame of fire that devours the stubble,

like a strong people set in battle array.

6 At their presence the peoples are in anguish.

All faces have grown pale.

7 They run like mighty men.

They climb the wall like warriors.

They each march in his line, and they don’t swerve off course.

8 One doesn’t jostle another.

They each march in their own path.

They burst through the defenses

and don’t break ranks.

9 They rush on the city.

They run on the wall.

They climb up into the houses.

They enter in at the windows like thieves.

10 The earth quakes before them.

The heavens tremble.

The sun and the moon are darkened,

and the stars withdraw their shining.

11 Yahweh thunders his voice before his army,

for his forces are very great;

for he is strong who obeys his command;

for the day of Yahweh is great and very awesome,

and who can endure it?

12 “Yet even now,” says Yahweh, “turn to me with all your heart,

and with fasting, and with weeping, and with mourning.”

13 Tear your heart and not your garments,

and turn to Yahweh, your God;

for he is gracious and merciful,

slow to anger, and abundant in loving kindness,

and relents from sending calamity.

14 Who knows? He may turn and relent,

and leave a blessing behind him,

even a meal offering and a drink offering to Yahweh, your God.

15 Blow the trumpet in Zion!

Sanctify a fast.

Call a solemn assembly.

16 Gather the people.

Sanctify the assembly.

Assemble the elders.

Gather the children, and those who nurse from breasts.

Let the bridegroom go out of his room,

and the bride out of her chamber.

17 Let the priests, the ministers of Yahweh, weep between the porch and the altar,

and let them say, “Spare your people, Yahweh,

and don’t give your heritage to reproach,

that the nations should rule over them.

Why should they say among the peoples,

‘Where is their God?’ ”

18 Then Yahweh was jealous for his land,

And had pity on his people.

19 Yahweh answered his people,

“Behold,[*] I will send you grain, new wine, and oil,

and you will be satisfied with them;

and I will no more make you a reproach among the nations.

20 But I will remove the northern army far away from you,

and will drive it into a barren and desolate land,

its front into the eastern sea,

and its back into the western sea;

and its stench will come up,

and its bad smell will rise.”

Surely he has done great things.

21 Land, don’t be afraid.

Be glad and rejoice, for Yahweh has done great things.

22 Don’t be afraid, you animals of the field;

for the pastures of the wilderness spring up,

for the tree bears its fruit.

The fig tree and the vine yield their strength.

23 “Be glad then, you children of Zion,

and rejoice in Yahweh, your God;

for he gives you the early rain in just measure,

and he causes the rain to come down for you,

the early rain and the latter rain, as before.

24 The threshing floors will be full of wheat,

and the vats will overflow with new wine and oil.

25 I will restore to you the years that the swarming locust has eaten,

the great locust, the grasshopper, and the caterpillar,

my great army, which I sent among you.

26 You will have plenty to eat and be satisfied,

and will praise the name of Yahweh, your God,

who has dealt wondrously with you;

and my people will never again be disappointed.

27 You will know that I am among Israel,

and that I am Yahweh, your God, and there is no one else;

and my people will never again be disappointed.

28 “It will happen afterward, that I will pour out my Spirit on all flesh;

and your sons and your daughters will prophesy.

Your old men will dream dreams.

Your young men will see visions.

29 And also on the servants and on the handmaids in those days,

I will pour out my Spirit.

30 I will show wonders in the heavens and in the earth:

blood, fire, and pillars of smoke.

31 The sun will be turned into darkness,

and the moon into blood,

before the great and terrible day of Yahweh comes.

32 It will happen that whoever will call on Yahweh’s name shall be saved;

for in Mount Zion and in Jerusalem there will be those who escape,

as Yahweh has said,

and among the remnant, those whom Yahweh calls.

3

1 “For, behold, in those days,

and in that time,

when I restore the fortunes of Judah and Jerusalem,

2 I will gather all nations,

and will bring them down into the valley of Jehoshaphat;

and I will execute judgment on them there for my people,

and for my heritage, Israel, whom they have scattered among the nations.

They have divided my land,

3 and have cast lots for my people,

and have given a boy for a prostitute,

and sold a girl for wine, that they may drink.

4 “Yes, and what are you to me, Tyre and Sidon,

and all the regions of Philistia?

Will you repay me?

And if you repay me,

I will swiftly and speedily return your repayment on your own head.

5 Because you have taken my silver and my gold,

and have carried my finest treasures into your temples,

6 and have sold the children of Judah and the children of Jerusalem to the sons of the Greeks,

that you may remove them far from their border.

7 Behold, I will stir them up out of the place where you have sold them,

and will return your repayment on your own head;

8 and I will sell your sons and your daughters into the hands of the children of Judah,

and they will sell them to the men of Sheba,

to a faraway nation,

for Yahweh has spoken it.”

9 Proclaim this among the nations:

“Prepare for war!

Stir up the mighty men.

Let all the warriors draw near.

Let them come up. 10 Beat your plowshares into swords,

and your pruning hooks into spears.

Let the weak say, ‘I am strong.’

11 Hurry and come, all you surrounding nations,

and gather yourselves together.”

Cause your mighty ones to come down there, Yahweh.

12 “Let the nations arouse themselves,

and come up to the valley of Jehoshaphat;

for there I will sit to judge all the surrounding nations.

13 Put in the sickle;

for the harvest is ripe.

Come, tread, for the wine press is full,

the vats overflow, for their wickedness is great.”

14 Multitudes, multitudes in the valley of decision!

For the day of Yahweh is near in the valley of decision.

15 The sun and the moon are darkened,

and the stars withdraw their shining.

16 Yahweh will roar from Zion,

and thunder from Jerusalem;

and the heavens and the earth will shake;

but Yahweh will be a refuge to his people,

and a stronghold to the children of Israel.

17 “So you will know that I am Yahweh, your God,

dwelling in Zion, my holy mountain.

Then Jerusalem will be holy,

and no strangers will pass through her any more.

18 It will happen in that day,

that the mountains will drop down sweet wine,

the hills will flow with milk,

all the brooks of Judah will flow with waters;

and a fountain will flow out from Yahweh’s house,

and will water the valley of Shittim.

19 Egypt will be a desolation

and Edom will be a desolate wilderness,

for the violence done to the children of Judah,

because they have shed innocent blood in their land.

20 But Judah will be inhabited forever,

and Jerusalem from generation to generation.

21 I will cleanse their blood

that I have not cleansed,

for Yahweh dwells in Zion.”

* 1:1 “Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

† 1:13 The Hebrew word rendered “God” is “אֱלֹהִ֑ים” (Elohim).

* 2:19 “Behold”, from “הִנֵּה”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.

Jonah

1
2
3
4

The Book of

Jonah

1

1 Now Yahweh’s[*] word came to Jonah the son of Amittai, saying, 2 “Arise, go to Nineveh, that great city, and preach against it, for their wickedness has come up before me.”

3 But Jonah rose up to flee to Tarshish from the presence of Yahweh. He went down to Joppa, and found a ship going to Tarshish; so he paid its fare, and went down into it, to go with them to Tarshish from the presence of Yahweh.

4 But Yahweh sent out a great wind on the sea, and there was a mighty storm on the sea, so that the ship was likely to break up. 5 Then the mariners were afraid, and every man cried to his god. They threw the cargo that was in the ship into the sea to lighten the ship. But Jonah had gone down into the innermost parts of the ship and he was laying down, and was fast asleep. 6 So the ship master came to him, and said to him, “What do you mean, sleeper? Arise, call on your God![†] Maybe your God[‡] will notice us, so that we won’t perish.”

7 They all said to each other, “Come! Let’s cast lots, that we may know who is responsible for this evil that is on us.” So they cast lots, and the lot fell on Jonah. 8 Then they asked him, “Tell us, please, for whose cause this evil is on us. What is your occupation? Where do you come from? What is your country? Of what people are you?”

9 He said to them, “I am a Hebrew, and I fear Yahweh, the God[§] of heaven, who has made the sea and the dry land.”

10 Then the men were exceedingly afraid, and said to him, “What have you done?” For the men knew that he was fleeing from the presence of Yahweh, because he had told them. 11 Then they said to him, “What shall we do to you, that the sea may be calm to us?” For the sea grew more and more stormy.

12 He said to them, “Take me up, and throw me into the sea. Then the sea will be calm for you; for I know that because of me this great storm is on you.”

13 Nevertheless the men rowed hard to get them back to the land; but they could not, for the sea grew more and more stormy against them. 14 Therefore they cried to Yahweh, and said, “We beg you, Yahweh, we beg you, don’t let us die for this man’s life, and don’t lay on us innocent blood; for you, Yahweh, have done as it pleased you.” 15 So they took up Jonah and threw him into the sea; and the sea ceased its raging. 16 Then the men feared Yahweh exceedingly; and they offered a sacrifice to Yahweh and made vows.

17 Yahweh prepared a huge fish to swallow up Jonah, and Jonah was in the belly of the fish three days and three nights.

2

1 Then Jonah prayed to Yahweh, his God, out of the fish’s belly. 2 He said,

“I called because of my affliction to Yahweh.

He answered me.

Out of the belly of Sheol[*] I cried.

You heard my voice.

3 For you threw me into the depths,

in the heart of the seas.

The flood was all around me.

All your waves and your billows passed over me.

4 I said, ‘I have been banished from your sight;

yet I will look again toward your holy temple.’

5 The waters surrounded me,

even to the soul.

The deep was around me.

The weeds were wrapped around my head.

6 I went down to the bottoms of the mountains.

The earth barred me in forever;

yet you have brought my life up from the pit, Yahweh my God.

7 “When my soul fainted within me, I remembered Yahweh.

My prayer came in to you, into your holy temple.

8 Those who regard vain idols forsake their own mercy.

9 But I will sacrifice to you with the voice of thanksgiving.

I will pay that which I have vowed.

Salvation belongs to Yahweh.”

10 Then Yahweh spoke to the fish, and it vomited out Jonah on the dry land.

3

1 Yahweh’s word came to Jonah the second time, saying, 2 “Arise, go to Nineveh, that great city, and preach to it the message that I give you.”

3 So Jonah arose, and went to Nineveh, according to Yahweh’s word. Now Nineveh was an exceedingly great city, three days’ journey across. 4 Jonah began to enter into the city a day’s journey, and he cried out, and said, “In forty days, Nineveh will be overthrown!”

5 The people of Nineveh believed God; and they proclaimed a fast and put on sackcloth, from their greatest even to their least. 6 The news reached the king of Nineveh, and he arose from his throne, took off his royal robe, covered himself with sackcloth, and sat in ashes. 7 He made a proclamation and published through Nineveh by the decree of the king and his nobles, saying, “Let neither man nor animal, herd nor flock, taste anything; let them not feed, nor drink water; 8 but let them be covered with sackcloth, both man and animal, and let them cry mightily to God. Yes, let them turn everyone from his evil way and from the violence that is in his hands. 9 Who knows whether God will not turn and relent, and turn away from his fierce anger, so that we might not perish?”

10 God saw their works, that they turned from their evil way. God relented of the disaster which he said he would do to them, and he didn’t do it.

4

1 But it displeased Jonah exceedingly, and he was angry. 2 He prayed to Yahweh, and said, “Please, Yahweh, wasn’t this what I said when I was still in my own country? Therefore I hurried to flee to Tarshish, for I knew that you are a gracious God and merciful, slow to anger, and abundant in loving kindness, and you relent of doing harm. 3 Therefore now, Yahweh, take, I beg you, my life from me, for it is better for me to die than to live.”

4 Yahweh said, “Is it right for you to be angry?”

5 Then Jonah went out of the city and sat on the east side of the city, and there made himself a booth and sat under it in the shade, until he might see what would become of the city. 6 Yahweh God prepared a vine and made it to come up over Jonah, that it might be a shade over his head to deliver him from his discomfort. So Jonah was exceedingly glad because of the vine. 7 But God prepared a worm at dawn the next day, and it chewed on the vine so that it withered. 8 When the sun arose, God prepared a sultry east wind; and the sun beat on Jonah’s head, so that he was faint and requested for himself that he might die. He said, “It is better for me to die than to live.”

9 God said to Jonah, “Is it right for you to be angry about the vine?”

He said, “I am right to be angry, even to death.”

10 Yahweh said, “You have been concerned for the vine, for which you have not labored, neither made it grow; which came up in a night and perished in a night. 11 Shouldn’t I be concerned for Nineveh, that great city, in which are more than one hundred twenty thousand persons who can’t discern between their right hand and their left hand, and also many animals?”

* 1:1 “Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

† 1:6 or, gods

‡ 1:6 or, gods

§ 1:9 The Hebrew word rendered “God” is “אֱלֹהִ֑ים” (Elohim).

* 2:2 Sheol is the place of the dead.

Joshua

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10

11
12
13
14
15
16
17
18
19
20

21
22
23
24

The Book of

Joshua

1

1 Now after the death of Moses the servant of Yahweh,[*] Yahweh spoke to Joshua the son of Nun, Moses’ servant, saying, 2 “Moses my servant is dead. Now therefore arise, go across this Jordan, you and all these people, to the land which I am giving to them, even to the children of Israel. 3 I have given you every place that the sole of your foot will tread on, as I told Moses. 4 From the wilderness and this Lebanon even to the great river, the river Euphrates, all the land of the Hittites, and to the great sea toward the going down of the sun, shall be your border. 5 No man will be able to stand before you all the days of your life. As I was with Moses, so I will be with you. I will not fail you nor forsake you.

6 “Be strong and courageous; for you shall cause this people to inherit the land which I swore to their fathers to give them. 7 Only be strong and very courageous. Be careful to observe to do according to all the law which Moses my servant commanded you. Don’t turn from it to the right hand or to the left, that you may have good success wherever you go. 8 This book of the law shall not depart from your mouth, but you shall meditate on it day and night, that you may observe to do according to all that is written in it; for then you shall make your way prosperous, and then you shall have good success. 9 Haven’t I commanded you? Be strong and courageous. Don’t be afraid. Don’t be dismayed, for Yahweh your God[†] is with you wherever you go.”

10 Then Joshua commanded the officers of the people, saying, 11 “Pass through the middle of the camp, and command the people, saying, ‘Prepare food; for within three days you are to pass over this Jordan, to go in to possess the land which Yahweh your God gives you to possess.’ ”

12 Joshua spoke to the Reubenites, and to the Gadites, and to the half-tribe of Manasseh, saying, 13 “Remember the word which Moses the servant of Yahweh commanded you, saying, ‘Yahweh your God gives you rest, and will give you this land. 14 Your wives, your little ones, and your livestock shall live in the land which Moses gave you beyond the Jordan; but you shall pass over before your brothers armed, all the mighty men of valor, and shall help them 15 until Yahweh has given your brothers rest, as he has given you, and they have also possessed the land which Yahweh your God gives them. Then you shall return to the land of your possession and possess it, which Moses the servant of Yahweh gave you beyond the Jordan toward the sunrise.’ ”

16 They answered Joshua, saying, “All that you have commanded us we will do, and wherever you send us we will go. 17 Just as we listened to Moses in all things, so will we listen to you. Only may Yahweh your God be with you, as he was with Moses. 18 Whoever rebels against your commandment, and doesn’t listen to your words in all that you command him shall himself be put to death. Only be strong and courageous.”

2

1 Joshua the son of Nun secretly sent two men out of Shittim as spies, saying, “Go, view the land, including Jericho.” They went and came into the house of a prostitute whose name was Rahab, and slept there.

2 The king of Jericho was told, “Behold,[*] men of the children of Israel came in here tonight to spy out the land.”

3 Jericho’s king sent to Rahab, saying, “Bring out the men who have come to you, who have entered into your house; for they have come to spy out all the land.”

4 The woman took the two men and hid them. Then she said, “Yes, the men came to me, but I didn’t know where they came from. 5 About the time of the shutting of the gate, when it was dark, the men went out. Where the men went, I don’t know. Pursue them quickly. You may catch up with them.” 6 But she had brought them up to the roof, and hidden them under the stalks of flax which she had laid in order on the roof. 7 The men pursued them along the way to the fords of the Jordan River. As soon as those who pursued them had gone out, they shut the gate. 8 Before they had lain down, she came up to them on the roof. 9 She said to the men, “I know that Yahweh has given you the land, and that the fear of you has fallen upon us, and that all the inhabitants of the land melt away before you. 10 For we have heard how Yahweh dried up the water of the Red Sea before you, when you came out of Egypt; and what you did to the two kings of the Amorites, who were beyond the Jordan, to Sihon and to Og, whom you utterly destroyed. 11 As soon as we had heard it, our hearts melted, and there wasn’t any more spirit in any man, because of you: for Yahweh your God, he is God in heaven above, and on earth beneath. 12 Now therefore, please swear to me by Yahweh, since I have dealt kindly with you, that you also will deal kindly with my father’s house, and give me a true sign; 13 and that you will save alive my father, my mother, my brothers, and my sisters, and all that they have, and will deliver our lives from death.”

14 The men said to her, “Our life for yours, if you don’t talk about this business of ours; and it shall be, when Yahweh gives us the land, that we will deal kindly and truly with you.”

15 Then she let them down by a cord through the window; for her house was on the side of the wall, and she lived on the wall. 16 She said to them, “Go to the mountain, lest the pursuers find you. Hide yourselves there three days, until the pursuers have returned. Afterward, you may go your way.”

17 The men said to her, “We will be guiltless of this your oath which you’ve made us to swear. 18 Behold, when we come into the land, tie this line of scarlet thread in the window which you used to let us down. Gather to yourself into the house your father, your mother, your brothers, and all your father’s household. 19 It shall be that whoever goes out of the doors of your house into the street, his blood will be on his head, and we will be guiltless. Whoever is with you in the house, his blood shall be on our head, if any hand is on him. 20 But if you talk about this business of ours, then we shall be guiltless of your oath which you’ve made us to swear.”

21 She said, “Let it be as you have said.” She sent them away, and they departed. Then she tied the scarlet line in the window.

22 They went and came to the mountain, and stayed there three days, until the pursuers had returned. The pursuers sought them all along the way, but didn’t find them. 23 Then the two men returned, descended from the mountain, crossed the river, and came to Joshua the son of Nun. They told him all that had happened to them. 24 They said to Joshua, “Truly Yahweh has delivered all the land into our hands. Moreover, all the inhabitants of the land melt away before us.”

3

1 Joshua got up early in the morning; and they moved from Shittim and came to the Jordan, he and all the children of Israel. They camped there before they crossed over. 2 After three days, the officers went through the middle of the camp; 3 and they commanded the people, saying, “When you see the ark of Yahweh your God’s covenant, and the Levitical priests bearing it, then leave your place and follow it. 4 Yet there shall be a space between you and it of about two thousand cubits[*] by measure—don’t come closer to it—that you may know the way by which you must go; for you have not passed this way before.”

5 Joshua said to the people, “Sanctify yourselves; for tomorrow Yahweh will do wonders among you.”

6 Joshua spoke to the priests, saying, “Take up the ark of the covenant, and cross over before the people.” They took up the ark of the covenant, and went before the people.

7 Yahweh said to Joshua, “Today I will begin to magnify you in the sight of all Israel, that they may know that as I was with Moses, so I will be with you. 8 You shall command the priests who bear the ark of the covenant, saying, ‘When you come to the brink of the waters of the Jordan, you shall stand still in the Jordan.’ ”

9 Joshua said to the children of Israel, “Come here, and hear the words of Yahweh your God.” 10 Joshua said, “By this you shall know that the living God is among you, and that he will without fail drive the Canaanite, the Hittite, the Hivite, the Perizzite, the Girgashite, the Amorite, and the Jebusite out from before you. 11 Behold, the ark of the covenant of the Lord[†] of all the earth passes over before you into the Jordan. 12 Now therefore take twelve men out of the tribes of Israel, for every tribe a man. 13 It shall be that when the soles of the feet of the priests who bear the ark of Yahweh, the Lord of all the earth, rest in the waters of the Jordan, that the waters of the Jordan will be cut off. The waters that come down from above shall stand in one heap.”

14 When the people moved from their tents to pass over the Jordan, the priests who bore the ark of the covenant being before the people, 15 and when those who bore the ark had come to the Jordan, and the feet of the priests who bore the ark had dipped in the edge of the water (for the Jordan overflows all its banks all the time of harvest), 16 the waters which came down from above stood, and rose up in one heap a great way off, at Adam, the city that is beside Zarethan; and those that went down toward the sea of the Arabah, even the Salt Sea, were wholly cut off. Then the people passed over near Jericho. 17 The priests who bore the ark of Yahweh’s covenant stood firm on dry ground in the middle of the Jordan; and all Israel crossed over on dry ground, until all the nation had passed completely over the Jordan.

4

1 When all the nation had completely crossed over the Jordan, Yahweh spoke to Joshua, saying, 2 “Take twelve men out of the people, a man out of every tribe, 3 and command them, saying, ‘Take from out of the middle of the Jordan, out of the place where the priests’ feet stood firm, twelve stones, carry them over with you, and lay them down in the place where you’ll camp tonight.’ ”

4 Then Joshua called the twelve men whom he had prepared of the children of Israel, a man out of every tribe. 5 Joshua said to them, “Cross before the ark of Yahweh your God into the middle of the Jordan, and each of you pick up a stone and put it on your shoulder, according to the number of the tribes of the children of Israel; 6 that this may be a sign among you, that when your children ask in the future, saying, ‘What do you mean by these stones?’ 7 then you shall tell them, ‘Because the waters of the Jordan were cut off before the ark of Yahweh’s covenant. When it crossed over the Jordan, the waters of the Jordan were cut off. These stones shall be for a memorial to the children of Israel forever.’ ”

8 The children of Israel did as Joshua commanded, and took up twelve stones out of the middle of the Jordan, as Yahweh spoke to Joshua, according to the number of the tribes of the children of Israel. They carried them over with them to the place where they camped, and laid them down there. 9 Joshua set up twelve stones in the middle of the Jordan, in the place where the feet of the priests who bore the ark of the covenant stood; and they are there to this day. 10 For the priests who bore the ark stood in the middle of the Jordan until everything was finished that Yahweh commanded Joshua to speak to the people, according to all that Moses commanded Joshua; and the people hurried and passed over. 11 When all the people had completely crossed over, Yahweh’s ark crossed over with the priests in the presence of the people.

12 The children of Reuben, and the children of Gad, and the half-tribe of Manasseh crossed over armed before the children of Israel, as Moses spoke to them. 13 About forty thousand men, ready and armed for war, passed over before Yahweh to battle, to the plains of Jericho. 14 On that day, Yahweh magnified Joshua in the sight of all Israel; and they feared him, as they feared Moses, all the days of his life.

15 Yahweh spoke to Joshua, saying, 16 “Command the priests who bear the ark of the covenant, that they come up out of the Jordan.”

17 Joshua therefore commanded the priests, saying, “Come up out of the Jordan!” 18 When the priests who bore the ark of Yahweh’s covenant had come up out of the middle of the Jordan, and the soles of the priests’ feet had been lifted up to the dry ground, the waters of the Jordan returned to their place, and went over all its banks, as before. 19 The people came up out of the Jordan on the tenth day of the first month, and encamped in Gilgal, on the east border of Jericho.

20 Joshua set up those twelve stones, which they took out of the Jordan, in Gilgal. 21 He spoke to the children of Israel, saying, “When your children ask their fathers in time to come, saying, ‘What do these stones mean?’ 22 Then you shall let your children know, saying, ‘Israel came over this Jordan on dry land. 23 For Yahweh your God dried up the waters of the Jordan from before you until you had crossed over, as Yahweh your God did to the Red Sea, which he dried up from before us, until we had crossed over, 24 that all the peoples of the earth may know that Yahweh’s hand is mighty, and that you may fear Yahweh your God forever.’ ”

5

1 When all the kings of the Amorites, who were beyond the Jordan westward, and all the kings of the Canaanites, who were by the sea, heard how Yahweh had dried up the waters of the Jordan from before the children of Israel until we had crossed over, their heart melted, and there was no more spirit in them, because of the children of Israel. 2 At that time, Yahweh said to Joshua, “Make flint knives, and circumcise again the sons of Israel the second time.” 3 Joshua made himself flint knives, and circumcised the sons of Israel at the hill of the foreskins. 4 This is the reason Joshua circumcised them: all the people who came out of Egypt, who were males, even all the men of war, died in the wilderness along the way, after they came out of Egypt. 5 For all the people who came out were circumcised; but all the people who were born in the wilderness along the way as they came out of Egypt had not been circumcised. 6 For the children of Israel walked forty years in the wilderness until all the nation, even the men of war who came out of Egypt, were consumed, because they didn’t listen to Yahweh’s voice. Yahweh swore to them that he wouldn’t let them see the land which Yahweh swore to their fathers that he would give us, a land flowing with milk and honey. 7 Their children, whom he raised up in their place, were circumcised by Joshua, for they were uncircumcised, because they had not circumcised them on the way. 8 When they were done circumcising the whole nation, they stayed in their places in the camp until they were healed.

9 Yahweh said to Joshua, “Today I have rolled away the reproach of Egypt from you.” Therefore the name of that place was called Gilgal[*] to this day. 10 The children of Israel encamped in Gilgal. They kept the Passover on the fourteenth day of the month at evening in the plains of Jericho. 11 They ate unleavened cakes and parched grain of the produce of the land on the next day after the Passover, in the same day. 12 The manna ceased on the next day, after they had eaten of the produce of the land. The children of Israel didn’t have manna any more, but they ate of the fruit of the land of Canaan that year.

13 When Joshua was by Jericho, he lifted up his eyes and looked, and behold, a man stood in front of him with his sword drawn in his hand. Joshua went to him and said to him, “Are you for us, or for our enemies?”

14 He said, “No; but I have come now as commander of Yahweh’s army.”

Joshua fell on his face to the earth, and worshiped, and asked him, “What does my lord say to his servant?”

15 The prince of Yahweh’s army said to Joshua, “Take off your sandals, for the place on which you stand is holy.” Joshua did so.

6

1 Now Jericho was tightly shut up because of the children of Israel. No one went out, and no one came in. 2 Yahweh said to Joshua, “Behold, I have given Jericho into your hand, with its king and the mighty men of valor. 3 All of your men of war shall march around the city, going around the city once. You shall do this six days. 4 Seven priests shall bear seven trumpets of rams’ horns before the ark. On the seventh day, you shall march around the city seven times, and the priests shall blow the trumpets. 5 It shall be that when they make a long blast with the ram’s horn, and when you hear the sound of the trumpet, all the people shall shout with a great shout; then the city wall will fall down flat, and the people shall go up, every man straight in front of him.”

6 Joshua the son of Nun called the priests, and said to them, “Take up the ark of the covenant, and let seven priests bear seven trumpets of rams’ horns before Yahweh’s ark.”

7 They said to the people, “Advance! March around the city, and let the armed men pass on before Yahweh’s ark.”

8 It was so, that when Joshua had spoken to the people, the seven priests bearing the seven trumpets of rams’ horns before Yahweh advanced and blew the trumpets, and the ark of Yahweh’s covenant followed them. 9 The armed men went before the priests who blew the trumpets, and the ark went after them. The trumpets sounded as they went.

10 Joshua commanded the people, saying, “You shall not shout nor let your voice be heard, neither shall any word proceed out of your mouth until the day I tell you to shout. Then you shall shout.” 11 So he caused Yahweh’s ark to go around the city, circling it once. Then they came into the camp, and stayed in the camp. 12 Joshua rose early in the morning, and the priests took up Yahweh’s ark. 13 The seven priests bearing the seven trumpets of rams’ horns in front of Yahweh’s ark went on continually, and blew the trumpets. The armed men went in front of them. The rear guard came after Yahweh’s ark. The trumpets sounded as they went. 14 The second day they marched around the city once, and returned into the camp. They did this six days.

15 On the seventh day, they rose early at the dawning of the day, and marched around the city in the same way seven times. On this day only they marched around the city seven times. 16 At the seventh time, when the priests blew the trumpets, Joshua said to the people, “Shout, for Yahweh has given you the city! 17 The city shall be devoted, even it and all that is in it, to Yahweh. Only Rahab the prostitute shall live, she and all who are with her in the house, because she hid the messengers that we sent. 18 But as for you, only keep yourselves from what is devoted to destruction, lest when you have devoted it, you take of the devoted thing; so you would make the camp of Israel accursed and trouble it. 19 But all the silver, gold, and vessels of bronze and iron are holy to Yahweh. They shall come into Yahweh’s treasury.”

20 So the people shouted and the priests blew the trumpets. When the people heard the sound of the trumpet, the people shouted with a great shout, and the wall fell down flat, so that the people went up into the city, every man straight in front of him, and they took the city. 21 They utterly destroyed all that was in the city, both man and woman, both young and old, and ox, sheep, and donkey, with the edge of the sword. 22 Joshua said to the two men who had spied out the land, “Go into the prostitute’s house, and bring the woman and all that she has out from there, as you swore to her.” 23 The young men who were spies went in, and brought out Rahab with her father, her mother, her brothers, and all that she had. They also brought out all of her relatives, and they set them outside of the camp of Israel. 24 They burned the city with fire, and all that was in it. Only they put the silver, the gold, and the vessels of bronze and of iron into the treasury of Yahweh’s house. 25 But Rahab the prostitute, her father’s household, and all that she had, Joshua saved alive. She lives in the middle of Israel to this day, because she hid the messengers whom Joshua sent to spy out Jericho.

26 Joshua commanded them with an oath at that time, saying, “Cursed is the man before Yahweh who rises up and builds this city Jericho. With the loss of his firstborn he will lay its foundation, and with the loss of his youngest son he will set up its gates.” 27 So Yahweh was with Joshua; and his fame was in all the land.

7

1 But the children of Israel committed a trespass in the devoted things; for Achan, the son of Carmi, the son of Zabdi, the son of Zerah, of the tribe of Judah, took some of the devoted things. Therefore Yahweh’s anger burned against the children of Israel. 2 Joshua sent men from Jericho to Ai, which is beside Beth Aven, on the east side of Bethel, and spoke to them, saying, “Go up and spy out the land.”

The men went up and spied out Ai. 3 They returned to Joshua, and said to him, “Don’t let all the people go up, but let about two or three thousand men go up and strike Ai. Don’t make all the people to toil there, for there are only a few of them.” 4 So about three thousand men of the people went up there, and they fled before the men of Ai. 5 The men of Ai struck about thirty-six men of them. They chased them from before the gate even to Shebarim, and struck them at the descent. The hearts of the people melted, and became like water. 6 Joshua tore his clothes, and fell to the earth on his face before Yahweh’s ark until the evening, he and the elders of Israel; and they put dust on their heads. 7 Joshua said, “Alas, Lord Yahweh, why have you brought this people over the Jordan at all, to deliver us into the hand of the Amorites, to cause us to perish? I wish that we had been content and lived beyond the Jordan! 8 Oh, Lord, what shall I say, after Israel has turned their backs before their enemies? 9 For the Canaanites and all the inhabitants of the land will hear of it, and will surround us, and cut off our name from the earth. What will you do for your great name?”

10 Yahweh said to Joshua, “Get up! Why have you fallen on your face like that? 11 Israel has sinned. Yes, they have even transgressed my covenant which I commanded them. Yes, they have even taken some of the devoted things, and have also stolen, and also deceived. They have even put it among their own stuff. 12 Therefore the children of Israel can’t stand before their enemies. They turn their backs before their enemies, because they have become devoted for destruction. I will not be with you any more, unless you destroy the devoted things from among you. 13 Get up! Sanctify the people, and say, ‘Sanctify yourselves for tomorrow, for Yahweh, the God of Israel, says, “There is a devoted thing among you, Israel. You cannot stand before your enemies until you take away the devoted thing from among you.” 14 In the morning therefore you shall be brought near by your tribes. It shall be that the tribe which Yahweh selects shall come near by families. The family which Yahweh selects shall come near by households. The household which Yahweh selects shall come near man by man. 15 It shall be, that he who is taken with the devoted thing shall be burned with fire, he and all that he has, because he has transgressed Yahweh’s covenant, and because he has done a disgraceful thing in Israel.’ ”

16 So Joshua rose up early in the morning and brought Israel near by their tribes. The tribe of Judah was selected. 17 He brought near the family of Judah, and he selected the family of the Zerahites. He brought near the family of the Zerahites man by man, and Zabdi was selected. 18 He brought near his household man by man, and Achan, the son of Carmi, the son of Zabdi, the son of Zerah, of the tribe of Judah, was selected. 19 Joshua said to Achan, “My son, please give glory to Yahweh, the God of Israel, and make confession to him. Tell me now what you have done! Don’t hide it from me!”

20 Achan answered Joshua, and said, “I have truly sinned against Yahweh, the God of Israel, and this is what I have done. 21 When I saw among the plunder a beautiful Babylonian robe, two hundred shekels[*] of silver, and a wedge of gold weighing fifty shekels, then I coveted them and took them. Behold, they are hidden in the ground in the middle of my tent, with the silver under it.”

22 So Joshua sent messengers, and they ran to the tent. Behold, it was hidden in his tent, with the silver under it. 23 They took them from the middle of the tent, and brought them to Joshua and to all the children of Israel. They laid them down before Yahweh. 24 Joshua, and all Israel with him, took Achan the son of Zerah, the silver, the robe, the wedge of gold, his sons, his daughters, his cattle, his donkeys, his sheep, his tent, and all that he had; and they brought them up to the valley of Achor. 25 Joshua said, “Why have you troubled us? Yahweh will trouble you today.” All Israel stoned him with stones, and they burned them with fire and stoned them with stones. 26 They raised over him a great heap of stones that remains to this day. Yahweh turned from the fierceness of his anger. Therefore the name of that place was called “The valley of Achor” to this day.

8

1 Yahweh said to Joshua, “Don’t be afraid, and don’t be dismayed. Take all the warriors with you, and arise, go up to Ai. Behold, I have given into your hand the king of Ai, with his people, his city, and his land. 2 You shall do to Ai and her king as you did to Jericho and her king, except you shall take its goods and its livestock for yourselves. Set an ambush for the city behind it.”

3 So Joshua arose, with all the warriors, to go up to Ai. Joshua chose thirty thousand men, the mighty men of valor, and sent them out by night. 4 He commanded them, saying, “Behold, you shall lie in ambush against the city, behind the city. Don’t go very far from the city, but all of you be ready. 5 I and all the people who are with me will approach the city. It shall happen, when they come out against us, as at the first, that we will flee before them. 6 They will come out after us until we have drawn them away from the city; for they will say, ‘They flee before us, like the first time.’ So we will flee before them, 7 and you shall rise up from the ambush, and take possession of the city; for Yahweh your God will deliver it into your hand. 8 It shall be, when you have seized the city, that you shall set the city on fire. You shall do this according to Yahweh’s word. Behold, I have commanded you.”

9 Joshua sent them out; and they went to set up the ambush, and stayed between Bethel and Ai on the west side of Ai; but Joshua stayed among the people that night. 10 Joshua rose up early in the morning, mustered the people, and went up, he and the elders of Israel, before the people to Ai. 11 All the people, even the men of war who were with him, went up and came near, and came before the city and encamped on the north side of Ai. Now there was a valley between him and Ai. 12 He took about five thousand men, and set them in ambush between Bethel and Ai, on the west side of the city. 13 So they set the people, even all the army who was on the north of the city, and their ambush on the west of the city; and Joshua went that night into the middle of the valley. 14 When the king of Ai saw it, they hurried and rose up early, and the men of the city went out against Israel to battle, he and all his people, at the time appointed, before the Arabah; but he didn’t know that there was an ambush against him behind the city. 15 Joshua and all Israel made as if they were beaten before them, and fled by the way of the wilderness. 16 All the people who were in the city were called together to pursue after them. They pursued Joshua, and were drawn away from the city. 17 There was not a man left in Ai or Bethel who didn’t go out after Israel. They left the city open, and pursued Israel.

18 Yahweh said to Joshua, “Stretch out the javelin that is in your hand toward Ai, for I will give it into your hand.”

Joshua stretched out the javelin that was in his hand toward the city. 19 The ambush arose quickly out of their place, and they ran as soon as he had stretched out his hand and entered into the city and took it. They hurried and set the city on fire. 20 When the men of Ai looked behind them, they saw, and behold, the smoke of the city ascended up to heaven, and they had no power to flee this way or that way. The people who fled to the wilderness turned back on the pursuers. 21 When Joshua and all Israel saw that the ambush had taken the city, and that the smoke of the city ascended, then they turned back and killed the men of Ai. 22 The others came out of the city against them, so they were in the middle of Israel, some on this side, and some on that side. They struck them, so that they let none of them remain or escape. 23 They captured the king of Ai alive, and brought him to Joshua.

24 When Israel had finished killing all the inhabitants of Ai in the field, in the wilderness in which they pursued them, and they had all fallen by the edge of the sword until they were consumed, all Israel returned to Ai and struck it with the edge of the sword. 25 All that fell that day, both of men and women, were twelve thousand, even all the people of Ai. 26 For Joshua didn’t draw back his hand, with which he stretched out the javelin, until he had utterly destroyed all the inhabitants of Ai. 27 Israel took for themselves only the livestock and the goods of that city, according to Yahweh’s word which he commanded Joshua. 28 So Joshua burned Ai and made it a heap forever, even a desolation, to this day. 29 He hanged the king of Ai on a tree until the evening. At sundown, Joshua commanded, and they took his body down from the tree and threw it at the entrance of the gate of the city, and raised a great heap of stones on it that remains to this day.

30 Then Joshua built an altar to Yahweh, the God of Israel, on Mount Ebal, 31 as Moses the servant of Yahweh commanded the children of Israel, as it is written in the book of the law of Moses: an altar of uncut stones, on which no one had lifted up any iron. They offered burnt offerings on it to Yahweh and sacrificed peace offerings. 32 He wrote there on the stones a copy of Moses’ law, which he wrote in the presence of the children of Israel. 33 All Israel, with their elders, officers, and judges, stood on both sides of the ark before the Levitical priests, who carried the ark of Yahweh’s covenant, the foreigner as well as the native; half of them in front of Mount Gerizim, and half of them in front of Mount Ebal, as Moses the servant of Yahweh had commanded at the first, that they should bless the people of Israel. 34 Afterward he read all the words of the law, the blessing and the curse, according to all that is written in the book of the law. 35 There was not a word of all that Moses commanded which Joshua didn’t read before all the assembly of Israel, with the women, the little ones, and the foreigners who were among them.

9

1 When all the kings who were beyond the Jordan, in the hill country, and in the lowland, and on all the shore of the great sea in front of Lebanon, the Hittite, the Amorite, the Canaanite, the Perizzite, the Hivite, and the Jebusite, heard of it 2 they gathered themselves together to fight with Joshua and with Israel, with one accord. 3 But when the inhabitants of Gibeon heard what Joshua had done to Jericho and to Ai, 4 they also resorted to a ruse, and went and made as if they had been ambassadors, and took old sacks on their donkeys, and old, torn-up and bound up wine skins, 5 and old and patched sandals on their feet, and wore old garments. All the bread of their food supply was dry and moldy. 6 They went to Joshua at the camp at Gilgal, and said to him and to the men of Israel, “We have come from a far country. Now therefore make a covenant with us.”

7 The men of Israel said to the Hivites, “What if you live among us? How could we make a covenant with you?”

8 They said to Joshua, “We are your servants.”

Joshua said to them, “Who are you? Where do you come from?”

9 They said to him, “Your servants have come from a very far country because of the name of Yahweh your God; for we have heard of his fame, all that he did in Egypt, 10 and all that he did to the two kings of the Amorites who were beyond the Jordan, to Sihon king of Heshbon and to Og king of Bashan, who was at Ashtaroth. 11 Our elders and all the inhabitants of our country spoke to us, saying, ‘Take supplies in your hand for the journey, and go to meet them. Tell them, “We are your servants. Now make a covenant with us.” ’ 12 This our bread we took hot for our supplies out of our houses on the day we went out to go to you; but now, behold, it is dry, and has become moldy. 13 These wine skins, which we filled, were new; and behold, they are torn. These our garments and our sandals have become old because of the very long journey.”

14 The men sampled their provisions, and didn’t ask counsel from Yahweh’s mouth. 15 Joshua made peace with them, and made a covenant with them, to let them live. The princes of the congregation swore to them. 16 At the end of three days after they had made a covenant with them, they heard that they were their neighbors, and that they lived among them. 17 The children of Israel traveled and came to their cities on the third day. Now their cities were Gibeon, Chephirah, Beeroth, and Kiriath Jearim. 18 The children of Israel didn’t strike them, because the princes of the congregation had sworn to them by Yahweh, the God of Israel. All the congregation murmured against the princes. 19 But all the princes said to all the congregation, “We have sworn to them by Yahweh, the God of Israel. Now therefore we may not touch them. 20 We will do this to them, and let them live; lest wrath be on us, because of the oath which we swore to them.” 21 The princes said to them, “Let them live.” So they became wood cutters and drawers of water for all the congregation, as the princes had spoken to them.

22 Joshua called for them, and he spoke to them, saying, “Why have you deceived us, saying, ‘We are very far from you,’ when you live among us? 23 Now therefore you are cursed, and some of you will never fail to be slaves, both wood cutters and drawers of water for the house of my God.”

24 They answered Joshua, and said, “Because your servants were certainly told how Yahweh your God commanded his servant Moses to give you all the land, and to destroy all the inhabitants of the land from before you. Therefore we were very afraid for our lives because of you, and have done this thing. 25 Now, behold, we are in your hand. Do to us as it seems good and right to you to do.”

26 He did so to them, and delivered them out of the hand of the children of Israel, so that they didn’t kill them. 27 That day Joshua made them wood cutters and drawers of water for the congregation and for Yahweh’s altar to this day, in the place which he should choose.

10

1 Now when Adoni-Zedek king of Jerusalem heard how Joshua had taken Ai, and had utterly destroyed it; as he had done to Jericho and her king, so he had done to Ai and her king; and how the inhabitants of Gibeon had made peace with Israel, and were among them, 2 they were very afraid, because Gibeon was a great city, as one of the royal cities, and because it was greater than Ai, and all its men were mighty. 3 Therefore Adoni-Zedek king of Jerusalem sent to Hoham king of Hebron, Piram king of Jarmuth, Japhia king of Lachish, and Debir king of Eglon, saying, 4 “Come up to me and help me. Let’s strike Gibeon; for they have made peace with Joshua and with the children of Israel.” 5 Therefore the five kings of the Amorites, the king of Jerusalem, the king of Hebron, the king of Jarmuth, the king of Lachish, and the king of Eglon, gathered themselves together and went up, they and all their armies, and encamped against Gibeon, and made war against it. 6 The men of Gibeon sent to Joshua at the camp at Gilgal, saying, “Don’t abandon your servants! Come up to us quickly and save us! Help us; for all the kings of the Amorites that dwell in the hill country have gathered together against us.”

7 So Joshua went up from Gilgal, he and the whole army with him, including all the mighty men of valor. 8 Yahweh said to Joshua, “Don’t fear them, for I have delivered them into your hands. Not a man of them will stand before you.”

9 Joshua therefore came to them suddenly. He marched from Gilgal all night. 10 Yahweh confused them before Israel. He killed them with a great slaughter at Gibeon, and chased them by the way of the ascent of Beth Horon, and struck them to Azekah and to Makkedah. 11 As they fled from before Israel, while they were at the descent of Beth Horon, Yahweh hurled down great stones from the sky on them to Azekah, and they died. There were more who died from the hailstones than those whom the children of Israel killed with the sword.

12 Then Joshua spoke to Yahweh in the day when Yahweh delivered up the Amorites before the children of Israel. He said in the sight of Israel, “Sun, stand still on Gibeon! You, moon, stop in the valley of Aijalon!”

13 The sun stood still, and the moon stayed, until the nation had avenged themselves of their enemies. Isn’t this written in the book of Jashar? The sun stayed in the middle of the sky, and didn’t hurry to go down about a whole day. 14 There was no day like that before it or after it, that Yahweh listened to the voice of a man; for Yahweh fought for Israel.

15 Joshua returned, and all Israel with him, to the camp to Gilgal. 16 These five kings fled, and hid themselves in the cave at Makkedah. 17 Joshua was told, saying, “The five kings have been found, hidden in the cave at Makkedah.”

18 Joshua said, “Roll large stones to cover the cave’s entrance, and set men by it to guard them; 19 but don’t stay there. Pursue your enemies, and attack them from the rear. Don’t allow them to enter into their cities; for Yahweh your God has delivered them into your hand.”

20 When Joshua and the children of Israel had finished killing them with a very great slaughter until they were consumed, and the remnant which remained of them had entered into the fortified cities, 21 all the people returned to the camp to Joshua at Makkedah in peace. None moved his tongue against any of the children of Israel. 22 Then Joshua said, “Open the cave entrance, and bring those five kings out of the cave to me.”

23 They did so, and brought those five kings out of the cave to him: the king of Jerusalem, the king of Hebron, the king of Jarmuth, the king of Lachish, and the king of Eglon. 24 When they brought those kings out to Joshua, Joshua called for all the men of Israel, and said to the chiefs of the men of war who went with him, “Come near. Put your feet on the necks of these kings.”

They came near, and put their feet on their necks.

25 Joshua said to them, “Don’t be afraid, nor be dismayed. Be strong and courageous, for Yahweh will do this to all your enemies against whom you fight.”

26 Afterward Joshua struck them, put them to death, and hanged them on five trees. They were hanging on the trees until the evening. 27 At the time of the going down of the sun, Joshua commanded, and they took them down off the trees, and threw them into the cave in which they had hidden themselves, and laid great stones on the mouth of the cave, which remain to this very day.

28 Joshua took Makkedah on that day, and struck it with the edge of the sword, with its king. He utterly destroyed it and all the souls who were in it. He left no one remaining. He did to the king of Makkedah as he had done to the king of Jericho.

29 Joshua passed from Makkedah, and all Israel with him, to Libnah, and fought against Libnah. 30 Yahweh delivered it also, with its king, into the hand of Israel. He struck it with the edge of the sword, and all the souls who were in it. He left no one remaining in it. He did to its king as he had done to the king of Jericho.

31 Joshua passed from Libnah, and all Israel with him, to Lachish, and encamped against it, and fought against it. 32 Yahweh delivered Lachish into the hand of Israel. He took it on the second day, and struck it with the edge of the sword, with all the souls who were in it, according to all that he had done to Libnah. 33 Then Horam king of Gezer came up to help Lachish; and Joshua struck him and his people, until he had left him no one remaining.

34 Joshua passed from Lachish, and all Israel with him, to Eglon; and they encamped against it and fought against it. 35 They took it on that day, and struck it with the edge of the sword. He utterly destroyed all the souls who were in it that day, according to all that he had done to Lachish.

36 Joshua went up from Eglon, and all Israel with him, to Hebron; and they fought against it. 37 They took it, and struck it with the edge of the sword, with its king and all its cities, and all the souls who were in it. He left no one remaining, according to all that he had done to Eglon; but he utterly destroyed it, and all the souls who were in it.

38 Joshua returned, and all Israel with him, to Debir, and fought against it. 39 He took it, with its king and all its cities. They struck them with the edge of the sword, and utterly destroyed all the souls who were in it. He left no one remaining. As he had done to Hebron, so he did to Debir, and to its king; as he had done also to Libnah, and to its king. 40 So Joshua struck all the land, the hill country, the South, the lowland, the slopes, and all their kings. He left no one remaining, but he utterly destroyed all that breathed, as Yahweh, the God of Israel, commanded. 41 Joshua struck them from Kadesh Barnea even to Gaza, and all the country of Goshen, even to Gibeon. 42 Joshua took all these kings and their land at one time because Yahweh, the God of Israel, fought for Israel. 43 Joshua returned, and all Israel with him, to the camp to Gilgal.

11

1 When Jabin king of Hazor heard of it, he sent to Jobab king of Madon, to the king of Shimron, to the king of Achshaph, 2 and to the kings who were on the north, in the hill country, in the Arabah south of Chinneroth, in the lowland, and in the heights of Dor on the west, 3 to the Canaanite on the east and on the west, the Amorite, the Hittite, the Perizzite, the Jebusite in the hill country, and the Hivite under Hermon in the land of Mizpah. 4 They went out, they and all their armies with them, many people, even as the sand that is on the seashore in multitude, with very many horses and chariots. 5 All these kings met together; and they came and encamped together at the waters of Merom, to fight with Israel.

6 Yahweh said to Joshua, “Don’t be afraid because of them; for tomorrow at this time, I will deliver them up all slain before Israel. You shall hamstring their horses and burn their chariots with fire.”

7 So Joshua came suddenly, with all the warriors, against them by the waters of Merom, and attacked them. 8 Yahweh delivered them into the hand of Israel, and they struck them, and chased them to great Sidon, and to Misrephoth Maim, and to the valley of Mizpah eastward. They struck them until they left them no one remaining. 9 Joshua did to them as Yahweh told him. He hamstrung their horses and burned their chariots with fire. 10 Joshua turned back at that time, and took Hazor, and struck its king with the sword; for Hazor used to be the head of all those kingdoms. 11 They struck all the souls who were in it with the edge of the sword, utterly destroying them. There was no one left who breathed. He burned Hazor with fire. 12 Joshua captured all the cities of those kings, with their kings, and he struck them with the edge of the sword, and utterly destroyed them, as Moses the servant of Yahweh commanded. 13 But as for the cities that stood on their mounds, Israel burned none of them, except Hazor only. Joshua burned that. 14 The children of Israel took all the plunder of these cities, with the livestock, as plunder for themselves; but every man they struck with the edge of the sword, until they had destroyed them. They didn’t leave any who breathed.

15 As Yahweh commanded Moses his servant, so Moses commanded Joshua. Joshua did so. He left nothing undone of all that Yahweh commanded Moses. 16 So Joshua captured all that land, the hill country, all the South, all the land of Goshen, the lowland, the Arabah, the hill country of Israel, and the lowland of the same, 17 from Mount Halak, that goes up to Seir, even to Baal Gad in the valley of Lebanon under Mount Hermon. He took all their kings, struck them, and put them to death. 18 Joshua made war a long time with all those kings. 19 There was not a city that made peace with the children of Israel, except the Hivites, the inhabitants of Gibeon. They took all in battle. 20 For it was of Yahweh to harden their hearts, to come against Israel in battle, that he might utterly destroy them, that they might have no favor, but that he might destroy them, as Yahweh commanded Moses. 21 Joshua came at that time, and cut off the Anakim from the hill country, from Hebron, from Debir, from Anab, and from all the hill country of Judah, and from all the hill country of Israel. Joshua utterly destroyed them with their cities. 22 There were none of the Anakim left in the land of the children of Israel. Only in Gaza, in Gath, and in Ashdod, did some remain. 23 So Joshua took the whole land, according to all that Yahweh spoke to Moses; and Joshua gave it for an inheritance to Israel according to their divisions by their tribes. Then the land had rest from war.

12

1 Now these are the kings of the land, whom the children of Israel struck, and possessed their land beyond the Jordan toward the sunrise, from the valley of the Arnon to Mount Hermon, and all the Arabah eastward: 2 Sihon king of the Amorites, who lived in Heshbon, and ruled from Aroer, which is on the edge of the valley of the Arnon, and the middle of the valley, and half Gilead, even to the river Jabbok, the border of the children of Ammon; 3 and the Arabah to the sea of Chinneroth, eastward, and to the sea of the Arabah, even the Salt Sea, eastward, the way to Beth Jeshimoth; and on the south, under the slopes of Pisgah: 4 and the border of Og king of Bashan, of the remnant of the Rephaim, who lived at Ashtaroth and at Edrei, 5 and ruled in Mount Hermon, and in Salecah, and in all Bashan, to the border of the Geshurites and the Maacathites, and half Gilead, the border of Sihon king of Heshbon. 6 Moses the servant of Yahweh and the children of Israel struck them. Moses the servant of Yahweh gave it for a possession to the Reubenites, and the Gadites, and the half-tribe of Manasseh.

7 These are the kings of the land whom Joshua and the children of Israel struck beyond the Jordan westward, from Baal Gad in the valley of Lebanon even to Mount Halak, that goes up to Seir. Joshua gave it to the tribes of Israel for a possession according to their divisions; 8 in the hill country, and in the lowland, and in the Arabah, and in the slopes, and in the wilderness, and in the South; the Hittite, the Amorite, and the Canaanite, the Perizzite, the Hivite, and the Jebusite:

9 the king of Jericho, one;

the king of Ai, which is beside Bethel, one;

10 the king of Jerusalem, one;

the king of Hebron, one;

11 the king of Jarmuth, one;

the king of Lachish, one;

12 the king of Eglon, one;

the king of Gezer, one;

13 the king of Debir, one;

the king of Geder, one;

14 the king of Hormah, one;

the king of Arad, one;

15 the king of Libnah, one;

the king of Adullam, one;

16 the king of Makkedah, one;

the king of Bethel, one;

17 the king of Tappuah, one;

the king of Hepher, one;

18 the king of Aphek, one;

the king of Lassharon, one;

19 the king of Madon, one;

the king of Hazor, one;

20 the king of Shimron Meron, one;

the king of Achshaph, one;

21 the king of Taanach, one;

the king of Megiddo, one;

22 the king of Kedesh, one;

the king of Jokneam in Carmel, one;

23 the king of Dor in the height of Dor, one;

the king of Goiim in Gilgal, one;

24 the king of Tirzah, one:

all the kings thirty-one.

13

1 Now Joshua was old and well advanced in years. Yahweh said to him, “You are old and advanced in years, and there remains yet very much land to be possessed.

2 “This is the land that still remains: all the regions of the Philistines, and all the Geshurites; 3 from the Shihor, which is before Egypt, even to the border of Ekron northward, which is counted as Canaanite; the five lords of the Philistines; the Gazites, and the Ashdodites, the Ashkelonites, the Gittites, and the Ekronites; also the Avvim, 4 on the south; all the land of the Canaanites, and Mearah that belongs to the Sidonians, to Aphek, to the border of the Amorites; 5 and the land of the Gebalites, and all Lebanon, toward the sunrise, from Baal Gad under Mount Hermon to the entrance of Hamath; 6 all the inhabitants of the hill country from Lebanon to Misrephoth Maim, even all the Sidonians. I will drive them out from before the children of Israel. Just allocate it to Israel for an inheritance, as I have commanded you. 7 Now therefore divide this land for an inheritance to the nine tribes and the half-tribe of Manasseh.” 8 With him the Reubenites and the Gadites received their inheritance, which Moses gave them, beyond the Jordan eastward, even as Moses the servant of Yahweh gave them: 9 from Aroer, that is on the edge of the valley of the Arnon, and the city that is in the middle of the valley, and all the plain of Medeba to Dibon; 10 and all the cities of Sihon king of the Amorites, who reigned in Heshbon, to the border of the children of Ammon; 11 and Gilead, and the border of the Geshurites and Maacathites, and all Mount Hermon, and all Bashan to Salecah; 12 all the kingdom of Og in Bashan, who reigned in Ashtaroth and in Edrei (who was left of the remnant of the Rephaim); for Moses attacked these, and drove them out. 13 Nevertheless the children of Israel didn’t drive out the Geshurites, nor the Maacathites: but Geshur and Maacath live within Israel to this day. 14 Only he gave no inheritance to the tribe of Levi. The offerings of Yahweh, the God of Israel, made by fire are his inheritance, as he spoke to him. 15 Moses gave to the tribe of the children of Reuben according to their families. 16 Their border was from Aroer, that is on the edge of the valley of the Arnon, and the city that is in the middle of the valley, and all the plain by Medeba; 17 Heshbon, and all its cities that are in the plain; Dibon, Bamoth Baal, Beth Baal Meon, 18 Jahaz, Kedemoth, Mephaath, 19 Kiriathaim, Sibmah, Zereth Shahar in the mount of the valley, 20 Beth Peor, the slopes of Pisgah, Beth Jeshimoth, 21 all the cities of the plain, and all the kingdom of Sihon king of the Amorites, who reigned in Heshbon, whom Moses struck with the chiefs of Midian, Evi, Rekem, Zur, Hur, and Reba, the princes of Sihon, who lived in the land. 22 The children of Israel also killed Balaam the son of Beor, the soothsayer, with the sword, among the rest of their slain.

23 The border of the children of Reuben was the bank of the Jordan. This was the inheritance of the children of Reuben according to their families, the cities and its villages.

24 Moses gave to the tribe of Gad, to the children of Gad, according to their families. 25 Their border was Jazer, and all the cities of Gilead, and half the land of the children of Ammon, to Aroer that is near Rabbah; 26 and from Heshbon to Ramath Mizpeh, and Betonim; and from Mahanaim to the border of Debir; 27 and in the valley, Beth Haram, Beth Nimrah, Succoth, and Zaphon, the rest of the kingdom of Sihon king of Heshbon, the Jordan’s bank, to the uttermost part of the sea of Chinnereth beyond the Jordan eastward. 28 This is the inheritance of the children of Gad according to their families, the cities and its villages.

29 Moses gave an inheritance to the half-tribe of Manasseh. It was for the half-tribe of the children of Manasseh according to their families. 30 Their border was from Mahanaim, all Bashan, all the kingdom of Og king of Bashan, and all the villages of Jair, which are in Bashan, sixty cities. 31 Half Gilead, Ashtaroth, and Edrei, the cities of the kingdom of Og in Bashan, were for the children of Machir the son of Manasseh, even for the half of the children of Machir according to their families.

32 These are the inheritances which Moses distributed in the plains of Moab, beyond the Jordan at Jericho, eastward. 33 But Moses gave no inheritance to the tribe of Levi. Yahweh, the God of Israel, is their inheritance, as he spoke to them.

14

1 These are the inheritances which the children of Israel took in the land of Canaan, which Eleazar the priest, Joshua the son of Nun, and the heads of the fathers’ houses of the tribes of the children of Israel, distributed to them, 2 by the lot of their inheritance, as Yahweh commanded by Moses, for the nine tribes, and for the half-tribe. 3 For Moses had given the inheritance of the two tribes and the half-tribe beyond the Jordan; but to the Levites he gave no inheritance among them. 4 For the children of Joseph were two tribes, Manasseh and Ephraim. They gave no portion to the Levites in the land, except cities to dwell in, with their pasture lands for their livestock and for their property. 5 The children of Israel did as Yahweh commanded Moses, and they divided the land.

6 Then the children of Judah came near to Joshua in Gilgal. Caleb the son of Jephunneh the Kenizzite said to him, “You know the thing that Yahweh spoke to Moses the man of God concerning me and concerning you in Kadesh Barnea. 7 I was forty years old when Moses the servant of Yahweh sent me from Kadesh Barnea to spy out the land. I brought him word again as it was in my heart. 8 Nevertheless, my brothers who went up with me made the heart of the people melt; but I wholly followed Yahweh my God. 9 Moses swore on that day, saying, ‘Surely the land where you walked shall be an inheritance to you and to your children forever, because you have wholly followed Yahweh my God.’

10 “Now, behold, Yahweh has kept me alive, as he spoke, these forty-five years, from the time that Yahweh spoke this word to Moses, while Israel walked in the wilderness. Now, behold, I am eighty-five years old, today. 11 As yet I am as strong today as I was in the day that Moses sent me. As my strength was then, even so is my strength now for war, to go out and to come in. 12 Now therefore give me this hill country, of which Yahweh spoke in that day; for you heard in that day how the Anakim were there, and great and fortified cities. It may be that Yahweh will be with me, and I shall drive them out, as Yahweh said.”

13 Joshua blessed him; and he gave Hebron to Caleb the son of Jephunneh for an inheritance. 14 Therefore Hebron became the inheritance of Caleb the son of Jephunneh the Kenizzite to this day, because he followed Yahweh, the God of Israel wholeheartedly. 15 Now the name of Hebron before was Kiriath Arba, after the greatest man among the Anakim. Then the land had rest from war.

15

1 The lot for the tribe of the children of Judah according to their families was to the border of Edom, even to the wilderness of Zin southward, at the uttermost part of the south. 2 Their south border was from the uttermost part of the Salt Sea, from the bay that looks southward; 3 and it went out southward of the ascent of Akrabbim, and passed along to Zin, and went up by the south of Kadesh Barnea, and passed along by Hezron, went up to Addar, and turned toward Karka; 4 and it passed along to Azmon, went out at the brook of Egypt; and the border ended at the sea. This shall be your south border. 5 The east border was the Salt Sea, even to the end of the Jordan. The border of the north quarter was from the bay of the sea at the end of the Jordan. 6 The border went up to Beth Hoglah, and passed along by the north of Beth Arabah; and the border went up to the stone of Bohan the son of Reuben. 7 The border went up to Debir from the valley of Achor, and so northward, looking toward Gilgal, that faces the ascent of Adummim, which is on the south side of the river. The border passed along to the waters of En Shemesh, and ended at En Rogel. 8 The border went up by the valley of the son of Hinnom to the side of the Jebusite (also called Jerusalem) southward; and the border went up to the top of the mountain that lies before the valley of Hinnom westward, which is at the farthest part of the valley of Rephaim northward. 9 The border extended from the top of the mountain to the spring of the waters of Nephtoah, and went out to the cities of Mount Ephron; and the border extended to Baalah (also called Kiriath Jearim); 10 and the border turned about from Baalah westward to Mount Seir, and passed along to the side of Mount Jearim (also called Chesalon) on the north, and went down to Beth Shemesh, and passed along by Timnah; 11 and the border went out to the side of Ekron northward; and the border extended to Shikkeron, and passed along to Mount Baalah, and went out at Jabneel; and the goings out of the border were at the sea. 12 The west border was to the shore of the great sea. This is the border of the children of Judah according to their families.

13 He gave to Caleb the son of Jephunneh a portion among the children of Judah, according to the commandment of Yahweh to Joshua, even Kiriath Arba, named after the father of Anak (also called Hebron). 14 Caleb drove out the three sons of Anak: Sheshai, and Ahiman, and Talmai, the children of Anak. 15 He went up against the inhabitants of Debir: now the name of Debir before was Kiriath Sepher. 16 Caleb said, “He who strikes Kiriath Sepher, and takes it, to him I will give Achsah my daughter as wife.” 17 Othniel the son of Kenaz, the brother of Caleb, took it: and he gave him Achsah his daughter as wife. 18 When she came, she had him ask her father for a field. She got off her donkey, and Caleb said, “What do you want?”

19 She said, “Give me a blessing. Because you have set me in the land of the South, give me also springs of water.”

So he gave her the upper springs and the lower springs.

20 This is the inheritance of the tribe of the children of Judah according to their families. 21 The farthest cities of the tribe of the children of Judah toward the border of Edom in the South were Kabzeel, Eder, Jagur, 22 Kinah, Dimonah, Adadah, 23 Kedesh, Hazor, Ithnan, 24 Ziph, Telem, Bealoth, 25 Hazor Hadattah, Kerioth Hezron (also called Hazor), 26 Amam, Shema, Moladah, 27 Hazar Gaddah, Heshmon, Beth Pelet, 28 Hazar Shual, Beersheba, Biziothiah, 29 Baalah, Iim, Ezem, 30 Eltolad, Chesil, Hormah, 31 Ziklag, Madmannah, Sansannah, 32 Lebaoth, Shilhim, Ain, and Rimmon. All the cities are twenty-nine, with their villages.

33 In the lowland, Eshtaol, Zorah, Ashnah, 34 Zanoah, En Gannim, Tappuah, Enam, 35 Jarmuth, Adullam, Socoh, Azekah, 36 Shaaraim, Adithaim and Gederah (or Gederothaim); fourteen cities with their villages.

37 Zenan, Hadashah, Migdal Gad, 38 Dilean, Mizpah, Joktheel, 39 Lachish, Bozkath, Eglon, 40 Cabbon, Lahmam, Chitlish, 41 Gederoth, Beth Dagon, Naamah, and Makkedah; sixteen cities with their villages.

42 Libnah, Ether, Ashan, 43 Iphtah, Ashnah, Nezib, 44 Keilah, Achzib, and Mareshah; nine cities with their villages.

45 Ekron, with its towns and its villages; 46 from Ekron even to the sea, all that were by the side of Ashdod, with their villages. 47 Ashdod, its towns and its villages; Gaza, its towns and its villages; to the brook of Egypt, and the great sea with its coastline.

48 In the hill country, Shamir, Jattir, Socoh, 49 Dannah, Kiriath Sannah (which is Debir), 50 Anab, Eshtemoh, Anim, 51 Goshen, Holon, and Giloh; eleven cities with their villages.

52 Arab, Dumah, Eshan, 53 Janim, Beth Tappuah, Aphekah, 54 Humtah, Kiriath Arba (also called Hebron), and Zior; nine cities with their villages.

55 Maon, Carmel, Ziph, Jutah, 56 Jezreel, Jokdeam, Zanoah, 57 Kain, Gibeah, and Timnah; ten cities with their villages.

58 Halhul, Beth Zur, Gedor, 59 Maarath, Beth Anoth, and Eltekon; six cities with their villages. 60 Kiriath Baal (also called Kiriath Jearim), and Rabbah; two cities with their villages.

61 In the wilderness, Beth Arabah, Middin, Secacah, 62 Nibshan, the City of Salt, and En Gedi; six cities with their villages.

63 As for the Jebusites, the inhabitants of Jerusalem, the children of Judah couldn’t drive them out; but the Jebusites live with the children of Judah at Jerusalem to this day.

16

1 The lot came out for the children of Joseph from the Jordan at Jericho, at the waters of Jericho on the east, even the wilderness, going up from Jericho through the hill country to Bethel. 2 It went out from Bethel to Luz, and passed along to the border of the Archites to Ataroth; 3 and it went down westward to the border of the Japhletites, to the border of Beth Horon the lower, and on to Gezer; and ended at the sea.

4 The children of Joseph, Manasseh and Ephraim, took their inheritance. 5 This was the border of the children of Ephraim according to their families. The border of their inheritance eastward was Ataroth Addar, to Beth Horon the upper. 6 The border went out westward at Michmethath on the north. The border turned about eastward to Taanath Shiloh, and passed along it on the east of Janoah. 7 It went down from Janoah to Ataroth, to Naarah, reached to Jericho, and went out at the Jordan. 8 From Tappuah the border went along westward to the brook of Kanah; and ended at the sea. This is the inheritance of the tribe of the children of Ephraim according to their families; 9 together with the cities which were set apart for the children of Ephraim in the middle of the inheritance of the children of Manasseh, all the cities with their villages. 10 They didn’t drive out the Canaanites who lived in Gezer; but the Canaanites dwell in the territory of Ephraim to this day, and have become servants to do forced labor.

17

1 This was the lot for the tribe of Manasseh, for he was the firstborn of Joseph. As for Machir the firstborn of Manasseh, the father of Gilead, because he was a man of war, therefore he had Gilead and Bashan. 2 So this was for the rest of the children of Manasseh according to their families: for the children of Abiezer, for the children of Helek, for the children of Asriel, for the children of Shechem, for the children of Hepher, and for the children of Shemida. These were the male children of Manasseh the son of Joseph according to their families. 3 But Zelophehad, the son of Hepher, the son of Gilead, the son of Machir, the son of Manasseh, had no sons, but daughters. These are the names of his daughters: Mahlah, Noah, Hoglah, Milcah, and Tirzah. 4 They came to Eleazar the priest, and to Joshua the son of Nun, and to the princes, saying, “Yahweh commanded Moses to give us an inheritance among our brothers.” Therefore according to the commandment of Yahweh he gave them an inheritance among the brothers of their father. 5 Ten parts fell to Manasseh, in addition to the land of Gilead and Bashan, which is beyond the Jordan; 6 because the daughters of Manasseh had an inheritance among his sons. The land of Gilead belonged to the rest of the sons of Manasseh. 7 The border of Manasseh was from Asher to Michmethath, which is before Shechem. The border went along to the right hand, to the inhabitants of En Tappuah. 8 The land of Tappuah belonged to Manasseh; but Tappuah on the border of Manasseh belonged to the children of Ephraim. 9 The border went down to the brook of Kanah, southward of the brook. These cities belonged to Ephraim among the cities of Manasseh. The border of Manasseh was on the north side of the brook, and ended at the sea. 10 Southward it was Ephraim’s, and northward it was Manasseh’s, and the sea was his border. They reached to Asher on the north, and to Issachar on the east. 11 Manasseh had three heights in Issachar, in Asher Beth Shean and its towns, and Ibleam and its towns, and the inhabitants of Dor and its towns, and the inhabitants of Endor and its towns, and the inhabitants of Taanach and its towns, and the inhabitants of Megiddo and its towns. 12 Yet the children of Manasseh couldn’t drive out the inhabitants of those cities; but the Canaanites would dwell in that land.

13 When the children of Israel had grown strong, they put the Canaanites to forced labor, and didn’t utterly drive them out. 14 The children of Joseph spoke to Joshua, saying, “Why have you given me just one lot and one part for an inheritance, since we are a numerous people, because Yahweh has blessed us so far?”

15 Joshua said to them, “If you are a numerous people, go up to the forest, and clear land for yourself there in the land of the Perizzites and of the Rephaim, since the hill country of Ephraim is too narrow for you.”

16 The children of Joseph said, “The hill country is not enough for us. All the Canaanites who dwell in the land of the valley have chariots of iron, both those who are in Beth Shean and its towns, and those who are in the valley of Jezreel.”

17 Joshua spoke to the house of Joseph, that is, to Ephraim and to Manasseh, saying, “You are a numerous people, and have great power. You shall not have one lot only; 18 but the hill country shall be yours. Although it is a forest, you shall cut it down, and it’s farthest extent shall be yours; for you shall drive out the Canaanites, though they have chariots of iron, and though they are strong.”

18

1 The whole congregation of the children of Israel assembled themselves together at Shiloh, and set up the Tent of Meeting there. The land was subdued before them. 2 Seven tribes remained among the children of Israel, which had not yet divided their inheritance. 3 Joshua said to the children of Israel, “How long will you neglect to go in to possess the land, which Yahweh, the God of your fathers, has given you? 4 Appoint for yourselves three men from each tribe. I will send them, and they shall arise, walk through the land, and describe it according to their inheritance; then they shall come to me. 5 They shall divide it into seven portions. Judah shall live in his borders on the south, and the house of Joseph shall live in their borders on the north. 6 You shall survey the land into seven parts, and bring the description here to me; and I will cast lots for you here before Yahweh our God. 7 However, the Levites have no portion among you; for the priesthood of Yahweh is their inheritance. Gad, Reuben, and the half-tribe of Manasseh have received their inheritance east of the Jordan, which Moses the servant of Yahweh gave them.”

8 The men arose and went. Joshua commanded those who went to survey the land, saying, “Go walk through the land, survey it, and come again to me. I will cast lots for you here before Yahweh in Shiloh.”

9 The men went and passed through the land, and surveyed it by cities into seven portions in a book. They came to Joshua to the camp at Shiloh. 10 Joshua cast lots for them in Shiloh before Yahweh. There Joshua divided the land to the children of Israel according to their divisions.

11 The lot of the tribe of the children of Benjamin came up according to their families. The border of their lot went out between the children of Judah and the children of Joseph. 12 Their border on the north quarter was from the Jordan. The border went up to the side of Jericho on the north, and went up through the hill country westward. It ended at the wilderness of Beth Aven. 13 The border passed along from there to Luz, to the side of Luz (also called Bethel), southward. The border went down to Ataroth Addar, by the mountain that lies on the south of Beth Horon the lower. 14 The border extended, and turned around on the west quarter southward, from the mountain that lies before Beth Horon southward; and ended at Kiriath Baal (also called Kiriath Jearim), a city of the children of Judah. This was the west quarter. 15 The south quarter was from the farthest part of Kiriath Jearim. The border went out westward, and went out to the spring of the waters of Nephtoah. 16 The border went down to the farthest part of the mountain that lies before the valley of the son of Hinnom, which is in the valley of Rephaim northward. It went down to the valley of Hinnom, to the side of the Jebusite southward, and went down to En Rogel. 17 It extended northward, went out at En Shemesh, and went out to Geliloth, which is opposite the ascent of Adummim. It went down to the stone of Bohan the son of Reuben. 18 It passed along to the side opposite the Arabah northward, and went down to the Arabah. 19 The border passed along to the side of Beth Hoglah northward; and the border ended at the north bay of the Salt Sea, at the south end of the Jordan. This was the south border. 20 The Jordan was its border on the east quarter. This was the inheritance of the children of Benjamin, by the borders around it, according to their families. 21 Now the cities of the tribe of the children of Benjamin according to their families were Jericho, Beth Hoglah, Emek Keziz, 22 Beth Arabah, Zemaraim, Bethel, 23 Avvim, Parah, Ophrah, 24 Chephar Ammoni, Ophni, and Geba; twelve cities with their villages. 25 Gibeon, Ramah, Beeroth, 26 Mizpeh, Chephirah, Mozah, 27 Rekem, Irpeel, Taralah, 28 Zelah, Eleph, the Jebusite (also called Jerusalem), Gibeath, and Kiriath; fourteen cities with their villages. This is the inheritance of the children of Benjamin according to their families.

19

1 The second lot came out for Simeon, even for the tribe of the children of Simeon according to their families. Their inheritance was in the middle of the inheritance of the children of Judah. 2 They had for their inheritance Beersheba (or Sheba), Moladah, 3 Hazar Shual, Balah, Ezem, 4 Eltolad, Bethul, Hormah, 5 Ziklag, Beth Marcaboth, Hazar Susah, 6 Beth Lebaoth, and Sharuhen; thirteen cities with their villages; 7 Ain, Rimmon, Ether, and Ashan; four cities with their villages; 8 and all the villages that were around these cities to Baalath Beer, Ramah of the South. This is the inheritance of the tribe of the children of Simeon according to their families. 9 Out of the part of the children of Judah was the inheritance of the children of Simeon; for the portion of the children of Judah was too much for them. Therefore the children of Simeon had inheritance in the middle of their inheritance.

10 The third lot came up for the children of Zebulun according to their families. The border of their inheritance was to Sarid. 11 Their border went up westward, even to Maralah, and reached to Dabbesheth. It reached to the brook that is before Jokneam. 12 It turned from Sarid eastward toward the sunrise to the border of Chisloth Tabor. It went out to Daberath, and went up to Japhia. 13 From there it passed along eastward to Gath Hepher, to Ethkazin; and it went out at Rimmon which stretches to Neah. 14 The border turned around it on the north to Hannathon; and it ended at the valley of Iphtah El; 15 Kattath, Nahalal, Shimron, Idalah, and Bethlehem: twelve cities with their villages. 16 This is the inheritance of the children of Zebulun according to their families, these cities with their villages.

17 The fourth lot came out for Issachar, even for the children of Issachar according to their families. 18 Their border was to Jezreel, Chesulloth, Shunem, 19 Hapharaim, Shion, Anaharath, 20 Rabbith, Kishion, Ebez, 21 Remeth, Engannim, En Haddah, and Beth Pazzez. 22 The border reached to Tabor, Shahazumah, and Beth Shemesh. Their border ended at the Jordan: sixteen cities with their villages. 23 This is the inheritance of the tribe of the children of Issachar according to their families, the cities with their villages.

24 The fifth lot came out for the tribe of the children of Asher according to their families. 25 Their border was Helkath, Hali, Beten, Achshaph, 26 Allammelech, Amad, Mishal. It reached to Carmel westward, and to Shihorlibnath. 27 It turned toward the sunrise to Beth Dagon, and reached to Zebulun, and to the valley of Iphtah El northward to Beth Emek and Neiel. It went out to Cabul on the left hand, 28 and Ebron, Rehob, Hammon, and Kanah, even to great Sidon. 29 The border turned to Ramah, to the fortified city of Tyre; and the border turned to Hosah. It ended at the sea by the region of Achzib; 30 Ummah also, and Aphek, and Rehob: twenty-two cities with their villages. 31 This is the inheritance of the tribe of the children of Asher according to their families, these cities with their villages.

32 The sixth lot came out for the children of Naphtali, even for the children of Naphtali according to their families. 33 Their border was from Heleph, from the oak in Zaanannim, Adami-nekeb, and Jabneel, to Lakkum. It ended at the Jordan. 34 The border turned westward to Aznoth Tabor, and went out from there to Hukkok. It reached to Zebulun on the south, and reached to Asher on the west, and to Judah at the Jordan toward the sunrise. 35 The fortified cities were Ziddim, Zer, Hammath, Rakkath, Chinnereth, 36 Adamah, Ramah, Hazor, 37 Kedesh, Edrei, En Hazor, 38 Iron, Migdal El, Horem, Beth Anath, and Beth Shemesh; nineteen cities with their villages. 39 This is the inheritance of the tribe of the children of Naphtali according to their families, the cities with their villages.

40 The seventh lot came out for the tribe of the children of Dan according to their families. 41 The border of their inheritance was Zorah, Eshtaol, Irshemesh, 42 Shaalabbin, Aijalon, Ithlah, 43 Elon, Timnah, Ekron, 44 Eltekeh, Gibbethon, Baalath, 45 Jehud, Bene Berak, Gath Rimmon, 46 Me Jarkon, and Rakkon, with the border opposite Joppa. 47 The border of the children of Dan went out beyond them; for the children of Dan went up and fought against Leshem, and took it, and struck it with the edge of the sword, and possessed it, and lived therein, and called Leshem, Dan, after the name of Dan their forefather. 48 This is the inheritance of the tribe of the children of Dan according to their families, these cities with their villages.

49 So they finished distributing the land for inheritance by its borders. The children of Israel gave an inheritance to Joshua the son of Nun among them. 50 According to Yahweh’s commandment, they gave him the city which he asked, even Timnathserah in the hill country of Ephraim; and he built the city, and lived there. 51 These are the inheritances, which Eleazar the priest, Joshua the son of Nun, and the heads of the fathers’ houses of the tribes of the children of Israel, distributed for inheritance by lot in Shiloh before Yahweh, at the door of the Tent of Meeting. So they finished dividing the land.

20

1 Yahweh spoke to Joshua, saying, 2 “Speak to the children of Israel, saying, ‘Assign the cities of refuge, of which I spoke to you by Moses, 3 that the man slayer who kills any person accidentally or unintentionally may flee there. They shall be to you for a refuge from the avenger of blood. 4 He shall flee to one of those cities, and shall stand at the entrance of the gate of the city, and declare his case in the ears of the elders of that city. They shall take him into the city with them, and give him a place, that he may live among them. 5 If the avenger of blood pursues him, then they shall not deliver up the man slayer into his hand; because he struck his neighbor unintentionally, and didn’t hate him before. 6 He shall dwell in that city until he stands before the congregation for judgment, until the death of the high priest that shall be in those days. Then the man slayer shall return, and come to his own city, and to his own house, to the city he fled from.’ ”

7 They set apart Kedesh in Galilee in the hill country of Naphtali, Shechem in the hill country of Ephraim, and Kiriath Arba (also called Hebron) in the hill country of Judah. 8 Beyond the Jordan at Jericho eastward, they assigned Bezer in the wilderness in the plain out of the tribe of Reuben, Ramoth in Gilead out of the tribe of Gad, and Golan in Bashan out of the tribe of Manasseh. 9 These were the appointed cities for all the children of Israel, and for the alien who lives among them, that whoever kills any person unintentionally might flee there, and not die by the hand of the avenger of blood, until he stands trial before the congregation.

21

1 Then the heads of fathers’ houses of the Levites came near to Eleazar the priest, and to Joshua the son of Nun, and to the heads of fathers’ houses of the tribes of the children of Israel. 2 They spoke to them at Shiloh in the land of Canaan, saying, “Yahweh commanded through Moses to give us cities to dwell in, with their pasture lands for our livestock.”

3 The children of Israel gave to the Levites out of their inheritance, according to the commandment of Yahweh, these cities with their pasture lands. 4 The lot came out for the families of the Kohathites. The children of Aaron the priest, who were of the Levites, had thirteen cities by lot out of the tribe of Judah, out of the tribe of the Simeonites, and out of the tribe of Benjamin. 5 The rest of the children of Kohath had ten cities by lot out of the families of the tribe of Ephraim, out of the tribe of Dan, and out of the half-tribe of Manasseh. 6 The children of Gershon had thirteen cities by lot out of the families of the tribe of Issachar, out of the tribe of Asher, out of the tribe of Naphtali, and out of the half-tribe of Manasseh in Bashan. 7 The children of Merari according to their families had twelve cities out of the tribe of Reuben, out of the tribe of Gad, and out of the tribe of Zebulun. 8 The children of Israel gave these cities with their pasture lands by lot to the Levites, as Yahweh commanded by Moses. 9 They gave out of the tribe of the children of Judah, and out of the tribe of the children of Simeon, these cities which are mentioned by name: 10 and they were for the children of Aaron, of the families of the Kohathites, who were of the children of Levi; for theirs was the first lot. 11 They gave them Kiriath Arba, named after the father of Anak (also called Hebron), in the hill country of Judah, with its pasture lands around it. 12 But they gave the fields of the city and its villages to Caleb the son of Jephunneh for his possession. 13 To the children of Aaron the priest they gave Hebron with its pasture lands, the city of refuge for the man slayer, Libnah with its pasture lands, 14 Jattir with its pasture lands, Eshtemoa with its pasture lands, 15 Holon with its pasture lands, Debir with its pasture lands, 16 Ain with its pasture lands, Juttah with its pasture lands, and Beth Shemesh with its pasture lands: nine cities out of those two tribes. 17 Out of the tribe of Benjamin, Gibeon with its pasture lands, Geba with its pasture lands, 18 Anathoth with its pasture lands, and Almon with its pasture lands: four cities. 19 All the cities of the children of Aaron, the priests, were thirteen cities with their pasture lands.

20 The families of the children of Kohath, the Levites, even the rest of the children of Kohath, had the cities of their lot out of the tribe of Ephraim. 21 They gave them Shechem with its pasture lands in the hill country of Ephraim, the city of refuge for the man slayer, and Gezer with its pasture lands, 22 Kibzaim with its pasture lands, and Beth Horon with its pasture lands: four cities. 23 Out of the tribe of Dan, Elteke with its pasture lands, Gibbethon with its pasture lands, 24 Aijalon with its pasture lands, Gath Rimmon with its pasture lands: four cities. 25 Out of the half-tribe of Manasseh, Taanach with its pasture lands, and Gath Rimmon with its pasture lands: two cities. 26 All the cities of the families of the rest of the children of Kohath were ten with their pasture lands.

27 They gave to the children of Gershon, of the families of the Levites, out of the half-tribe of Manasseh Golan in Bashan with its pasture lands, the city of refuge for the man slayer, and Be Eshterah with its pasture lands: two cities. 28 Out of the tribe of Issachar, Kishion with its pasture lands, Daberath with its pasture lands, 29 Jarmuth with its pasture lands, En Gannim with its pasture lands: four cities. 30 Out of the tribe of Asher, Mishal with its pasture lands, Abdon with its pasture lands, 31 Helkath with its pasture lands, and Rehob with its pasture lands: four cities. 32 Out of the tribe of Naphtali, Kedesh in Galilee with its pasture lands, the city of refuge for the man slayer, Hammothdor with its pasture lands, and Kartan with its pasture lands: three cities. 33 All the cities of the Gershonites according to their families were thirteen cities with their pasture lands.

34 To the families of the children of Merari, the rest of the Levites, out of the tribe of Zebulun, Jokneam with its pasture lands, Kartah with its pasture lands, 35 Dimnah with its pasture lands, and Nahalal with its pasture lands: four cities. 36 Out of the tribe of Reuben, Bezer with its pasture lands, Jahaz with its pasture lands, 37 Kedemoth with its pasture lands, and Mephaath with its pasture lands: four cities. 38 Out of the tribe of Gad, Ramoth in Gilead with its pasture lands, the city of refuge for the man slayer, and Mahanaim with its pasture lands, 39 Heshbon with its pasture lands, Jazer with its pasture lands: four cities in all. 40 All these were the cities of the children of Merari according to their families, even the rest of the families of the Levites. Their lot was twelve cities.

41 All the cities of the Levites among the possessions of the children of Israel were forty-eight cities with their pasture lands. 42 Each of these cities included their pasture lands around them. It was this way with all these cities.

43 So Yahweh gave to Israel all the land which he swore to give to their fathers. They possessed it, and lived in it. 44 Yahweh gave them rest all around, according to all that he swore to their fathers. Not a man of all their enemies stood before them. Yahweh delivered all their enemies into their hand. 45 Nothing failed of any good thing which Yahweh had spoken to the house of Israel. All came to pass.

22

1 Then Joshua called the Reubenites, the Gadites, and the half-tribe of Manasseh, 2 and said to them, “You have kept all that Moses the servant of Yahweh commanded you, and have listened to my voice in all that I commanded you. 3 You have not left your brothers these many days to this day, but have performed the duty of the commandment of Yahweh your God. 4 Now Yahweh your God has given rest to your brothers, as he spoke to them. Therefore now return and go to your tents, to the land of your possession, which Moses the servant of Yahweh gave you beyond the Jordan. 5 Only take diligent heed to do the commandment and the law which Moses the servant of Yahweh commanded you, to love Yahweh your God, to walk in all his ways, to keep his commandments, to hold fast to him, and to serve him with all your heart and with all your soul.”

6 So Joshua blessed them, and sent them away; and they went to their tents. 7 Now to the one half-tribe of Manasseh Moses had given inheritance in Bashan; but Joshua gave to the other half among their brothers beyond the Jordan westward. Moreover when Joshua sent them away to their tents, he blessed them, 8 and spoke to them, saying, “Return with much wealth to your tents, with very much livestock, with silver, with gold, with bronze, with iron, and with very much clothing. Divide the plunder of your enemies with your brothers.”

9 The children of Reuben and the children of Gad and the half-tribe of Manasseh returned, and departed from the children of Israel out of Shiloh, which is in the land of Canaan, to go to the land of Gilead, to the land of their possession, which they owned, according to the commandment of Yahweh by Moses. 10 When they came to the region near the Jordan, that is in the land of Canaan, the children of Reuben and the children of Gad and the half-tribe of Manasseh built an altar there by the Jordan, a great altar to look at. 11 The children of Israel heard this, “Behold, the children of Reuben and the children of Gad and the half-tribe of Manasseh have built an altar along the border of the land of Canaan, in the region around the Jordan, on the side that belongs to the children of Israel.” 12 When the children of Israel heard of it, the whole congregation of the children of Israel gathered themselves together at Shiloh, to go up against them to war. 13 The children of Israel sent to the children of Reuben, and to the children of Gad, and to the half-tribe of Manasseh, into the land of Gilead, Phinehas the son of Eleazar the priest. 14 With him were ten princes, one prince of a fathers’ house for each of the tribes of Israel; and they were each head of their fathers’ houses among the thousands of Israel. 15 They came to the children of Reuben, and to the children of Gad, and to the half-tribe of Manasseh, to the land of Gilead, and they spoke with them, saying, 16 “The whole congregation of Yahweh says, ‘What trespass is this that you have committed against the God of Israel, to turn away today from following Yahweh, in that you have built yourselves an altar, to rebel today against Yahweh? 17 Is the iniquity of Peor too little for us, from which we have not cleansed ourselves to this day, although there came a plague on the congregation of Yahweh, 18 that you must turn away today from following Yahweh? It will be, since you rebel today against Yahweh, that tomorrow he will be angry with the whole congregation of Israel. 19 However, if the land of your possession is unclean, then pass over to the land of the possession of Yahweh, in which Yahweh’s tabernacle dwells, and take possession among us; but don’t rebel against Yahweh, nor rebel against us, in building an altar other than Yahweh our God’s altar. 20 Didn’t Achan the son of Zerah commit a trespass in the devoted thing, and wrath fell on all the congregation of Israel? That man didn’t perish alone in his iniquity.’ ”

21 Then the children of Reuben and the children of Gad and the half-tribe of Manasseh answered, and spoke to the heads of the thousands of Israel, 22 “The Mighty One, God, Yahweh, the Mighty One, God, Yahweh, he knows; and Israel shall know: if it was in rebellion, or if in trespass against Yahweh (don’t save us today), 23 that we have built us an altar to turn away from following Yahweh; or if to offer burnt offering or meal offering, or if to offer sacrifices of peace offerings, let Yahweh himself require it.

24 “If we have not out of concern done this, and for a reason, saying, ‘In time to come your children might speak to our children, saying, “What have you to do with Yahweh, the God of Israel? 25 For Yahweh has made the Jordan a border between us and you, you children of Reuben and children of Gad. You have no portion in Yahweh.” ’ So your children might make our children cease from fearing Yahweh.

26 “Therefore we said, ‘Let’s now prepare to build ourselves an altar, not for burnt offering, nor for sacrifice; 27 but it will be a witness between us and you, and between our generations after us, that we may perform the service of Yahweh before him with our burnt offerings, with our sacrifices, and with our peace offerings;’ that your children may not tell our children in time to come, ‘You have no portion in Yahweh.’

28 “Therefore we said, ‘It shall be, when they tell us or our generations this in time to come, that we shall say, “Behold the pattern of Yahweh’s altar, which our fathers made, not for burnt offering, nor for sacrifice; but it is a witness between us and you.” ’

29 “Far be it from us that we should rebel against Yahweh, and turn away today from following Yahweh, to build an altar for burnt offering, for meal offering, or for sacrifice, besides Yahweh our God’s altar that is before his tabernacle!”

30 When Phinehas the priest, and the princes of the congregation, even the heads of the thousands of Israel that were with him, heard the words that the children of Reuben and the children of Gad and the children of Manasseh spoke, it pleased them well. 31 Phinehas the son of Eleazar the priest said to the children of Reuben, to the children of Gad, and to the children of Manasseh, “Today we know that Yahweh is among us, because you have not committed this trespass against Yahweh. Now you have delivered the children of Israel out of Yahweh’s hand.” 32 Phinehas the son of Eleazar the priest, and the princes, returned from the children of Reuben, and from the children of Gad, out of the land of Gilead, to the land of Canaan, to the children of Israel, and brought them word again. 33 The thing pleased the children of Israel; and the children of Israel blessed God, and spoke no more of going up against them to war, to destroy the land in which the children of Reuben and the children of Gad lived. 34 The children of Reuben and the children of Gad named the altar “A Witness Between Us that Yahweh is God.”

23

1 After many days, when Yahweh had given rest to Israel from their enemies all around, and Joshua was old and well advanced in years, 2 Joshua called for all Israel, for their elders and for their heads, and for their judges and for their officers, and said to them, “I am old and well advanced in years. 3 You have seen all that Yahweh your God has done to all these nations because of you; for it is Yahweh your God who has fought for you. 4 Behold, I have allotted to you these nations that remain, to be an inheritance for your tribes, from the Jordan, with all the nations that I have cut off, even to the great sea toward the going down of the sun. 5 Yahweh your God will thrust them out from before you, and drive them from out of your sight. You shall possess their land, as Yahweh your God spoke to you.

6 “Therefore be very courageous to keep and to do all that is written in the book of the law of Moses, that you not turn away from it to the right hand or to the left; 7 that you not come among these nations, these that remain among you; neither make mention of the name of their gods, nor cause to swear by them, neither serve them, nor bow down yourselves to them; 8 but hold fast to Yahweh your God, as you have done to this day.

9 “For Yahweh has driven great and strong nations out from before you. But as for you, no man has stood before you to this day. 10 One man of you shall chase a thousand; for it is Yahweh your God who fights for you, as he spoke to you. 11 Take good heed therefore to yourselves, that you love Yahweh your God.

12 “But if you do at all go back, and hold fast to the remnant of these nations, even these who remain among you, and make marriages with them, and go in to them, and they to you; 13 know for a certainty that Yahweh your God will no longer drive these nations from out of your sight; but they shall be a snare and a trap to you, a scourge in your sides, and thorns in your eyes, until you perish from off this good land which Yahweh your God has given you.

14 “Behold, today I am going the way of all the earth. You know in all your hearts and in all your souls that not one thing has failed of all the good things which Yahweh your God spoke concerning you. All have happened to you. Not one thing has failed of it. 15 It shall happen that as all the good things have come on you of which Yahweh your God spoke to you, so Yahweh will bring on you all the evil things, until he has destroyed you from off this good land which Yahweh your God has given you, 16 when you disobey the covenant of Yahweh your God, which he commanded you, and go and serve other gods, and bow down yourselves to them. Then Yahweh’s anger will be kindled against you, and you will perish quickly from off the good land which he has given to you.”

24

1 Joshua gathered all the tribes of Israel to Shechem, and called for the elders of Israel, for their heads, for their judges, and for their officers; and they presented themselves before God. 2 Joshua said to all the people, “Yahweh, the God of Israel, says, ‘Your fathers lived of old time beyond the River, even Terah, the father of Abraham, and the father of Nahor. They served other gods. 3 I took your father Abraham from beyond the River, and led him throughout all the land of Canaan, and multiplied his offspring,[*] and gave him Isaac. 4 I gave to Isaac Jacob and Esau: and I gave to Esau Mount Seir, to possess it. Jacob and his children went down into Egypt.

5 “ ‘I sent Moses and Aaron, and I plagued Egypt, according to that which I did among them: and afterward I brought you out. 6 I brought your fathers out of Egypt: and you came to the sea. The Egyptians pursued your fathers with chariots and with horsemen to the Red Sea. 7 When they cried out to Yahweh, he put darkness between you and the Egyptians, and brought the sea on them, and covered them; and your eyes saw what I did in Egypt. You lived in the wilderness many days.

8 “ ‘I brought you into the land of the Amorites, that lived beyond the Jordan. They fought with you, and I gave them into your hand. You possessed their land, and I destroyed them from before you. 9 Then Balak the son of Zippor, king of Moab, arose and fought against Israel. He sent and called Balaam the son of Beor to curse you, 10 but I would not listen to Balaam; therefore he blessed you still. So I delivered you out of his hand.

11 “ ‘You went over the Jordan, and came to Jericho. The men of Jericho fought against you, the Amorite, the Perizzite, the Canaanite, the Hittite, the Girgashite, the Hivite, and the Jebusite; and I delivered them into your hand. 12 I sent the hornet before you, which drove them out from before you, even the two kings of the Amorites; not with your sword, nor with your bow. 13 I gave you a land on which you had not labored, and cities which you didn’t build, and you live in them. You eat of vineyards and olive groves which you didn’t plant.’

14 “Now therefore fear Yahweh, and serve him in sincerity and in truth. Put away the gods which your fathers served beyond the River, in Egypt; and serve Yahweh. 15 If it seems evil to you to serve Yahweh, choose today whom you will serve; whether the gods which your fathers served that were beyond the River, or the gods of the Amorites, in whose land you dwell; but as for me and my house, we will serve Yahweh.”

16 The people answered, “Far be it from us that we should forsake Yahweh, to serve other gods; 17 for it is Yahweh our God who brought us and our fathers up out of the land of Egypt, from the house of bondage, and who did those great signs in our sight, and preserved us in all the way in which we went, and among all the peoples through the middle of whom we passed. 18 Yahweh drove out from before us all the peoples, even the Amorites who lived in the land. Therefore we also will serve Yahweh; for he is our God.”

19 Joshua said to the people, “You can’t serve Yahweh, for he is a holy God. He is a jealous God. He will not forgive your disobedience nor your sins. 20 If you forsake Yahweh, and serve foreign gods, then he will turn and do you evil, and consume you, after he has done you good.”

21 The people said to Joshua, “No, but we will serve Yahweh.” 22 Joshua said to the people, “You are witnesses against yourselves that you have chosen Yahweh yourselves, to serve him.”

They said, “We are witnesses.”

23 “Now therefore put away the foreign gods which are among you, and incline your heart to Yahweh, the God of Israel.”

24 The people said to Joshua, “We will serve Yahweh our God, and we will listen to his voice.”

25 So Joshua made a covenant with the people that day, and made for them a statute and an ordinance in Shechem. 26 Joshua wrote these words in the book of the law of God; and he took a great stone, and set it up there under the oak that was by the sanctuary of Yahweh. 27 Joshua said to all the people, “Behold, this stone shall be a witness against us, for it has heard all Yahweh’s words which he spoke to us. It shall be therefore a witness against you, lest you deny your God.” 28 So Joshua sent the people away, each to his own inheritance.

29 After these things, Joshua the son of Nun, the servant of Yahweh, died, being one hundred ten years old. 30 They buried him in the border of his inheritance in Timnathserah, which is in the hill country of Ephraim, on the north of the mountain of Gaash. 31 Israel served Yahweh all the days of Joshua, and all the days of the elders who outlived Joshua, and had known all the work of Yahweh, that he had worked for Israel. 32 They buried the bones of Joseph, which the children of Israel brought up out of Egypt, in Shechem, in the parcel of ground which Jacob bought from the sons of Hamor the father of Shechem for a hundred pieces of silver.[†] They became the inheritance of the children of Joseph. 33 Eleazar the son of Aaron died. They buried him in the hill of Phinehas his son, which was given him in the hill country of Ephraim.

* 1:1 “Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

† 1:9 The Hebrew word rendered “God” is “אֱלֹהִ֑ים” (Elohim).

* 2:2 “Behold”, from “הִנֵּה”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.

* 3:4 A cubit is the length from the tip of the middle finger to the elbow on a man’s arm, or about 18 inches or 46 centimeters, so 2,000 cubits is about 920 meters.

† 3:11 The word translated “Lord” is “Adonai.”

* 5:9 “Gilgal” sounds like the Hebrew for “roll.”

* 7:21 A shekel is about 10 grams or about 0.35 ounces.

* 24:3 or, seed

† 24:32 Hebrew: kesitahs. A kesitah was a kind of silver coin.

Lamentations

1
2
3
4
5

The

Lamentations

of Jeremiah

1

1 How the city sits solitary,

that was full of people!

She has become as a widow,

who was great among the nations!

She who was a princess among the provinces

has become a slave!

2 She weeps bitterly in the night.

Her tears are on her cheeks.

Among all her lovers

she has no one to comfort her.

All her friends have dealt treacherously with her.

They have become her enemies.

3 Judah has gone into captivity because of affliction

and because of great servitude.

She dwells among the nations.

She finds no rest.

All her persecutors overtook her in her distress.

4 The roads to Zion mourn,

because no one comes to the solemn assembly.

All her gates are desolate.

Her priests sigh.

Her virgins are afflicted,

and she herself is in bitterness.

5 Her adversaries have become the head.

Her enemies prosper;

for Yahweh[*] has afflicted her for the multitude of her transgressions.

Her young children have gone into captivity before the adversary.

6 All majesty has departed from the daughter of Zion.

Her princes have become like deer that find no pasture.

They have gone without strength before the pursuer.

7 Jerusalem remembers in the days of her affliction and of her miseries

all her pleasant things that were from the days of old;

when her people fell into the hand of the adversary,

and no one helped her.

The adversaries saw her.

They mocked at her desolations.

8 Jerusalem has grievously sinned.

Therefore she has become unclean.

All who honored her despise her,

because they have seen her nakedness.

Yes, she sighs and turns backward.

9 Her filthiness was in her skirts.

She didn’t remember her latter end.

Therefore she has come down astoundingly.

She has no comforter.

“See, Yahweh, my affliction;

for the enemy has magnified himself.”

10 The adversary has spread out his hand on all her pleasant things;

for she has seen that the nations have entered into her sanctuary,

concerning whom you commanded that they should not enter into your assembly.

11 All her people sigh.

They seek bread.

They have given their pleasant things for food to refresh their soul.

“Look, Yahweh, and see,

for I have become despised.”

12 “Is it nothing to you, all you who pass by?

Look, and see if there is any sorrow like my sorrow,

which is brought on me,

with which Yahweh has afflicted me in the day of his fierce anger.

13 “From on high has he sent fire into my bones,

and it prevails against them.

He has spread a net for my feet.

He has turned me back.

He has made me desolate and I faint all day long.

14 “The yoke of my transgressions is bound by his hand.

They are knit together.

They have come up on my neck.

He made my strength fail.

The Lord[†] has delivered me into their hands,

against whom I am not able to stand.

15 “The Lord has set at nothing all my mighty men within me.

He has called a solemn assembly against me to crush my young men.

The Lord has trodden the virgin daughter of Judah as in a wine press.

16 “For these things I weep.

My eye, my eye runs down with water,

because the comforter who should refresh my soul is far from me.

My children are desolate,

because the enemy has prevailed.”

17 Zion spreads out her hands.

There is no one to comfort her.

Yahweh has commanded concerning Jacob,

that those who are around him should be his adversaries.

Jerusalem is among them as an unclean thing.

18 “Yahweh is righteous,

for I have rebelled against his commandment.

Please hear all you peoples,

and see my sorrow.

My virgins and my young men have gone into captivity.

19 “I called for my lovers,

but they deceived me.

My priests and my elders gave up the spirit in the city,

while they sought food for themselves to refresh their souls.

20 “Look, Yahweh; for I am in distress.

My heart is troubled.

My heart turns over within me,

for I have grievously rebelled.

Abroad, the sword bereaves.

At home, it is like death.

21 “They have heard that I sigh.

There is no one to comfort me.

All my enemies have heard of my trouble.

They are glad that you have done it.

You will bring the day that you have proclaimed,

and they will be like me.

22 “Let all their wickedness come before you.

Do to them as you have done to me for all my transgressions.

For my sighs are many,

and my heart is faint.

2

1 How has the Lord covered the daughter of Zion with a cloud in his anger!

He has cast the beauty of Israel down from heaven to the earth,

and hasn’t remembered his footstool in the day of his anger.

2 The Lord has swallowed up all the dwellings of Jacob

without pity.

He has thrown down in his wrath the strongholds of the daughter of Judah.

He has brought them down to the ground.

He has profaned the kingdom and its princes.

3 He has cut off all the horn of Israel in fierce anger.

He has drawn back his right hand from before the enemy.

He has burned up Jacob like a flaming fire,

which devours all around.

4 He has bent his bow like an enemy.

He has stood with his right hand as an adversary.

He has killed all that were pleasant to the eye.

In the tent of the daughter of Zion, he has poured out his wrath like fire.

5 The Lord has become as an enemy.

He has swallowed up Israel.

He has swallowed up all her palaces.

He has destroyed his strongholds.

He has multiplied mourning and lamentation in the daughter of Judah.

6 He has violently taken away his tabernacle,

as if it were a garden.

He has destroyed his place of assembly.

Yahweh has caused solemn assembly and Sabbath to be forgotten in Zion.

In the indignation of his anger, he has despised the king and the priest.

7 The Lord has cast off his altar.

He has abhorred his sanctuary.

He has given the walls of her palaces into the hand of the enemy.

They have made a noise in Yahweh’s house,

as in the day of a solemn assembly.

8 Yahweh has purposed to destroy the wall of the daughter of Zion.

He has stretched out the line.

He has not withdrawn his hand from destroying;

He has made the rampart and wall lament.

They languish together.

9 Her gates have sunk into the ground.

He has destroyed and broken her bars.

Her king and her princes are among the nations where the law is not.

Yes, her prophets find no vision from Yahweh.

10 The elders of the daughter of Zion sit on the ground.

They keep silence.

They have cast up dust on their heads.

They have clothed themselves with sackcloth.

The virgins of Jerusalem hang down their heads to the ground.

11 My eyes fail with tears.

My heart is troubled.

My bile is poured on the earth,

because of the destruction of the daughter of my people,

because the young children and the infants swoon in the streets of the city.

12 They ask their mothers,

“Where is grain and wine?”

when they swoon as the wounded in the streets of the city,

when their soul is poured out into their mothers’ bosom.

13 What shall I testify to you?

What shall I liken to you, daughter of Jerusalem?

What shall I compare to you,

that I may comfort you, virgin daughter of Zion?

For your breach is as big as the sea.

Who can heal you?

14 Your prophets have seen false and foolish visions for you.

They have not uncovered your iniquity,

to reverse your captivity,

but have seen for you false revelations and causes of banishment.

15 All that pass by clap their hands at you.

They hiss and wag their head at the daughter of Jerusalem, saying,

“Is this the city that men called ‘The perfection of beauty,

the joy of the whole earth’?”

16 All your enemies have opened their mouth wide against you.

They hiss and gnash their teeth.

They say, “We have swallowed her up.

Certainly this is the day that we looked for.

We have found it.

We have seen it.”

17 Yahweh has done that which he planned.

He has fulfilled his word that he commanded in the days of old.

He has thrown down,

and has not pitied.

He has caused the enemy to rejoice over you.

He has exalted the horn of your adversaries.

18 Their heart cried to the Lord.

O wall of the daughter of Zion,

let tears run down like a river day and night.

Give yourself no relief.

Don’t let your eyes rest.

19 Arise, cry out in the night,

at the beginning of the watches!

Pour out your heart like water before the face of the Lord.

Lift up your hands toward him for the life of your young children,

who faint for hunger at the head of every street.

20 “Look, Yahweh, and see to whom you have done thus!

Should the women eat their offspring,

the children that they held and bounced on their knees?

Should the priest and the prophet be killed in the sanctuary of the Lord?

21 “The youth and the old man lie on the ground in the streets.

My virgins and my young men have fallen by the sword.

You have killed them in the day of your anger.

You have slaughtered, and not pitied.

22 “You have called, as in the day of a solemn assembly, my terrors on every side.

There was no one that escaped or remained in the day of Yahweh’s anger.

My enemy has consumed those whom I have cared for and brought up.

3

1 I am the man who has seen affliction

by the rod of his wrath.

2 He has led me and caused me to walk in darkness,

and not in light.

3 Surely he turns his hand against me

again and again all day long.

4 He has made my flesh and my skin old.

He has broken my bones.

5 He has built against me,

and surrounded me with bitterness and hardship.

6 He has made me dwell in dark places,

as those who have been long dead.

7 He has walled me about, so that I can’t go out.

He has made my chain heavy.

8 Yes, when I cry, and call for help,

he shuts out my prayer.

9 He has walled up my ways with cut stone.

He has made my paths crooked.

10 He is to me as a bear lying in wait,

as a lion in hiding.

11 He has turned away my path,

and pulled me in pieces.

He has made me desolate.

12 He has bent his bow,

and set me as a mark for the arrow.

13 He has caused the shafts of his quiver to enter into my kidneys.

14 I have become a derision to all my people,

and their song all day long.

15 He has filled me with bitterness.

He has stuffed me with wormwood.

16 He has also broken my teeth with gravel.

He has covered me with ashes.

17 You have removed my soul far away from peace.

I forgot prosperity.

18 I said, “My strength has perished,

along with my expectation from Yahweh.”

19 Remember my affliction and my misery,

the wormwood and the bitterness.

20 My soul still remembers them,

and is bowed down within me.

21 This I recall to my mind;

therefore I have hope.

22 It is because of Yahweh’s loving kindnesses that we are not consumed,

because his mercies don’t fail.

23 They are new every morning.

Great is your faithfulness.

24 “Yahweh is my portion,” says my soul.

“Therefore I will hope in him.”

25 Yahweh is good to those who wait for him,

to the soul who seeks him.

26 It is good that a man should hope

and quietly wait for the salvation of Yahweh.

27 It is good for a man that he bear the yoke in his youth.

28 Let him sit alone and keep silence,

because he has laid it on him.

29 Let him put his mouth in the dust,

if it is so that there may be hope.

30 Let him give his cheek to him who strikes him.

Let him be filled full of reproach.

31 For the Lord will not cast off forever.

32 For though he causes grief,

yet he will have compassion according to the multitude of his loving kindnesses.

33 For he does not afflict willingly,

nor grieve the children of men.

34 To crush under foot all the prisoners of the earth,

35 to turn away the right of a man before the face of the Most High,

36 to subvert a man in his cause, the Lord doesn’t approve.

37 Who is he who says, and it comes to pass,

when the Lord doesn’t command it?

38 Doesn’t evil and good come out of the mouth of the Most High?

39 Why should a living man complain,

a man for the punishment of his sins?

40 Let us search and try our ways,

and turn again to Yahweh.

41 Let’s lift up our heart with our hands to God[*] in the heavens.

42 “We have transgressed and have rebelled.

You have not pardoned.

43 “You have covered us with anger and pursued us.

You have killed.

You have not pitied.

44 You have covered yourself with a cloud,

so that no prayer can pass through.

45 You have made us an off-scouring and refuse

in the middle of the peoples.

46 “All our enemies have opened their mouth wide against us.

47 Terror and the pit have come on us,

devastation and destruction.”

48 My eye runs down with streams of water,

for the destruction of the daughter of my people.

49 My eye pours down

and doesn’t cease,

without any intermission,

50 until Yahweh looks down,

and sees from heaven.

51 My eye affects my soul,

because of all the daughters of my city.

52 They have chased me relentlessly like a bird,

those who are my enemies without cause.

53 They have cut off my life in the dungeon,

and have cast a stone on me.

54 Waters flowed over my head.

I said, “I am cut off.”

55 I called on your name, Yahweh,

out of the lowest dungeon.

56 You heard my voice:

“Don’t hide your ear from my sighing,

and my cry.”

57 You came near in the day that I called on you.

You said, “Don’t be afraid.”

58 Lord, you have pleaded the causes of my soul.

You have redeemed my life.

59 Yahweh, you have seen my wrong.

Judge my cause.

60 You have seen all their vengeance

and all their plans against me.

61 You have heard their reproach, Yahweh,

and all their plans against me,

62 the lips of those that rose up against me,

and their plots against me all day long.

63 You see their sitting down and their rising up.

I am their song.

64 You will pay them back, Yahweh,

according to the work of their hands.

65 You will give them hardness of heart,

your curse to them.

66 You will pursue them in anger,

and destroy them from under the heavens of Yahweh.

4

1 How the gold has become dim!

The most pure gold has changed!

The stones of the sanctuary are poured out

at the head of every street.

2 The precious sons of Zion,

comparable to fine gold,

how they are esteemed as earthen pitchers,

the work of the hands of the potter!

3 Even the jackals offer their breast.

They nurse their young ones.

But the daughter of my people has become cruel,

like the ostriches in the wilderness.

4 The tongue of the nursing child clings to the roof of his mouth for thirst.

The young children ask bread,

and no one breaks it for them.

5 Those who ate delicacies are desolate in the streets.

Those who were brought up in purple embrace dunghills.

6 For the iniquity of the daughter of my people is greater than the sin of Sodom,

which was overthrown as in a moment.

No hands were laid on her.

7 Her nobles were purer than snow.

They were whiter than milk.

They were more ruddy in body than rubies.

Their polishing was like sapphire.

8 Their appearance is blacker than a coal.

They are not known in the streets.

Their skin clings to their bones.

It is withered.

It has become like wood.

9 Those who are killed with the sword are better than those who are killed with hunger;

For these pine away, stricken through,

for lack of the fruits of the field.

10 The hands of the pitiful women have boiled their own children.

They were their food in the destruction of the daughter of my people.

11 Yahweh has accomplished his wrath.

He has poured out his fierce anger.

He has kindled a fire in Zion,

which has devoured its foundations.

12 The kings of the earth didn’t believe,

neither did all the inhabitants of the world,

that the adversary and the enemy would enter into the gates of Jerusalem.

13 It is because of the sins of her prophets

and the iniquities of her priests,

that have shed the blood of the just in the middle of her.

14 They wander as blind men in the streets.

They are polluted with blood,

So that men can’t touch their garments.

15 “Go away!” they cried to them.

“Unclean! Go away! Go away! Don’t touch!

When they fled away and wandered, men said among the nations,

“They can’t live here any more.”

16 Yahweh’s anger has scattered them.

He will not pay attention to them any more.

They didn’t respect the persons of the priests.

They didn’t favor the elders.

17 Our eyes still fail,

looking in vain for our help.

In our watching we have watched for a nation that could not save.

18 They hunt our steps,

so that we can’t go in our streets.

Our end is near.

Our days are fulfilled,

for our end has come.

19 Our pursuers were swifter than the eagles of the sky.

They chased us on the mountains.

They set an ambush for us in the wilderness.

20 The breath of our nostrils,

the anointed of Yahweh,

was taken in their pits;

of whom we said,

under his shadow we will live among the nations.

21 Rejoice and be glad, daughter of Edom,

who dwells in the land of Uz.

The cup will pass through to you also.

You will be drunken,

and will make yourself naked.

22 The punishment of your iniquity is accomplished, daughter of Zion.

He will no more carry you away into captivity.

He will visit your iniquity, daughter of Edom.

He will uncover your sins.

5

1 Remember, Yahweh, what has come on us.

Look, and see our reproach.

2 Our inheritance has been turned over to strangers,

our houses to aliens.

3 We are orphans and fatherless.

Our mothers are as widows.

4 We must pay for water to drink.

Our wood is sold to us.

5 Our pursuers are on our necks.

We are weary, and have no rest.

6 We have given our hands to the Egyptians,

and to the Assyrians, to be satisfied with bread.

7 Our fathers sinned, and are no more.

We have borne their iniquities.

8 Servants rule over us.

There is no one to deliver us out of their hand.

9 We get our bread at the peril of our lives,

because of the sword in the wilderness.

10 Our skin is black like an oven,

because of the burning heat of famine.

11 They ravished the women in Zion,

the virgins in the cities of Judah.

12 Princes were hanged up by their hands.

The faces of elders were not honored.

13 The young men carry millstones.

The children stumbled under loads of wood.

14 The elders have ceased from the gate,

and the young men from their music.

15 The joy of our heart has ceased.

Our dance is turned into mourning.

16 The crown has fallen from our head.

Woe to us, for we have sinned!

17 For this our heart is faint.

For these things our eyes are dim:

18 for the mountain of Zion, which is desolate.

The foxes walk on it.

19 You, Yahweh, remain forever.

Your throne is from generation to generation.

20 Why do you forget us forever,

and forsake us for so long a time?

21 Turn us to yourself, Yahweh, and we will be turned.

Renew our days as of old.

22 But you have utterly rejected us.

You are very angry against us.

* 1:5 “Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

† 1:14 The word translated “Lord” is “Adonai.”

* 3:41 The Hebrew word rendered “God” is “אֱלֹהִ֑ים” (Elohim).

Leviticus

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10

11
12
13
14
15
16
17
18
19
20

21
22
23
24
25
26
27

The Third Book of Moses,

Commonly Called

Leviticus

1

1 Yahweh[*] called to Moses, and spoke to him from the Tent of Meeting, saying, 2 “Speak to the children of Israel, and tell them, ‘When anyone of you offers an offering to Yahweh, you shall offer your offering of the livestock, from the herd and from the flock.

3 “ ‘If his offering is a burnt offering from the herd, he shall offer a male without defect. He shall offer it at the door of the Tent of Meeting, that he may be accepted before Yahweh. 4 He shall lay his hand on the head of the burnt offering, and it shall be accepted for him to make atonement for him. 5 He shall kill the bull before Yahweh. Aaron’s sons, the priests, shall present the blood and sprinkle the blood around on the altar that is at the door of the Tent of Meeting. 6 He shall skin the burnt offering and cut it into pieces. 7 The sons of Aaron the priest shall put fire on the altar, and lay wood in order on the fire; 8 and Aaron’s sons, the priests, shall lay the pieces, the head, and the fat in order on the wood that is on the fire which is on the altar; 9 but he shall wash its innards and its legs with water. The priest shall burn all of it on the altar, for a burnt offering, an offering made by fire, of a pleasant aroma to Yahweh.

10 “ ‘If his offering is from the flock, from the sheep or from the goats, for a burnt offering, he shall offer a male without defect. 11 He shall kill it on the north side of the altar before Yahweh. Aaron’s sons, the priests, shall sprinkle its blood around on the altar. 12 He shall cut it into its pieces, with its head and its fat. The priest shall lay them in order on the wood that is on the fire which is on the altar, 13 but the innards and the legs he shall wash with water. The priest shall offer the whole, and burn it on the altar. It is a burnt offering, an offering made by fire, of a pleasant aroma to Yahweh.

14 “ ‘If his offering to Yahweh is a burnt offering of birds, then he shall offer his offering from turtledoves or of young pigeons. 15 The priest shall bring it to the altar, and wring off its head, and burn it on the altar; and its blood shall be drained out on the side of the altar; 16 and he shall take away its crop and its feathers, and cast it beside the altar on the east part, in the place of the ashes. 17 He shall tear it by its wings, but shall not divide it apart. The priest shall burn it on the altar, on the wood that is on the fire. It is a burnt offering, an offering made by fire, of a pleasant aroma to Yahweh.

2

1 “ ‘When anyone offers an offering of a meal offering to Yahweh, his offering shall be of fine flour. He shall pour oil on it, and put frankincense on it. 2 He shall bring it to Aaron’s sons, the priests. He shall take his handful of its fine flour, and of its oil, with all its frankincense, and the priest shall burn its memorial on the altar, an offering made by fire, of a pleasant aroma to Yahweh. 3 That which is left of the meal offering shall be Aaron’s and his sons’. It is a most holy part of the offerings of Yahweh made by fire.

4 “ ‘When you offer an offering of a meal offering baked in the oven, it shall be unleavened cakes of fine flour mixed with oil, or unleavened wafers anointed with oil. 5 If your offering is a meal offering made on a griddle, it shall be of unleavened fine flour, mixed with oil. 6 You shall cut it in pieces, and pour oil on it. It is a meal offering. 7 If your offering is a meal offering of the pan, it shall be made of fine flour with oil. 8 You shall bring the meal offering that is made of these things to Yahweh. It shall be presented to the priest, and he shall bring it to the altar. 9 The priest shall take from the meal offering its memorial, and shall burn it on the altar, an offering made by fire, of a pleasant aroma to Yahweh. 10 That which is left of the meal offering shall be Aaron’s and his sons’. It is a most holy part of the offerings of Yahweh made by fire.

11 “ ‘No meal offering which you shall offer to Yahweh shall be made with yeast; for you shall burn no yeast, nor any honey, as an offering made by fire to Yahweh. 12 As an offering of first fruits you shall offer them to Yahweh, but they shall not rise up as a pleasant aroma on the altar. 13 Every offering of your meal offering you shall season with salt. You shall not allow the salt of the covenant of your God[*] to be lacking from your meal offering. With all your offerings you shall offer salt.

14 “ ‘If you offer a meal offering of first fruits to Yahweh, you shall offer for the meal offering of your first fruits fresh heads of grain parched with fire and crushed. 15 You shall put oil on it and lay frankincense on it. It is a meal offering. 16 The priest shall burn as its memorial part of its crushed grain and part of its oil, along with all its frankincense. It is an offering made by fire to Yahweh.

3

1 “ ‘If his offering is a sacrifice of peace offerings, if he offers it from the herd, whether male or female, he shall offer it without defect before Yahweh. 2 He shall lay his hand on the head of his offering, and kill it at the door of the Tent of Meeting. Aaron’s sons, the priests, shall sprinkle the blood around on the altar. 3 He shall offer of the sacrifice of peace offerings an offering made by fire to Yahweh. The fat that covers the innards, and all the fat that is on the innards, 4 and the two kidneys, and the fat that is on them, which is by the loins, and the cover on the liver, with the kidneys, he shall take away. 5 Aaron’s sons shall burn it on the altar on the burnt offering, which is on the wood that is on the fire: it is an offering made by fire, of a pleasant aroma to Yahweh.

6 “ ‘If his offering for a sacrifice of peace offerings to Yahweh is from the flock, either male or female, he shall offer it without defect. 7 If he offers a lamb for his offering, then he shall offer it before Yahweh; 8 and he shall lay his hand on the head of his offering, and kill it before the Tent of Meeting. Aaron’s sons shall sprinkle its blood around on the altar. 9 He shall offer from the sacrifice of peace offerings an offering made by fire to Yahweh; its fat, the entire tail fat, he shall take away close to the backbone; and the fat that covers the entrails, and all the fat that is on the entrails, 10 and the two kidneys, and the fat that is on them, which is by the loins, and the cover on the liver, with the kidneys, he shall take away. 11 The priest shall burn it on the altar: it is the food of the offering made by fire to Yahweh.

12 “ ‘If his offering is a goat, then he shall offer it before Yahweh. 13 He shall lay his hand on its head, and kill it before the Tent of Meeting; and the sons of Aaron shall sprinkle its blood around on the altar. 14 He shall offer from it as his offering, an offering made by fire to Yahweh; the fat that covers the innards, and all the fat that is on the innards, 15 and the two kidneys, and the fat that is on them, which is by the loins, and the cover on the liver, with the kidneys, he shall take away. 16 The priest shall burn them on the altar: it is the food of the offering made by fire, for a pleasant aroma; all the fat is Yahweh’s.

17 “ ‘It shall be a perpetual statute throughout your generations in all your dwellings, that you shall eat neither fat nor blood.’ ”

4

1 Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, 2 “Speak to the children of Israel, saying, ‘If anyone sins unintentionally, in any of the things which Yahweh has commanded not to be done, and does any one of them, 3 if the anointed priest sins so as to bring guilt on the people, then let him offer for his sin which he has sinned a young bull without defect to Yahweh for a sin offering. 4 He shall bring the bull to the door of the Tent of Meeting before Yahweh; and he shall lay his hand on the head of the bull, and kill the bull before Yahweh. 5 The anointed priest shall take some of the blood of the bull, and bring it to the Tent of Meeting. 6 The priest shall dip his finger in the blood, and sprinkle some of the blood seven times before Yahweh, before the veil of the sanctuary. 7 The priest shall put some of the blood on the horns of the altar of sweet incense before Yahweh, which is in the Tent of Meeting; and he shall pour out the rest of the blood of the bull at the base of the altar of burnt offering, which is at the door of the Tent of Meeting. 8 He shall take all the fat of the bull of the sin offering from it: the fat that covers the innards, and all the fat that is on the innards, 9 and the two kidneys, and the fat that is on them, which is by the loins, and the cover on the liver, with the kidneys, he shall remove, 10 as it is removed from the bull of the sacrifice of peace offerings. The priest shall burn them on the altar of burnt offering. 11 He shall carry the bull’s skin, all its meat, with its head, and with its legs, its innards, and its dung 12 —all the rest of the bull—outside of the camp to a clean place where the ashes are poured out, and burn it on wood with fire. It shall be burned where the ashes are poured out.

13 “ ‘If the whole congregation of Israel sins, and the thing is hidden from the eyes of the assembly, and they have done any of the things which Yahweh has commanded not to be done, and are guilty; 14 when the sin in which they have sinned is known, then the assembly shall offer a young bull for a sin offering, and bring it before the Tent of Meeting. 15 The elders of the congregation shall lay their hands on the head of the bull before Yahweh; and the bull shall be killed before Yahweh. 16 The anointed priest shall bring some of the blood of the bull to the Tent of Meeting. 17 The priest shall dip his finger in the blood and sprinkle it seven times before Yahweh, before the veil. 18 He shall put some of the blood on the horns of the altar which is before Yahweh, that is in the Tent of Meeting; and the rest of the blood he shall pour out at the base of the altar of burnt offering, which is at the door of the Tent of Meeting. 19 All its fat he shall take from it, and burn it on the altar. 20 He shall do this with the bull; as he did with the bull of the sin offering, so he shall do with this; and the priest shall make atonement for them, and they shall be forgiven. 21 He shall carry the bull outside the camp, and burn it as he burned the first bull. It is the sin offering for the assembly.

22 “ ‘When a ruler sins, and unwittingly does any one of all the things which Yahweh his God has commanded not to be done, and is guilty, 23 if his sin in which he has sinned is made known to him, he shall bring as his offering a goat, a male without defect. 24 He shall lay his hand on the head of the goat, and kill it in the place where they kill the burnt offering before Yahweh. It is a sin offering. 25 The priest shall take some of the blood of the sin offering with his finger, and put it on the horns of the altar of burnt offering. He shall pour out the rest of its blood at the base of the altar of burnt offering. 26 All its fat he shall burn on the altar, like the fat of the sacrifice of peace offerings; and the priest shall make atonement for him concerning his sin, and he will be forgiven.

27 “ ‘If anyone of the common people sins unwittingly, in doing any of the things which Yahweh has commanded not to be done, and is guilty, 28 if his sin which he has sinned is made known to him, then he shall bring for his offering a goat, a female without defect, for his sin which he has sinned. 29 He shall lay his hand on the head of the sin offering, and kill the sin offering in the place of burnt offering. 30 The priest shall take some of its blood with his finger, and put it on the horns of the altar of burnt offering; and the rest of its blood he shall pour out at the base of the altar. 31 All its fat he shall take away, like the fat is taken away from the sacrifice of peace offerings; and the priest shall burn it on the altar for a pleasant aroma to Yahweh; and the priest shall make atonement for him, and he will be forgiven.

32 “ ‘If he brings a lamb as his offering for a sin offering, he shall bring a female without defect. 33 He shall lay his hand on the head of the sin offering, and kill it for a sin offering in the place where they kill the burnt offering. 34 The priest shall take some of the blood of the sin offering with his finger, and put it on the horns of the altar of burnt offering; and all the rest of its blood he shall pour out at the base of the altar. 35 He shall remove all its fat, like the fat of the lamb is removed from the sacrifice of peace offerings. The priest shall burn them on the altar, on the offerings of Yahweh made by fire. The priest shall make atonement for him concerning his sin that he has sinned, and he will be forgiven.

5

1 “ ‘If anyone sins, in that he hears a public adjuration to testify, he being a witness, whether he has seen or known, if he doesn’t report it, then he shall bear his iniquity.

2 “ ‘Or if anyone touches any unclean thing, whether it is the carcass of an unclean animal, or the carcass of unclean livestock, or the carcass of unclean creeping things, and it is hidden from him, and he is unclean, then he shall be guilty.

3 “ ‘Or if he touches the uncleanness of man, whatever his uncleanness is with which he is unclean, and it is hidden from him; when he knows of it, then he shall be guilty.

4 “ ‘Or if anyone swears rashly with his lips to do evil or to do good—whatever it is that a man might utter rashly with an oath, and it is hidden from him—when he knows of it, then he will be guilty of one of these. 5 It shall be, when he is guilty of one of these, he shall confess that in which he has sinned; 6 and he shall bring his trespass offering to Yahweh for his sin which he has sinned: a female from the flock, a lamb or a goat, for a sin offering; and the priest shall make atonement for him concerning his sin.

7 “ ‘If he can’t afford a lamb, then he shall bring his trespass offering for that in which he has sinned, two turtledoves, or two young pigeons, to Yahweh; one for a sin offering, and the other for a burnt offering. 8 He shall bring them to the priest, who shall first offer the one which is for the sin offering. He shall wring off its head from its neck, but shall not sever it completely. 9 He shall sprinkle some of the blood of the sin offering on the side of the altar; and the rest of the blood shall be drained out at the base of the altar. It is a sin offering. 10 He shall offer the second for a burnt offering, according to the ordinance; and the priest shall make atonement for him concerning his sin which he has sinned, and he shall be forgiven.

11 “ ‘But if he can’t afford two turtledoves or two young pigeons, then he shall bring as his offering for that in which he has sinned, one tenth of an ephah[*] of fine flour for a sin offering. He shall put no oil on it, and he shall not put any frankincense on it, for it is a sin offering. 12 He shall bring it to the priest, and the priest shall take his handful of it as the memorial portion, and burn it on the altar, on the offerings of Yahweh made by fire. It is a sin offering. 13 The priest shall make atonement for him concerning his sin that he has sinned in any of these things, and he will be forgiven; and the rest shall be the priest’s, as the meal offering.’ ”

14 Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, 15 “If anyone commits a trespass, and sins unwittingly regarding Yahweh’s holy things, then he shall bring his trespass offering to Yahweh: a ram without defect from the flock, according to your estimation in silver by shekels, according to the shekel[†] of the sanctuary, for a trespass offering. 16 He shall make restitution for that which he has done wrong regarding the holy thing, and shall add a fifth part to it, and give it to the priest; and the priest shall make atonement for him with the ram of the trespass offering, and he will be forgiven.

17 “If anyone sins, doing any of the things which Yahweh has commanded not to be done, though he didn’t know it, he is still guilty, and shall bear his iniquity. 18 He shall bring a ram without defect from of the flock, according to your estimation, for a trespass offering, to the priest; and the priest shall make atonement for him concerning the thing in which he sinned and didn’t know it, and he will be forgiven. 19 It is a trespass offering. He is certainly guilty before Yahweh.”

6

1 Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, 2 “If anyone sins, and commits a trespass against Yahweh, and deals falsely with his neighbor in a matter of deposit, or of bargain, or of robbery, or has oppressed his neighbor, 3 or has found that which was lost, and lied about it, and swearing to a lie—in any of these things that a man sins in his actions— 4 then it shall be, if he has sinned, and is guilty, he shall restore that which he took by robbery, or the thing which he has gotten by oppression, or the deposit which was committed to him, or the lost thing which he found, 5 or any thing about which he has sworn falsely: he shall restore it in full, and shall add a fifth part more to it. He shall return it to him to whom it belongs in the day of his being found guilty. 6 He shall bring his trespass offering to Yahweh: a ram without defect from the flock, according to your estimation, for a trespass offering, to the priest. 7 The priest shall make atonement for him before Yahweh, and he will be forgiven concerning whatever he does to become guilty.”

8 Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, 9 “Command Aaron and his sons, saying, ‘This is the law of the burnt offering: the burnt offering shall be on the hearth on the altar all night until the morning; and the fire of the altar shall be kept burning on it. 10 The priest shall put on his linen garment, and he shall put on his linen trousers upon his body; and he shall remove the ashes from where the fire has consumed the burnt offering on the altar, and he shall put them beside the altar. 11 He shall take off his garments, and put on other garments, and carry the ashes outside the camp to a clean place. 12 The fire on the altar shall be kept burning on it, it shall not go out; and the priest shall burn wood on it every morning. He shall lay the burnt offering in order upon it, and shall burn on it the fat of the peace offerings. 13 Fire shall be kept burning on the altar continually; it shall not go out.

14 “ ‘This is the law of the meal offering: the sons of Aaron shall offer it before Yahweh, before the altar. 15 He shall take from there his handful of the fine flour of the meal offering, and of its oil, and all the frankincense which is on the meal offering, and shall burn it on the altar for a pleasant aroma, as its memorial portion, to Yahweh. 16 That which is left of it Aaron and his sons shall eat. It shall be eaten without yeast in a holy place. They shall eat it in the court of the Tent of Meeting. 17 It shall not be baked with yeast. I have given it as their portion of my offerings made by fire. It is most holy, as are the sin offering and the trespass offering. 18 Every male among the children of Aaron shall eat of it, as their portion forever throughout your generations, from the offerings of Yahweh made by fire. Whoever touches them shall be holy.’ ”

19 Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, 20 “This is the offering of Aaron and of his sons, which they shall offer to Yahweh in the day when he is anointed: one tenth of an ephah[*] of fine flour for a meal offering perpetually, half of it in the morning, and half of it in the evening. 21 It shall be made with oil in a griddle. When it is soaked, you shall bring it in. You shall offer the meal offering in baked pieces for a pleasant aroma to Yahweh. 22 The anointed priest that will be in his place from among his sons shall offer it. By a statute forever, it shall be wholly burned to Yahweh. 23 Every meal offering of a priest shall be wholly burned. It shall not be eaten.”

24 Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, 25 “Speak to Aaron and to his sons, saying, ‘This is the law of the sin offering: in the place where the burnt offering is killed, the sin offering shall be killed before Yahweh. It is most holy. 26 The priest who offers it for sin shall eat it. It shall be eaten in a holy place, in the court of the Tent of Meeting. 27 Whatever shall touch its flesh shall be holy. When there is any of its blood sprinkled on a garment, you shall wash that on which it was sprinkled in a holy place. 28 But the earthen vessel in which it is boiled shall be broken; and if it is boiled in a bronze vessel, it shall be scoured, and rinsed in water. 29 Every male among the priests shall eat of it. It is most holy. 30 No sin offering, of which any of the blood is brought into the Tent of Meeting to make atonement in the Holy Place, shall be eaten. It shall be burned with fire.

7

1 “ ‘This is the law of the trespass offering: It is most holy. 2 In the place where they kill the burnt offering, he shall kill the trespass offering; and its blood he shall sprinkle around on the altar. 3 He shall offer all of its fat: the fat tail, and the fat that covers the innards, 4 and he shall take away the two kidneys, and the fat that is on them, which is by the loins, and the cover on the liver, with the kidneys; 5 and the priest shall burn them on the altar for an offering made by fire to Yahweh: it is a trespass offering. 6 Every male among the priests may eat of it. It shall be eaten in a holy place. It is most holy.

7 “ ‘As is the sin offering, so is the trespass offering; there is one law for them. The priest who makes atonement with them shall have it. 8 The priest who offers any man’s burnt offering shall have for himself the skin of the burnt offering which he has offered. 9 Every meal offering that is baked in the oven, and all that is prepared in the pan and on the griddle, shall be the priest’s who offers it. 10 Every meal offering, mixed with oil or dry, belongs to all the sons of Aaron, one as well as another.

11 “ ‘This is the law of the sacrifice of peace offerings, which one shall offer to Yahweh: 12 If he offers it for a thanksgiving, then he shall offer with the sacrifice of thanksgiving unleavened cakes mixed with oil, and unleavened wafers anointed with oil, and cakes mixed with oil. 13 He shall offer his offering with the sacrifice of his peace offerings for thanksgiving with cakes of leavened bread. 14 Of it he shall offer one out of each offering for a heave offering to Yahweh. It shall be the priest’s who sprinkles the blood of the peace offerings. 15 The flesh of the sacrifice of his peace offerings for thanksgiving shall be eaten on the day of his offering. He shall not leave any of it until the morning.

16 “ ‘But if the sacrifice of his offering is a vow, or a free will offering, it shall be eaten on the day that he offers his sacrifice. On the next day what remains of it shall be eaten, 17 but what remains of the meat of the sacrifice on the third day shall be burned with fire. 18 If any of the meat of the sacrifice of his peace offerings is eaten on the third day, it will not be accepted, and it shall not be credited to him who offers it. It will be an abomination, and the soul who eats any of it will bear his iniquity.

19 “ ‘The meat that touches any unclean thing shall not be eaten. It shall be burned with fire. As for the meat, everyone who is clean may eat it; 20 but the soul who eats of the meat of the sacrifice of peace offerings that belongs to Yahweh, having his uncleanness on him, that soul shall be cut off from his people. 21 When anyone touches any unclean thing, the uncleanness of man, or an unclean animal, or any unclean abomination, and eats some of the meat of the sacrifice of peace offerings which belong to Yahweh, that soul shall be cut off from his people.’ ”

22 Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, 23 “Speak to the children of Israel, saying, ‘You shall eat no fat, of bull, or sheep, or goat. 24 The fat of that which dies of itself, and the fat of that which is torn of animals, may be used for any other service, but you shall in no way eat of it. 25 For whoever eats the fat of the animal which men offer as an offering made by fire to Yahweh, even the soul who eats it shall be cut off from his people. 26 You shall not eat any blood, whether it is of bird or of animal, in any of your dwellings. 27 Whoever it is who eats any blood, that soul shall be cut off from his people.’ ”

28 Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, 29 “Speak to the children of Israel, saying, ‘He who offers the sacrifice of his peace offerings to Yahweh shall bring his offering to Yahweh out of the sacrifice of his peace offerings. 30 With his own hands he shall bring the offerings of Yahweh made by fire. He shall bring the fat with the breast, that the breast may be waved for a wave offering before Yahweh. 31 The priest shall burn the fat on the altar, but the breast shall be Aaron’s and his sons’. 32 The right thigh you shall give to the priest for a heave offering out of the sacrifices of your peace offerings. 33 He among the sons of Aaron who offers the blood of the peace offerings, and the fat, shall have the right thigh for a portion. 34 For the waved breast and the heaved thigh I have taken from the children of Israel out of the sacrifices of their peace offerings, and have given them to Aaron the priest and to his sons as their portion forever from the children of Israel.’ ”

35 This is the consecrated portion of Aaron, and the consecrated portion of his sons, out of the offerings of Yahweh made by fire, in the day when he presented them to minister to Yahweh in the priest’s office; 36 which Yahweh commanded to be given them of the children of Israel, in the day that he anointed them. It is their portion forever throughout their generations. 37 This is the law of the burnt offering, the meal offering, the sin offering, the trespass offering, the consecration, and the sacrifice of peace offerings 38 which Yahweh commanded Moses in Mount Sinai in the day that he commanded the children of Israel to offer their offerings to Yahweh, in the wilderness of Sinai.

8

1 Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, 2 “Take Aaron and his sons with him, and the garments, and the anointing oil, and the bull of the sin offering, and the two rams, and the basket of unleavened bread; 3 and assemble all the congregation at the door of the Tent of Meeting.”

4 Moses did as Yahweh commanded him; and the congregation was assembled at the door of the Tent of Meeting. 5 Moses said to the congregation, “This is the thing which Yahweh has commanded to be done.” 6 Moses brought Aaron and his sons, and washed them with water. 7 He put the tunic on him, tied the sash on him, clothed him with the robe, put the ephod on him, and he tied the skillfully woven band of the ephod on him and fastened it to him with it. 8 He placed the breastplate on him. He put the Urim and Thummim in the breastplate. 9 He set the turban on his head. He set the golden plate, the holy crown, on the front of the turban, as Yahweh commanded Moses. 10 Moses took the anointing oil, and anointed the tabernacle and all that was in it, and sanctified them. 11 He sprinkled it on the altar seven times, and anointed the altar and all its vessels, and the basin and its base, to sanctify them. 12 He poured some of the anointing oil on Aaron’s head, and anointed him, to sanctify him. 13 Moses brought Aaron’s sons, and clothed them with tunics, and tied sashes on them, and put headbands on them, as Yahweh commanded Moses.

14 He brought the bull of the sin offering, and Aaron and his sons laid their hands on the head of the bull of the sin offering. 15 He killed it; and Moses took the blood, and put it around on the horns of the altar with his finger, and purified the altar, and poured out the blood at the base of the altar, and sanctified it, to make atonement for it. 16 He took all the fat that was on the innards, and the cover of the liver, and the two kidneys, and their fat; and Moses burned it on the altar. 17 But the bull, and its skin, and its meat, and its dung, he burned with fire outside the camp, as Yahweh commanded Moses. 18 He presented the ram of the burnt offering. Aaron and his sons laid their hands on the head of the ram. 19 He killed it; and Moses sprinkled the blood around on the altar. 20 He cut the ram into its pieces; and Moses burned the head, and the pieces, and the fat. 21 He washed the innards and the legs with water; and Moses burned the whole ram on the altar. It was a burnt offering for a pleasant aroma. It was an offering made by fire to Yahweh, as Yahweh commanded Moses. 22 He presented the other ram, the ram of consecration. Aaron and his sons laid their hands on the head of the ram. 23 He killed it; and Moses took some of its blood, and put it on the tip of Aaron’s right ear, and on the thumb of his right hand, and on the great toe of his right foot. 24 He brought Aaron’s sons; and Moses put some of the blood on the tip of their right ear, and on the thumb of their right hand, and on the great toe of their right foot; and Moses sprinkled the blood around on the altar. 25 He took the fat, the fat tail, all the fat that was on the innards, the cover of the liver, the two kidneys and their fat, and the right thigh; 26 and out of the basket of unleavened bread that was before Yahweh, he took one unleavened cake, one cake of oiled bread, and one wafer, and placed them on the fat and on the right thigh. 27 He put all these in Aaron’s hands and in his sons’ hands, and waved them for a wave offering before Yahweh. 28 Moses took them from their hands, and burned them on the altar on the burnt offering. They were a consecration offering for a pleasant aroma. It was an offering made by fire to Yahweh. 29 Moses took the breast, and waved it for a wave offering before Yahweh. It was Moses’ portion of the ram of consecration, as Yahweh commanded Moses. 30 Moses took some of the anointing oil, and some of the blood which was on the altar, and sprinkled it on Aaron, on his garments, and on his sons, and on his sons’ garments with him, and sanctified Aaron, his garments, and his sons, and his sons’ garments with him.

31 Moses said to Aaron and to his sons, “Boil the meat at the door of the Tent of Meeting, and there eat it and the bread that is in the basket of consecration, as I commanded, saying, ‘Aaron and his sons shall eat it.’ 32 What remains of the meat and of the bread you shall burn with fire. 33 You shall not go out from the door of the Tent of Meeting for seven days, until the days of your consecration are fulfilled: for he shall consecrate you seven days. 34 What has been done today, so Yahweh has commanded to do, to make atonement for you. 35 You shall stay at the door of the Tent of Meeting day and night seven days, and keep Yahweh’s command, that you don’t die: for so I am commanded.” 36 Aaron and his sons did all the things which Yahweh commanded by Moses.

9

1 On the eighth day, Moses called Aaron and his sons, and the elders of Israel; 2 and he said to Aaron, “Take a calf from the herd for a sin offering, and a ram for a burnt offering, without defect, and offer them before Yahweh. 3 You shall speak to the children of Israel, saying, ‘Take a male goat for a sin offering; and a calf and a lamb, both a year old, without defect, for a burnt offering; 4 and a bull and a ram for peace offerings, to sacrifice before Yahweh; and a meal offering mixed with oil: for today Yahweh appears to you.’ ”

5 They brought what Moses commanded before the Tent of Meeting. All the congregation came near and stood before Yahweh. 6 Moses said, “This is the thing which Yahweh commanded that you should do; and Yahweh’s glory shall appear to you.” 7 Moses said to Aaron, “Draw near to the altar, and offer your sin offering, and your burnt offering, and make atonement for yourself, and for the people; and offer the offering of the people, and make atonement for them, as Yahweh commanded.”

8 So Aaron came near to the altar, and killed the calf of the sin offering, which was for himself. 9 The sons of Aaron presented the blood to him; and he dipped his finger in the blood, and put it on the horns of the altar, and poured out the blood at the base of the altar; 10 but the fat, and the kidneys, and the cover from the liver of the sin offering, he burned upon the altar, as Yahweh commanded Moses. 11 The meat and the skin he burned with fire outside the camp. 12 He killed the burnt offering; and Aaron’s sons delivered the blood to him, and he sprinkled it around on the altar. 13 They delivered the burnt offering to him, piece by piece, and the head. He burned them upon the altar. 14 He washed the innards and the legs, and burned them on the burnt offering on the altar. 15 He presented the people’s offering, and took the goat of the sin offering which was for the people, and killed it, and offered it for sin, like the first. 16 He presented the burnt offering, and offered it according to the ordinance. 17 He presented the meal offering, and filled his hand from there, and burned it upon the altar, in addition to the burnt offering of the morning. 18 He also killed the bull and the ram, the sacrifice of peace offerings, which was for the people. Aaron’s sons delivered to him the blood, which he sprinkled around on the altar; 19 and the fat of the bull and of the ram, the fat tail, and that which covers the innards, and the kidneys, and the cover of the liver; 20 and they put the fat upon the breasts, and he burned the fat on the altar. 21 Aaron waved the breasts and the right thigh for a wave offering before Yahweh, as Moses commanded. 22 Aaron lifted up his hands toward the people, and blessed them; and he came down from offering the sin offering, and the burnt offering, and the peace offerings.

23 Moses and Aaron went into the Tent of Meeting, and came out, and blessed the people; and Yahweh’s glory appeared to all the people. 24 Fire came out from before Yahweh, and consumed the burnt offering and the fat upon the altar. When all the people saw it, they shouted, and fell on their faces.

10

1 Nadab and Abihu, the sons of Aaron, each took his censer, and put fire in it, and laid incense on it, and offered strange fire before Yahweh, which he had not commanded them. 2 Fire came out from before Yahweh, and devoured them, and they died before Yahweh.

3 Then Moses said to Aaron, “This is what Yahweh spoke of, saying,

‘I will show myself holy to those who come near me,

and before all the people I will be glorified.’ ”

Aaron held his peace. 4 Moses called Mishael and Elzaphan, the sons of Uzziel the uncle of Aaron, and said to them, “Draw near, carry your brothers from before the sanctuary out of the camp.” 5 So they came near, and carried them in their tunics out of the camp, as Moses had said.

6 Moses said to Aaron, and to Eleazar and to Ithamar, his sons, “Don’t let the hair of your heads go loose, and don’t tear your clothes, so that you don’t die, and so that he will not be angry with all the congregation; but let your brothers, the whole house of Israel, bewail the burning which Yahweh has kindled. 7 You shall not go out from the door of the Tent of Meeting, lest you die; for the anointing oil of Yahweh is on you.” They did according to the word of Moses. 8 Then Yahweh said to Aaron, 9 “You and your sons are not to drink wine or strong drink whenever you go into the Tent of Meeting, or you will die. This shall be a statute forever throughout your generations. 10 You are to make a distinction between the holy and the common, and between the unclean and the clean. 11 You are to teach the children of Israel all the statutes which Yahweh has spoken to them by Moses.”

12 Moses spoke to Aaron, and to Eleazar and to Ithamar, his sons who were left, “Take the meal offering that remains of the offerings of Yahweh made by fire, and eat it without yeast beside the altar; for it is most holy; 13 and you shall eat it in a holy place, because it is your portion, and your sons’ portion, of the offerings of Yahweh made by fire; for so I am commanded. 14 The waved breast and the heaved thigh you shall eat in a clean place, you, and your sons, and your daughters with you: for they are given as your portion, and your sons’ portion, out of the sacrifices of the peace offerings of the children of Israel. 15 They shall bring the heaved thigh and the waved breast with the offerings made by fire of the fat, to wave it for a wave offering before Yahweh. It shall be yours, and your sons’ with you, as a portion forever, as Yahweh has commanded.”

16 Moses diligently inquired about the goat of the sin offering, and, behold,[*] it was burned. He was angry with Eleazar and with Ithamar, the sons of Aaron who were left, saying, 17 “Why haven’t you eaten the sin offering in the place of the sanctuary, since it is most holy, and he has given it to you to bear the iniquity of the congregation, to make atonement for them before Yahweh? 18 Behold, its blood was not brought into the inner part of the sanctuary. You certainly should have eaten it in the sanctuary, as I commanded.”

19 Aaron spoke to Moses, “Behold, today they have offered their sin offering and their burnt offering before Yahweh; and such things as these have happened to me. If I had eaten the sin offering today, would it have been pleasing in Yahweh’s sight?”

20 When Moses heard that, it was pleasing in his sight.

11

1 Yahweh spoke to Moses and to Aaron, saying to them, 2 “Speak to the children of Israel, saying, ‘These are the living things which you may eat among all the animals that are on the earth. 3 Whatever parts the hoof, and is cloven-footed, and chews the cud among the animals, that you may eat.

4 “ ‘Nevertheless these you shall not eat of those that chew the cud, or of those who part the hoof: the camel, because it chews the cud but doesn’t have a parted hoof, is unclean to you. 5 The hyrax,[*] because it chews the cud but doesn’t have a parted hoof, is unclean to you. 6 The hare, because it chews the cud but doesn’t have a parted hoof, is unclean to you. 7 The pig, because it has a split hoof, and is cloven-footed, but doesn’t chew the cud, is unclean to you. 8 You shall not eat their meat. You shall not touch their carcasses. They are unclean to you.

9 “ ‘You may eat of all these that are in the waters: whatever has fins and scales in the waters, in the seas, and in the rivers, that you may eat. 10 All that don’t have fins and scales in the seas and rivers, all that move in the waters, and all the living creatures that are in the waters, they are an abomination to you, 11 and you shall detest them. You shall not eat of their meat, and you shall detest their carcasses. 12 Whatever has no fins nor scales in the waters is an abomination to you.

13 “ ‘You shall detest these among the birds; they shall not be eaten because they are an abomination: the eagle, the vulture, the black vulture, 14 the red kite, any kind of black kite, 15 any kind of raven, 16 the horned owl, the screech owl, the gull, any kind of hawk, 17 the little owl, the cormorant, the great owl, 18 the white owl, the desert owl, the osprey, 19 the stork, any kind of heron, the hoopoe, and the bat.

20 “ ‘All flying insects that walk on all fours are an abomination to you. 21 Yet you may eat these: of all winged creeping things that go on all fours, which have long, jointed legs for hopping on the earth. 22 Even of these you may eat: any kind of locust, any kind of katydid, any kind of cricket, and any kind of grasshopper. 23 But all winged creeping things which have four feet are an abomination to you.

24 “ ‘By these you will become unclean: whoever touches their carcass shall be unclean until the evening. 25 Whoever carries any part of their carcass shall wash his clothes, and be unclean until the evening.

26 “ ‘Every animal which has a split hoof that isn’t completely divided, or doesn’t chew the cud, is unclean to you. Everyone who touches them shall be unclean. 27 Whatever goes on its paws, among all animals that go on all fours, they are unclean to you. Whoever touches their carcass shall be unclean until the evening. 28 He who carries their carcass shall wash his clothes, and be unclean until the evening. They are unclean to you.

29 “ ‘These are they which are unclean to you among the creeping things that creep on the earth: the weasel, the rat, any kind of great lizard, 30 the gecko, and the monitor lizard, the wall lizard, the skink, and the chameleon. 31 These are they which are unclean to you among all that creep. Whoever touches them when they are dead shall be unclean until the evening. 32 Anything they fall on when they are dead shall be unclean; whether it is any vessel of wood, or clothing, or skin, or sack, whatever vessel it is, with which any work is done, it must be put into water, and it shall be unclean until the evening. Then it will be clean. 33 Every earthen vessel into which any of them falls and all that is in it shall be unclean. You shall break it. 34 All food which may be eaten which is soaked in water shall be unclean. All drink that may be drunk in every such vessel shall be unclean. 35 Everything whereupon part of their carcass falls shall be unclean; whether oven, or range for pots, it shall be broken in pieces. They are unclean, and shall be unclean to you. 36 Nevertheless a spring or a cistern in which water is gathered shall be clean, but that which touches their carcass shall be unclean. 37 If part of their carcass falls on any sowing seed which is to be sown, it is clean. 38 But if water is put on the seed, and part of their carcass falls on it, it is unclean to you.

39 “ ‘If any animal of which you may eat dies, he who touches its carcass shall be unclean until the evening. 40 He who eats of its carcass shall wash his clothes, and be unclean until the evening. He also who carries its carcass shall wash his clothes, and be unclean until the evening.

41 “ ‘Every creeping thing that creeps on the earth is an abomination. It shall not be eaten. 42 Whatever goes on its belly, and whatever goes on all fours, or whatever has many feet, even all creeping things that creep on the earth, them you shall not eat; for they are an abomination. 43 You shall not make yourselves abominable with any creeping thing that creeps. You shall not make yourselves unclean with them, that you should be defiled by them. 44 For I am Yahweh your God. Sanctify yourselves therefore, and be holy; for I am holy. You shall not defile yourselves with any kind of creeping thing that moves on the earth. 45 For I am Yahweh who brought you up out of the land of Egypt, to be your God. You shall therefore be holy, for I am holy.

46 “ ‘This is the law of the animal, and of the bird, and of every living creature that moves in the waters, and of every creature that creeps on the earth, 47 to make a distinction between the unclean and the clean, and between the living thing that may be eaten and the living thing that may not be eaten.’ ”

12

1 Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, 2 “Speak to the children of Israel, saying, ‘If a woman conceives, and bears a male child, then she shall be unclean seven days; as in the days of her monthly period she shall be unclean. 3 In the eighth day the flesh of his foreskin shall be circumcised. 4 She shall continue in the blood of purification thirty-three days. She shall not touch any holy thing, nor come into the sanctuary, until the days of her purifying are completed. 5 But if she bears a female child, then she shall be unclean two weeks, as in her period; and she shall continue in the blood of purification sixty-six days.

6 “ ‘When the days of her purification are completed for a son or for a daughter, she shall bring to the priest at the door of the Tent of Meeting, a year old lamb for a burnt offering, and a young pigeon or a turtledove, for a sin offering. 7 He shall offer it before Yahweh, and make atonement for her; then she shall be cleansed from the fountain of her blood.

“ ‘This is the law for her who bears, whether a male or a female. 8 If she cannot afford a lamb, then she shall take two turtledoves or two young pigeons: the one for a burnt offering, and the other for a sin offering. The priest shall make atonement for her, and she shall be clean.’ ”

13

1 Yahweh spoke to Moses and to Aaron, saying, 2 “When a man shall have a swelling in his body’s skin, or a scab, or a bright spot, and it becomes in the skin of his body the plague of leprosy, then he shall be brought to Aaron the priest or to one of his sons, the priests. 3 The priest shall examine the plague in the skin of the body. If the hair in the plague has turned white, and the appearance of the plague is deeper than the body’s skin, it is the plague of leprosy; so the priest shall examine him and pronounce him unclean. 4 If the bright spot is white in the skin of his body, and its appearance isn’t deeper than the skin, and its hair hasn’t turned white, then the priest shall isolate the infected person for seven days. 5 The priest shall examine him on the seventh day. Behold, if in his eyes the plague is arrested and the plague hasn’t spread in the skin, then the priest shall isolate him for seven more days. 6 The priest shall examine him again on the seventh day. Behold, if the plague has faded and the plague hasn’t spread in the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him clean. It is a scab. He shall wash his clothes, and be clean. 7 But if the scab spreads on the skin after he has shown himself to the priest for his cleansing, he shall show himself to the priest again. 8 The priest shall examine him; and behold, if the scab has spread on the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him unclean. It is leprosy.

9 “When the plague of leprosy is in a man, then he shall be brought to the priest; 10 and the priest shall examine him. Behold, if there is a white swelling in the skin, and it has turned the hair white, and there is raw flesh in the swelling, 11 it is a chronic leprosy in the skin of his body, and the priest shall pronounce him unclean. He shall not isolate him, for he is already unclean.

12 “If the leprosy breaks out all over the skin, and the leprosy covers all the skin of the infected person from his head even to his feet, as far as it appears to the priest, 13 then the priest shall examine him. Behold, if the leprosy has covered all his flesh, he shall pronounce him clean of the plague. It has all turned white: he is clean. 14 But whenever raw flesh appears in him, he shall be unclean. 15 The priest shall examine the raw flesh, and pronounce him unclean: the raw flesh is unclean. It is leprosy. 16 Or if the raw flesh turns again, and is changed to white, then he shall come to the priest. 17 The priest shall examine him. Behold, if the plague has turned white, then the priest shall pronounce him clean of the plague. He is clean.

18 “When the body has a boil on its skin, and it has healed, 19 and in the place of the boil there is a white swelling, or a bright spot, reddish-white, then it shall be shown to the priest. 20 The priest shall examine it. Behold, if its appearance is deeper than the skin, and its hair has turned white, then the priest shall pronounce him unclean. It is the plague of leprosy. It has broken out in the boil. 21 But if the priest examines it, and behold, there are no white hairs in it, and it isn’t deeper than the skin, but is dim, then the priest shall isolate him seven days. 22 If it spreads in the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him unclean. It is a plague. 23 But if the bright spot stays in its place, and hasn’t spread, it is the scar from the boil; and the priest shall pronounce him clean.

24 “Or when the body has a burn from fire on its skin, and the raw flesh of the burn becomes a bright spot, reddish-white, or white, 25 then the priest shall examine it; and behold, if the hair in the bright spot has turned white, and its appearance is deeper than the skin, it is leprosy. It has broken out in the burning, and the priest shall pronounce him unclean. It is the plague of leprosy. 26 But if the priest examines it, and behold, there is no white hair in the bright spot, and it isn’t deeper than the skin, but has faded, then the priest shall isolate him seven days. 27 The priest shall examine him on the seventh day. If it has spread in the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him unclean. It is the plague of leprosy. 28 If the bright spot stays in its place, and hasn’t spread in the skin, but is faded, it is the swelling from the burn, and the priest shall pronounce him clean, for it is the scar from the burn.

29 “When a man or woman has a plague on the head or on the beard, 30 then the priest shall examine the plague; and behold, if its appearance is deeper than the skin, and the hair in it is yellow and thin, then the priest shall pronounce him unclean. It is an itch. It is leprosy of the head or of the beard. 31 If the priest examines the plague of itching, and behold, its appearance isn’t deeper than the skin, and there is no black hair in it, then the priest shall isolate the person infected with itching seven days. 32 On the seventh day the priest shall examine the plague; and behold, if the itch hasn’t spread, and there is no yellow hair in it, and the appearance of the itch isn’t deeper than the skin, 33 then he shall be shaved, but he shall not shave the itch. Then the priest shall isolate the one who has the itch seven more days. 34 On the seventh day, the priest shall examine the itch; and behold, if the itch hasn’t spread in the skin, and its appearance isn’t deeper than the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him clean. He shall wash his clothes and be clean. 35 But if the itch spreads in the skin after his cleansing, 36 then the priest shall examine him; and behold, if the itch has spread in the skin, the priest shall not look for the yellow hair; he is unclean. 37 But if in his eyes the itch is arrested and black hair has grown in it, then the itch is healed. He is clean. The priest shall pronounce him clean.

38 “When a man or a woman has bright spots in the skin of the body, even white bright spots, 39 then the priest shall examine them. Behold, if the bright spots on the skin of their body are a dull white, it is a harmless rash. It has broken out in the skin. He is clean.

40 “If a man’s hair has fallen from his head, he is bald. He is clean. 41 If his hair has fallen off from the front part of his head, he is forehead bald. He is clean. 42 But if a reddish-white plague is in the bald head or the bald forehead, it is leprosy breaking out in his bald head or his bald forehead. 43 Then the priest shall examine him. Behold, if the swelling of the plague is reddish-white in his bald head, or in his bald forehead, like the appearance of leprosy in the skin of the body, 44 he is a leprous man. He is unclean. The priest shall surely pronounce him unclean. His plague is on his head.

45 “The leper in whom the plague is shall wear torn clothes, and the hair of his head shall hang loose. He shall cover his upper lip, and shall cry, ‘Unclean! Unclean!’ 46 All the days in which the plague is in him he shall be unclean. He is unclean. He shall dwell alone. His dwelling shall be outside of the camp.

47 “The garment also that the plague of leprosy is in, whether it is a woolen garment, or a linen garment; 48 whether it is in warp or woof;[*] of linen or of wool; whether in a leather, or in anything made of leather; 49 if the plague is greenish or reddish in the garment, or in the leather, or in the warp, or in the woof, or in anything made of leather; it is the plague of leprosy, and shall be shown to the priest. 50 The priest shall examine the plague, and isolate the plague seven days. 51 He shall examine the plague on the seventh day. If the plague has spread in the garment, either in the warp, or in the woof, or in the skin, whatever use the skin is used for, the plague is a destructive mildew. It is unclean. 52 He shall burn the garment, whether the warp or the woof, in wool or in linen, or anything of leather, in which the plague is, for it is a destructive mildew. It shall be burned in the fire.

53 “If the priest examines it, and behold, the plague hasn’t spread in the garment, either in the warp, or in the woof, or in anything of skin; 54 then the priest shall command that they wash the thing that the plague is in, and he shall isolate it seven more days. 55 Then the priest shall examine it, after the plague is washed; and behold, if the plague hasn’t changed its color, and the plague hasn’t spread, it is unclean; you shall burn it in the fire. It is a mildewed spot, whether the bareness is inside or outside. 56 If the priest looks, and behold, the plague has faded after it is washed, then he shall tear it out of the garment, or out of the skin, or out of the warp, or out of the woof; 57 and if it appears again in the garment, either in the warp, or in the woof, or in anything of skin, it is spreading. You shall burn what the plague is in with fire. 58 The garment, either the warp, or the woof, or whatever thing of skin it is, which you shall wash, if the plague has departed from them, then it shall be washed the second time, and it will be clean.”

59 This is the law of the plague of mildew in a garment of wool or linen, either in the warp, or the woof, or in anything of skin, to pronounce it clean, or to pronounce it unclean.

14

1 Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying,

2 “This shall be the law of the leper in the day of his cleansing: He shall be brought to the priest, 3 and the priest shall go out of the camp. The priest shall examine him. Behold, if the plague of leprosy is healed in the leper, 4 then the priest shall command them to take for him who is to be cleansed two living clean birds, cedar wood, scarlet, and hyssop. 5 The priest shall command them to kill one of the birds in an earthen vessel over running water. 6 As for the living bird, he shall take it, the cedar wood, the scarlet, and the hyssop, and shall dip them and the living bird in the blood of the bird that was killed over the running water. 7 He shall sprinkle on him who is to be cleansed from the leprosy seven times, and shall pronounce him clean, and shall let the living bird go into the open field.

8 “He who is to be cleansed shall wash his clothes, and shave off all his hair, and bathe himself in water; and he shall be clean. After that he shall come into the camp, but shall dwell outside his tent seven days. 9 It shall be on the seventh day, that he shall shave all his hair off his head and his beard and his eyebrows. He shall shave off all his hair. He shall wash his clothes, and he shall bathe his body in water. Then he shall be clean.

10 “On the eighth day he shall take two male lambs without defect, one ewe lamb a year old without defect, three tenths of an ephah[*] of fine flour for a meal offering, mixed with oil, and one log[†] of oil. 11 The priest who cleanses him shall set the man who is to be cleansed, and those things, before Yahweh, at the door of the Tent of Meeting.

12 “The priest shall take one of the male lambs, and offer him for a trespass offering, with the log of oil, and wave them for a wave offering before Yahweh. 13 He shall kill the male lamb in the place where they kill the sin offering and the burnt offering, in the place of the sanctuary; for as the sin offering is the priest’s, so is the trespass offering. It is most holy. 14 The priest shall take some of the blood of the trespass offering, and the priest shall put it on the tip of the right ear of him who is to be cleansed, and on the thumb of his right hand, and on the big toe of his right foot. 15 The priest shall take some of the log of oil, and pour it into the palm of his own left hand. 16 The priest shall dip his right finger in the oil that is in his left hand, and shall sprinkle some of the oil with his finger seven times before Yahweh. 17 The priest shall put some of the rest of the oil that is in his hand on the tip of the right ear of him who is to be cleansed, and on the thumb of his right hand, and on the big toe of his right foot, upon the blood of the trespass offering. 18 The rest of the oil that is in the priest’s hand he shall put on the head of him who is to be cleansed, and the priest shall make atonement for him before Yahweh.

19 “The priest shall offer the sin offering, and make atonement for him who is to be cleansed because of his uncleanness. Afterward he shall kill the burnt offering; 20 then the priest shall offer the burnt offering and the meal offering on the altar. The priest shall make atonement for him, and he shall be clean.

21 “If he is poor, and can’t afford so much, then he shall take one male lamb for a trespass offering to be waved, to make atonement for him, and one tenth of an ephah[‡] of fine flour mixed with oil for a meal offering, and a log[§] of oil; 22 and two turtledoves, or two young pigeons, such as he is able to afford; and the one shall be a sin offering, and the other a burnt offering.

23 “On the eighth day he shall bring them for his cleansing to the priest, to the door of the Tent of Meeting, before Yahweh. 24 The priest shall take the lamb of the trespass offering, and the log of oil, and the priest shall wave them for a wave offering before Yahweh. 25 He shall kill the lamb of the trespass offering. The priest shall take some of the blood of the trespass offering and put it on the tip of the right ear of him who is to be cleansed, and on the thumb of his right hand, and on the big toe of his right foot. 26 The priest shall pour some of the oil into the palm of his own left hand; 27 and the priest shall sprinkle with his right finger some of the oil that is in his left hand seven times before Yahweh. 28 Then the priest shall put some of the oil that is in his hand on the tip of the right ear of him who is to be cleansed, and on the thumb of his right hand, and on the big toe of his right foot, on the place of the blood of the trespass offering. 29 The rest of the oil that is in the priest’s hand he shall put on the head of him who is to be cleansed, to make atonement for him before Yahweh. 30 He shall offer one of the turtledoves, or of the young pigeons, which ever he is able to afford, 31 of the kind he is able to afford, the one for a sin offering, and the other for a burnt offering, with the meal offering. The priest shall make atonement for him who is to be cleansed before Yahweh.”

32 This is the law for him in whom is the plague of leprosy, who is not able to afford the sacrifice for his cleansing.

33 Yahweh spoke to Moses and to Aaron, saying, 34 “When you have come into the land of Canaan, which I give to you for a possession, and I put a spreading mildew in a house in the land of your possession, 35 then he who owns the house shall come and tell the priest, saying, ‘There seems to me to be some sort of plague in the house.’ 36 The priest shall command that they empty the house, before the priest goes in to examine the plague, that all that is in the house not be made unclean. Afterward the priest shall go in to inspect the house. 37 He shall examine the plague; and behold, if the plague is in the walls of the house with hollow streaks, greenish or reddish, and it appears to be deeper than the wall, 38 then the priest shall go out of the house to the door of the house, and shut up the house seven days. 39 The priest shall come again on the seventh day, and look. If the plague has spread in the walls of the house, 40 then the priest shall command that they take out the stones in which is the plague, and cast them into an unclean place outside of the city. 41 He shall cause the inside of the house to be scraped all over. They shall pour out the mortar that they scraped off outside of the city into an unclean place. 42 They shall take other stones, and put them in the place of those stones; and he shall take other mortar, and shall plaster the house.

43 “If the plague comes again, and breaks out in the house after he has taken out the stones, and after he has scraped the house, and after it was plastered, 44 then the priest shall come in and look; and behold, if the plague has spread in the house, it is a destructive mildew in the house. It is unclean. 45 He shall break down the house, its stones, and its timber, and all the house’s mortar. He shall carry them out of the city into an unclean place.

46 “Moreover he who goes into the house while it is shut up shall be unclean until the evening. 47 He who lies down in the house shall wash his clothes; and he who eats in the house shall wash his clothes.

48 “If the priest shall come in, and examine it, and behold, the plague hasn’t spread in the house, after the house was plastered, then the priest shall pronounce the house clean, because the plague is healed. 49 To cleanse the house he shall take two birds, cedar wood, scarlet, and hyssop. 50 He shall kill one of the birds in an earthen vessel over running water. 51 He shall take the cedar wood, the hyssop, the scarlet, and the living bird, and dip them in the blood of the slain bird, and in the running water, and sprinkle the house seven times. 52 He shall cleanse the house with the blood of the bird, and with the running water, with the living bird, with the cedar wood, with the hyssop, and with the scarlet; 53 but he shall let the living bird go out of the city into the open field. So shall he make atonement for the house; and it shall be clean.”

54 This is the law for any plague of leprosy, and for an itch, 55 and for the destructive mildew of a garment, and for a house, 56 and for a swelling, and for a scab, and for a bright spot; 57 to teach when it is unclean, and when it is clean.

This is the law of leprosy.

15

1 Yahweh spoke to Moses and to Aaron, saying, 2 “Speak to the children of Israel, and tell them, ‘When any man has a discharge from his body, because of his discharge he is unclean. 3 This shall be his uncleanness in his discharge: whether his body runs with his discharge, or his body has stopped from his discharge, it is his uncleanness.

4 “ ‘Every bed on which he who has the discharge lies shall be unclean; and everything he sits on shall be unclean. 5 Whoever touches his bed shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the evening. 6 He who sits on anything on which the man who has the discharge sat shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the evening.

7 “ ‘He who touches the body of him who has the discharge shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the evening.

8 “ ‘If he who has the discharge spits on him who is clean, then he shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the evening.

9 “ ‘Whatever saddle he who has the discharge rides on shall be unclean. 10 Whoever touches anything that was under him shall be unclean until the evening. He who carries those things shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the evening.

11 “ ‘Whomever he who has the discharge touches, without having rinsed his hands in water, he shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the evening.

12 “ ‘The earthen vessel, which he who has the discharge touches, shall be broken; and every vessel of wood shall be rinsed in water.

13 “ ‘When he who has a discharge is cleansed of his discharge, then he shall count to himself seven days for his cleansing, and wash his clothes; and he shall bathe his flesh in running water, and shall be clean.

14 “ ‘On the eighth day he shall take two turtledoves, or two young pigeons, and come before Yahweh to the door of the Tent of Meeting, and give them to the priest. 15 The priest shall offer them, the one for a sin offering, and the other for a burnt offering. The priest shall make atonement for him before Yahweh for his discharge.

16 “ ‘If any man has an emission of semen, then he shall bathe all his flesh in water, and be unclean until the evening. 17 Every garment and every skin which the semen is on shall be washed with water, and be unclean until the evening. 18 If a man lies with a woman and there is an emission of semen, they shall both bathe themselves in water, and be unclean until the evening.

19 “ ‘If a woman has a discharge, and her discharge in her flesh is blood, she shall be in her impurity seven days. Whoever touches her shall be unclean until the evening.

20 “ ‘Everything that she lies on in her impurity shall be unclean. Everything also that she sits on shall be unclean. 21 Whoever touches her bed shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the evening. 22 Whoever touches anything that she sits on shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the evening. 23 If it is on the bed, or on anything she sits on, when he touches it, he shall be unclean until the evening.

24 “ ‘If any man lies with her, and her monthly flow is on him, he shall be unclean seven days; and every bed he lies on shall be unclean.

25 “ ‘If a woman has a discharge of her blood many days not in the time of her period, or if she has a discharge beyond the time of her period, all the days of the discharge of her uncleanness shall be as in the days of her period. She is unclean. 26 Every bed she lies on all the days of her discharge shall be to her as the bed of her period. Everything she sits on shall be unclean, as the uncleanness of her period. 27 Whoever touches these things shall be unclean, and shall wash his clothes and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the evening.

28 “ ‘But if she is cleansed of her discharge, then she shall count to herself seven days, and after that she shall be clean. 29 On the eighth day she shall take two turtledoves, or two young pigeons, and bring them to the priest, to the door of the Tent of Meeting. 30 The priest shall offer the one for a sin offering, and the other for a burnt offering; and the priest shall make atonement for her before Yahweh for the uncleanness of her discharge.

31 “ ‘Thus you shall separate the children of Israel from their uncleanness, so they will not die in their uncleanness when they defile my tabernacle that is among them.’ ”

32 This is the law of him who has a discharge, and of him who has an emission of semen, so that he is unclean by it; 33 and of her who has her period, and of a man or woman who has a discharge, and of him who lies with her who is unclean.

16

1 Yahweh spoke to Moses after the death of the two sons of Aaron, when they came near before Yahweh, and died; 2 and Yahweh said to Moses, “Tell Aaron your brother not to come at just any time into the Most Holy Place within the veil, before the mercy seat which is on the ark; lest he die; for I will appear in the cloud on the mercy seat.

3 “Aaron shall come into the sanctuary with a young bull for a sin offering, and a ram for a burnt offering. 4 He shall put on the holy linen tunic. He shall have the linen trousers on his body, and shall put on the linen sash, and he shall be clothed with the linen turban. They are the holy garments. He shall bathe his body in water, and put them on. 5 He shall take from the congregation of the children of Israel two male goats for a sin offering, and one ram for a burnt offering.

6 “Aaron shall offer the bull of the sin offering, which is for himself, and make atonement for himself and for his house. 7 He shall take the two goats, and set them before Yahweh at the door of the Tent of Meeting. 8 Aaron shall cast lots for the two goats: one lot for Yahweh, and the other lot for the scapegoat. 9 Aaron shall present the goat on which the lot fell for Yahweh, and offer him for a sin offering. 10 But the goat on which the lot fell for the scapegoat shall be presented alive before Yahweh, to make atonement for him, to send him away as the scapegoat into the wilderness.

11 “Aaron shall present the bull of the sin offering, which is for himself, and shall make atonement for himself and for his house, and shall kill the bull of the sin offering which is for himself. 12 He shall take a censer full of coals of fire from off the altar before Yahweh, and two handfuls of sweet incense beaten small, and bring it within the veil. 13 He shall put the incense on the fire before Yahweh, that the cloud of the incense may cover the mercy seat that is on the covenant, so that he will not die. 14 He shall take some of the blood of the bull, and sprinkle it with his finger on the mercy seat on the east; and before the mercy seat he shall sprinkle some of the blood with his finger seven times.

15 “Then he shall kill the goat of the sin offering that is for the people, and bring his blood within the veil, and do with his blood as he did with the blood of the bull, and sprinkle it on the mercy seat and before the mercy seat. 16 He shall make atonement for the Holy Place, because of the uncleanness of the children of Israel, and because of their transgressions, even all their sins; and so he shall do for the Tent of Meeting that dwells with them in the middle of their uncleanness. 17 No one shall be in the Tent of Meeting when he enters to make atonement in the Holy Place, until he comes out, and has made atonement for himself and for his household, and for all the assembly of Israel.

18 “He shall go out to the altar that is before Yahweh and make atonement for it, and shall take some of the bull’s blood, and some of the goat’s blood, and put it around on the horns of the altar. 19 He shall sprinkle some of the blood on it with his finger seven times, and cleanse it, and make it holy from the uncleanness of the children of Israel.

20 “When he has finished atoning for the Holy Place, the Tent of Meeting, and the altar, he shall present the live goat. 21 Aaron shall lay both his hands on the head of the live goat, and confess over him all the iniquities of the children of Israel, and all their transgressions, even all their sins; and he shall put them on the head of the goat, and shall send him away into the wilderness by the hand of a man who is ready. 22 The goat shall carry all their iniquities on himself to a solitary land, and he shall release the goat in the wilderness.

23 “Aaron shall come into the Tent of Meeting, and shall take off the linen garments which he put on when he went into the Holy Place, and shall leave them there. 24 Then he shall bathe himself in water in a holy place, put on his garments, and come out and offer his burnt offering and the burnt offering of the people, and make atonement for himself and for the people. 25 The fat of the sin offering he shall burn on the altar.

26 “He who lets the goat go as the scapegoat shall wash his clothes, and bathe his flesh in water, and afterward he shall come into the camp. 27 The bull for the sin offering, and the goat for the sin offering, whose blood was brought in to make atonement in the Holy Place, shall be carried outside the camp; and they shall burn their skins, their flesh, and their dung with fire. 28 He who burns them shall wash his clothes, and bathe his flesh in water, and afterward he shall come into the camp.

29 “It shall be a statute to you forever: in the seventh month, on the tenth day of the month, you shall afflict your souls, and shall do no kind of work, whether native-born or a stranger who lives as a foreigner among you; 30 for on this day shall atonement be made for you, to cleanse you. You shall be clean from all your sins before Yahweh. 31 It is a Sabbath of solemn rest to you, and you shall afflict your souls. It is a statute forever. 32 The priest, who is anointed and who is consecrated to be priest in his father’s place, shall make the atonement, and shall put on the linen garments, even the holy garments. 33 Then he shall make atonement for the Holy Sanctuary; and he shall make atonement for the Tent of Meeting and for the altar; and he shall make atonement for the priests and for all the people of the assembly.

34 “This shall be an everlasting statute for you, to make atonement for the children of Israel once in the year because of all their sins.”

It was done as Yahweh commanded Moses.

17

1 Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, 2 “Speak to Aaron, and to his sons, and to all the children of Israel, and say to them, ‘This is the thing which Yahweh has commanded: 3 Whatever man there is of the house of Israel who kills a bull, or lamb, or goat in the camp, or who kills it outside the camp, 4 and hasn’t brought it to the door of the Tent of Meeting to offer it as an offering to Yahweh before Yahweh’s tabernacle: blood shall be imputed to that man. He has shed blood. That man shall be cut off from among his people. 5 This is to the end that the children of Israel may bring their sacrifices, which they sacrifice in the open field, that they may bring them to Yahweh, to the door of the Tent of Meeting, to the priest, and sacrifice them for sacrifices of peace offerings to Yahweh. 6 The priest shall sprinkle the blood on Yahweh’s altar at the door of the Tent of Meeting, and burn the fat for a pleasant aroma to Yahweh. 7 They shall no more sacrifice their sacrifices to the goat idols, after which they play the prostitute. This shall be a statute forever to them throughout their generations.’

8 “You shall say to them, ‘Any man there is of the house of Israel, or of the strangers who live as foreigners among them, who offers a burnt offering or sacrifice, 9 and doesn’t bring it to the door of the Tent of Meeting to sacrifice it to Yahweh, that man shall be cut off from his people.

10 “ ‘Any man of the house of Israel, or of the strangers who live as foreigners among them, who eats any kind of blood, I will set my face against that soul who eats blood, and will cut him off from among his people. 11 For the life of the flesh is in the blood. I have given it to you on the altar to make atonement for your souls; for it is the blood that makes atonement by reason of the life. 12 Therefore I have said to the children of Israel, “No person among you may eat blood, nor may any stranger who lives as a foreigner among you eat blood.”

13 “ ‘Whatever man there is of the children of Israel, or of the strangers who live as foreigners among them, who takes in hunting any animal or bird that may be eaten, he shall pour out its blood, and cover it with dust. 14 For as to the life of all flesh, its blood is with its life. Therefore I said to the children of Israel, “You shall not eat the blood of any kind of flesh; for the life of all flesh is its blood. Whoever eats it shall be cut off.”

15 “ ‘Every person that eats what dies of itself, or that which is torn by animals, whether he is native-born or a foreigner, shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the evening. Then he shall be clean. 16 But if he doesn’t wash them, or bathe his flesh, then he shall bear his iniquity.’ ”

18

1 Yahweh said to Moses, 2 “Speak to the children of Israel, and say to them, ‘I am Yahweh your God. 3 You shall not do as they do in the land of Egypt, where you lived. You shall not do as they do in the land of Canaan, where I am bringing you. You shall not follow their statutes. 4 You shall do my ordinances. You shall keep my statutes and walk in them. I am Yahweh your God. 5 You shall therefore keep my statutes and my ordinances, which if a man does, he shall live in them. I am Yahweh.

6 “ ‘None of you shall approach any close relatives, to uncover their nakedness: I am Yahweh.

7 “ ‘You shall not uncover the nakedness of your father, nor the nakedness of your mother: she is your mother. You shall not uncover her nakedness.

8 “ ‘You shall not uncover the nakedness of your father’s wife. It is your father’s nakedness.

9 “ ‘You shall not uncover the nakedness of your sister, the daughter of your father, or the daughter of your mother, whether born at home or born abroad.

10 “ ‘You shall not uncover the nakedness of your son’s daughter, or of your daughter’s daughter, even their nakedness; for theirs is your own nakedness.

11 “ ‘You shall not uncover the nakedness of your father’s wife’s daughter, conceived by your father, since she is your sister.

12 “ ‘You shall not uncover the nakedness of your father’s sister. She is your father’s near kinswoman.

13 “ ‘You shall not uncover the nakedness of your mother’s sister, for she is your mother’s near kinswoman.

14 “ ‘You shall not uncover the nakedness of your father’s brother. You shall not approach his wife. She is your aunt.

15 “ ‘You shall not uncover the nakedness of your daughter-in-law. She is your son’s wife. You shall not uncover her nakedness.

16 “ ‘You shall not uncover the nakedness of your brother’s wife. It is your brother’s nakedness.

17 “ ‘You shall not uncover the nakedness of a woman and her daughter. You shall not take her son’s daughter, or her daughter’s daughter, to uncover her nakedness. They are near kinswomen. It is wickedness.

18 “ ‘You shall not take a wife in addition to her sister, to be a rival, to uncover her nakedness, while her sister is still alive.

19 “ ‘You shall not approach a woman to uncover her nakedness, as long as she is impure by her uncleanness.

20 “ ‘You shall not lie carnally with your neighbor’s wife, and defile yourself with her.

21 “ ‘You shall not give any of your children as a sacrifice to Molech. You shall not profane the name of your God. I am Yahweh.

22 “ ‘You shall not lie with a man as with a woman. That is detestable.

23 “ ‘You shall not lie with any animal to defile yourself with it. No woman may give herself to an animal, to lie down with it: it is a perversion.

24 “ ‘Don’t defile yourselves in any of these things; for in all these the nations which I am casting out before you were defiled. 25 The land was defiled. Therefore I punished its iniquity, and the land vomited out her inhabitants. 26 You therefore shall keep my statutes and my ordinances, and shall not do any of these abominations; neither the native-born, nor the stranger who lives as a foreigner among you 27 (for the men of the land that were before you had done all these abominations, and the land became defiled), 28 that the land not vomit you out also, when you defile it, as it vomited out the nation that was before you.

29 “ ‘For whoever shall do any of these abominations, even the souls that do them shall be cut off from among their people. 30 Therefore you shall keep my requirements, that you do not practice any of these abominable customs which were practiced before you, and that you do not defile yourselves with them. I am Yahweh your God.’ ”

19

1 Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, 2 “Speak to all the congregation of the children of Israel, and tell them, ‘You shall be holy; for I, Yahweh your God, am holy.

3 “ ‘Each one of you shall respect his mother and his father. You shall keep my Sabbaths. I am Yahweh your God.

4 “ ‘Don’t turn to idols, nor make molten gods for yourselves. I am Yahweh your God.

5 “ ‘When you offer a sacrifice of peace offerings to Yahweh, you shall offer it so that you may be accepted. 6 It shall be eaten the same day you offer it, and on the next day. If anything remains until the third day, it shall be burned with fire. 7 If it is eaten at all on the third day, it is an abomination. It will not be accepted; 8 but everyone who eats it shall bear his iniquity, because he has profaned the holy thing of Yahweh, and that soul shall be cut off from his people.

9 “ ‘When you reap the harvest of your land, you shall not wholly reap the corners of your field, neither shall you gather the gleanings of your harvest. 10 You shall not glean your vineyard, neither shall you gather the fallen grapes of your vineyard. You shall leave them for the poor and for the foreigner. I am Yahweh your God.

11 “ ‘You shall not steal.

“ ‘You shall not lie.

“ ‘You shall not deceive one another.

12 “ ‘You shall not swear by my name falsely, and profane the name of your God. I am Yahweh.

13 “ ‘You shall not oppress your neighbor, nor rob him.

“ ‘The wages of a hired servant shall not remain with you all night until the morning.

14 “ ‘You shall not curse the deaf, nor put a stumbling block before the blind; but you shall fear your God. I am Yahweh.

15 “ ‘You shall do no injustice in judgment. You shall not be partial to the poor, nor show favoritism to the great; but you shall judge your neighbor in righteousness.

16 “ ‘You shall not go around as a slanderer among your people.

“ ‘You shall not endanger the life[*] of your neighbor. I am Yahweh.

17 “ ‘You shall not hate your brother in your heart. You shall surely rebuke your neighbor, and not bear sin because of him.

18 “ ‘You shall not take vengeance, nor bear any grudge against the children of your people; but you shall love your neighbor as yourself. I am Yahweh.

19 “ ‘You shall keep my statutes.

“ ‘You shall not cross-breed different kinds of animals.

“ ‘You shall not sow your field with two kinds of seed;

“ ‘Don’t wear a garment made of two kinds of material.

20 “ ‘If a man lies carnally with a woman who is a slave girl, pledged to be married to another man, and not ransomed or given her freedom; they shall be punished. They shall not be put to death, because she was not free. 21 He shall bring his trespass offering to Yahweh, to the door of the Tent of Meeting, even a ram for a trespass offering. 22 The priest shall make atonement for him with the ram of the trespass offering before Yahweh for his sin which he has committed; and the sin which he has committed shall be forgiven him.

23 “ ‘When you come into the land, and have planted all kinds of trees for food, then you shall count their fruit as forbidden.[†] For three years it shall be forbidden to you. It shall not be eaten. 24 But in the fourth year all its fruit shall be holy, for giving praise to Yahweh. 25 In the fifth year you shall eat its fruit, that it may yield its increase to you. I am Yahweh your God.

26 “ ‘You shall not eat any meat with the blood still in it. You shall not use enchantments, nor practice sorcery.

27 “ ‘You shall not cut the hair on the sides of your head or clip off the edge of your beard.

28 “ ‘You shall not make any cuttings in your flesh for the dead, nor tattoo any marks on you. I am Yahweh.

29 “ ‘Don’t profane your daughter, to make her a prostitute; lest the land fall to prostitution, and the land become full of wickedness.

30 “ ‘You shall keep my Sabbaths, and reverence my sanctuary; I am Yahweh.

31 “ ‘Don’t turn to those who are mediums, nor to the wizards. Don’t seek them out, to be defiled by them. I am Yahweh your God.

32 “ ‘You shall rise up before the gray head and honor the face of the elderly; and you shall fear your God. I am Yahweh.

33 “ ‘If a stranger lives as a foreigner with you in your land, you shall not do him wrong. 34 The stranger who lives as a foreigner with you shall be to you as the native-born among you, and you shall love him as yourself; for you lived as foreigners in the land of Egypt. I am Yahweh your God.

35 “ ‘You shall do no unrighteousness in judgment, in measures of length, of weight, or of quantity. 36 You shall have just balances, just weights, a just ephah,[‡] and a just hin.[§] I am Yahweh your God, who brought you out of the land of Egypt.

37 “ ‘You shall observe all my statutes and all my ordinances, and do them. I am Yahweh.’ ”

20

1 Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, 2 “Moreover, you shall tell the children of Israel, ‘Anyone of the children of Israel, or of the strangers who live as foreigners in Israel, who gives any of his offspring[*] to Molech shall surely be put to death. The people of the land shall stone that person with stones. 3 I also will set my face against that person, and will cut him off from among his people, because he has given of his offspring to Molech, to defile my sanctuary, and to profane my holy name. 4 If the people of the land all hide their eyes from that person when he gives of his offspring to Molech, and don’t put him to death, 5 then I will set my face against that man and against his family, and will cut him off, and all who play the prostitute after him to play the prostitute with Molech, from among their people.

6 “ ‘The person that turns to those who are mediums and wizards, to play the prostitute after them, I will even set my face against that person, and will cut him off from among his people.

7 “ ‘Sanctify yourselves therefore, and be holy; for I am Yahweh your God. 8 You shall keep my statutes, and do them. I am Yahweh who sanctifies you.

9 “ ‘For everyone who curses his father or his mother shall surely be put to death. He has cursed his father or his mother. His blood shall be upon himself.

10 “ ‘The man who commits adultery with another man’s wife, even he who commits adultery with his neighbor’s wife, the adulterer and the adulteress shall surely be put to death.

11 “ ‘The man who lies with his father’s wife has uncovered his father’s nakedness. Both of them shall surely be put to death. Their blood shall be upon themselves.

12 “ ‘If a man lies with his daughter-in-law, both of them shall surely be put to death. They have committed a perversion. Their blood shall be upon themselves.

13 “ ‘If a man lies with a male, as with a woman, both of them have committed an abomination. They shall surely be put to death. Their blood shall be upon themselves.

14 “ ‘If a man takes a wife and her mother, it is wickedness. They shall be burned with fire, both he and they, that there may be no wickedness among you.

15 “ ‘If a man lies with an animal, he shall surely be put to death; and you shall kill the animal.

16 “ ‘If a woman approaches any animal and lies with it, you shall kill the woman and the animal. They shall surely be put to death. Their blood shall be upon them.

17 “ ‘If a man takes his sister—his father’s daughter, or his mother’s daughter—and sees her nakedness, and she sees his nakedness, it is a shameful thing. They shall be cut off in the sight of the children of their people. He has uncovered his sister’s nakedness. He shall bear his iniquity.

18 “ ‘If a man lies with a woman having her monthly period, and uncovers her nakedness, he has made her fountain naked, and she has uncovered the fountain of her blood. Both of them shall be cut off from among their people.

19 “ ‘You shall not uncover the nakedness of your mother’s sister, nor of your father’s sister, for he has made his close relative naked. They shall bear their iniquity. 20 If a man lies with his uncle’s wife, he has uncovered his uncle’s nakedness. They shall bear their sin. They shall die childless.

21 “ ‘If a man takes his brother’s wife, it is an impurity. He has uncovered his brother’s nakedness. They shall be childless.

22 “ ‘You shall therefore keep all my statutes and all my ordinances, and do them, that the land where I am bringing you to dwell may not vomit you out. 23 You shall not walk in the customs of the nation which I am casting out before you; for they did all these things, and therefore I abhorred them. 24 But I have said to you, “You shall inherit their land, and I will give it to you to possess it, a land flowing with milk and honey.” I am Yahweh your God, who has separated you from the peoples.

25 “ ‘You shall therefore make a distinction between the clean animal and the unclean, and between the unclean fowl and the clean. You shall not make yourselves abominable by animal, or by bird, or by anything with which the ground teems, which I have separated from you as unclean for you. 26 You shall be holy to me, for I, Yahweh, am holy, and have set you apart from the peoples, that you should be mine.

27 “ ‘A man or a woman that is a medium or is a wizard shall surely be put to death. They shall be stoned with stones. Their blood shall be upon themselves.’ ”

21

1 Yahweh said to Moses, “Speak to the priests, the sons of Aaron, and say to them, ‘A priest shall not defile himself for the dead among his people, 2 except for his relatives that are near to him: for his mother, for his father, for his son, for his daughter, for his brother, 3 and for his virgin sister who is near to him, who has had no husband; for her he may defile himself. 4 He shall not defile himself, being a chief man among his people, to profane himself.

5 “ ‘They shall not shave their heads or shave off the corners of their beards or make any cuttings in their flesh. 6 They shall be holy to their God, and not profane the name of their God, for they offer the offerings of Yahweh made by fire, the bread of their God. Therefore they shall be holy.

7 “ ‘They shall not marry a woman who is a prostitute, or profane. A priest shall not marry a woman divorced from her husband; for he is holy to his God. 8 Therefore you shall sanctify him, for he offers the bread of your God. He shall be holy to you, for I Yahweh, who sanctify you, am holy.

9 “ ‘The daughter of any priest, if she profanes herself by playing the prostitute, she profanes her father. She shall be burned with fire.

10 “ ‘He who is the high priest among his brothers, upon whose head the anointing oil is poured, and who is consecrated to put on the garments, shall not let the hair of his head hang loose, or tear his clothes. 11 He must not go in to any dead body, or defile himself for his father or for his mother. 12 He shall not go out of the sanctuary, nor profane the sanctuary of his God; for the crown of the anointing oil of his God is upon him. I am Yahweh.

13 “ ‘He shall take a wife in her virginity. 14 He shall not marry a widow, or one divorced, or a woman who has been defiled, or a prostitute. He shall take a virgin of his own people as a wife. 15 He shall not profane his offspring among his people, for I am Yahweh who sanctifies him.’ ”

16 Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, 17 “Say to Aaron, ‘None of your offspring throughout their generations who has a defect may approach to offer the bread of his God. 18 For whatever man he is that has a defect, he shall not draw near: a blind man, or a lame, or he who has a flat nose, or any deformity, 19 or a man who has an injured foot, or an injured hand, 20 or hunchbacked, or a dwarf, or one who has a defect in his eye, or an itching disease, or scabs, or who has damaged testicles. 21 No man of the offspring of Aaron the priest who has a defect shall come near to offer the offerings of Yahweh made by fire. Since he has a defect, he shall not come near to offer the bread of his God. 22 He shall eat the bread of his God, both of the most holy, and of the holy. 23 He shall not come near to the veil, nor come near to the altar, because he has a defect; that he may not profane my sanctuaries, for I am Yahweh who sanctifies them.’ ”

24 So Moses spoke to Aaron, and to his sons, and to all the children of Israel.

22

1 Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, 2 “Tell Aaron and his sons to separate themselves from the holy things of the children of Israel, which they make holy to me, and that they not profane my holy name. I am Yahweh.

3 “Tell them, ‘If anyone of all your offspring throughout your generations approaches the holy things which the children of Israel make holy to Yahweh, having his uncleanness on him, that soul shall be cut off from before me. I am Yahweh.

4 “ ‘Whoever of the offspring of Aaron is a leper or has a discharge shall not eat of the holy things until he is clean. Whoever touches anything that is unclean by the dead, or a man who has a seminal emission, 5 or whoever touches any creeping thing by which he may be made unclean, or a man from whom he may become unclean, whatever uncleanness he has— 6 the person that touches any such shall be unclean until the evening, and shall not eat of the holy things unless he bathes his body in water. 7 When the sun is down, he shall be clean; and afterward he shall eat of the holy things, because it is his bread. 8 He shall not eat that which dies of itself or is torn by animals, defiling himself by it. I am Yahweh.

9 “ ‘They shall therefore follow my commandment, lest they bear sin for it and die in it, if they profane it. I am Yahweh who sanctifies them.

10 “ ‘No stranger shall eat of the holy thing: a foreigner living with the priests, or a hired servant, shall not eat of the holy thing. 11 But if a priest buys a slave, purchased by his money, he shall eat of it; and those who are born in his house shall eat of his bread. 12 If a priest’s daughter is married to an outsider, she shall not eat of the heave offering of the holy things. 13 But if a priest’s daughter is a widow, or divorced, and has no child, and has returned to her father’s house as in her youth, she may eat of her father’s bread; but no stranger shall eat any of it.

14 “ ‘If a man eats something holy unwittingly, then he shall add the fifth part of its value to it, and shall give the holy thing to the priest. 15 The priests shall not profane the holy things of the children of Israel, which they offer to Yahweh, 16 and so cause them to bear the iniquity that brings guilt when they eat their holy things; for I am Yahweh who sanctifies them.’ ”

17 Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, 18 “Speak to Aaron, and to his sons, and to all the children of Israel, and say to them, ‘Whoever is of the house of Israel, or of the foreigners in Israel, who offers his offering, whether it is any of their vows or any of their free will offerings, which they offer to Yahweh for a burnt offering: 19 that you may be accepted, you shall offer a male without defect, of the bulls, of the sheep, or of the goats. 20 But you shall not offer whatever has a defect, for it shall not be acceptable for you. 21 Whoever offers a sacrifice of peace offerings to Yahweh to accomplish a vow, or for a free will offering of the herd or of the flock, it shall be perfect to be accepted. It shall have no defect. 22 You shall not offer what is blind, is injured, is maimed, has a wart, is festering, or has a running sore to Yahweh, nor make an offering by fire of them on the altar to Yahweh. 23 Either a bull or a lamb that has any deformity or lacking in his parts, that you may offer for a free will offering; but for a vow it shall not be accepted. 24 You must not offer to Yahweh that which has its testicles bruised, crushed, broken, or cut. You must not do this in your land. 25 You must not offer any of these as the bread of your God from the hand of a foreigner, because their corruption is in them. There is a defect in them. They shall not be accepted for you.’ ”

26 Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, 27 “When a bull, a sheep, or a goat is born, it shall remain seven days with its mother. From the eighth day on it shall be accepted for the offering of an offering made by fire to Yahweh. 28 Whether it is a cow or ewe, you shall not kill it and its young both in one day.

29 “When you sacrifice a sacrifice of thanksgiving to Yahweh, you shall sacrifice it so that you may be accepted. 30 It shall be eaten on the same day; you shall leave none of it until the morning. I am Yahweh.

31 “Therefore you shall keep my commandments, and do them. I am Yahweh. 32 You shall not profane my holy name, but I will be made holy among the children of Israel. I am Yahweh who makes you holy, 33 who brought you out of the land of Egypt, to be your God. I am Yahweh.”

23

1 Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, 2 “Speak to the children of Israel, and tell them, ‘The set feasts of Yahweh, which you shall proclaim to be holy convocations, even these are my set feasts.

3 “ ‘Six days shall work be done, but on the seventh day is a Sabbath of solemn rest, a holy convocation; you shall do no kind of work. It is a Sabbath to Yahweh in all your dwellings.

4 “ ‘These are the set feasts of Yahweh, even holy convocations, which you shall proclaim in their appointed season. 5 In the first month, on the fourteenth day of the month in the evening, is Yahweh’s Passover. 6 On the fifteenth day of the same month is the feast of unleavened bread to Yahweh. Seven days you shall eat unleavened bread. 7 In the first day you shall have a holy convocation. You shall do no regular work. 8 But you shall offer an offering made by fire to Yahweh seven days. In the seventh day is a holy convocation. You shall do no regular work.’ ”

9 Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, 10 “Speak to the children of Israel, and tell them, ‘When you have come into the land which I give to you, and shall reap its harvest, then you shall bring the sheaf of the first fruits of your harvest to the priest. 11 He shall wave the sheaf before Yahweh, to be accepted for you. On the next day after the Sabbath the priest shall wave it. 12 On the day when you wave the sheaf, you shall offer a male lamb without defect a year old for a burnt offering to Yahweh. 13 The meal offering with it shall be two tenths of an ephah[*] of fine flour mixed with oil, an offering made by fire to Yahweh for a pleasant aroma; and the drink offering with it shall be of wine, the fourth part of a hin.[†] 14 You must not eat bread, or roasted grain, or fresh grain, until this same day, until you have brought the offering of your God. This is a statute forever throughout your generations in all your dwellings.

15 “ ‘You shall count from the next day after the Sabbath, from the day that you brought the sheaf of the wave offering: seven Sabbaths shall be completed. 16 The next day after the seventh Sabbath you shall count fifty days; and you shall offer a new meal offering to Yahweh. 17 You shall bring out of your habitations two loaves of bread for a wave offering made of two tenths of an ephah[‡] of fine flour. They shall be baked with yeast, for first fruits to Yahweh. 18 You shall present with the bread seven lambs without defect a year old, one young bull, and two rams. They shall be a burnt offering to Yahweh, with their meal offering and their drink offerings, even an offering made by fire, of a sweet aroma to Yahweh. 19 You shall offer one male goat for a sin offering, and two male lambs a year old for a sacrifice of peace offerings. 20 The priest shall wave them with the bread of the first fruits for a wave offering before Yahweh, with the two lambs. They shall be holy to Yahweh for the priest. 21 You shall make proclamation on the same day that there shall be a holy convocation to you. You shall do no regular work. This is a statute forever in all your dwellings throughout your generations.

22 “ ‘When you reap the harvest of your land, you must not wholly reap into the corners of your field. You must not gather the gleanings of your harvest. You must leave them for the poor and for the foreigner. I am Yahweh your God.’ ”

23 Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, 24 “Speak to the children of Israel, saying, ‘In the seventh month, on the first day of the month, there shall be a solemn rest for you, a memorial of blowing of trumpets, a holy convocation. 25 You shall do no regular work. You shall offer an offering made by fire to Yahweh.’ ”

26 Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, 27 “However on the tenth day of this seventh month is the day of atonement. It shall be a holy convocation to you. You shall afflict yourselves and you shall offer an offering made by fire to Yahweh. 28 You shall do no kind of work in that same day, for it is a day of atonement, to make atonement for you before Yahweh your God. 29 For whoever it is who shall not deny himself in that same day shall be cut off from his people. 30 Whoever does any kind of work in that same day, I will destroy that person from among his people. 31 You shall do no kind of work: it is a statute forever throughout your generations in all your dwellings. 32 It shall be a Sabbath of solemn rest for you, and you shall deny yourselves. In the ninth day of the month at evening, from evening to evening, you shall keep your Sabbath.”

33 Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, 34 “Speak to the children of Israel, and say, ‘On the fifteenth day of this seventh month is the feast of booths[§] for seven days to Yahweh. 35 On the first day shall be a holy convocation. You shall do no regular work. 36 Seven days you shall offer an offering made by fire to Yahweh. On the eighth day shall be a holy convocation to you. You shall offer an offering made by fire to Yahweh. It is a solemn assembly; you shall do no regular work.

37 “ ‘These are the appointed feasts of Yahweh which you shall proclaim to be holy convocations, to offer an offering made by fire to Yahweh, a burnt offering, a meal offering, a sacrifice, and drink offerings, each on its own day— 38 in addition to the Sabbaths of Yahweh, and in addition to your gifts, and in addition to all your vows, and in addition to all your free will offerings, which you give to Yahweh.

39 “ ‘So on the fifteenth day of the seventh month, when you have gathered in the fruits of the land, you shall keep the feast of Yahweh seven days. On the first day shall be a solemn rest, and on the eighth day shall be a solemn rest. 40 You shall take on the first day the fruit of majestic trees, branches of palm trees, and boughs of thick trees, and willows of the brook; and you shall rejoice before Yahweh your God seven days. 41 You shall keep it as a feast to Yahweh seven days in the year. It is a statute forever throughout your generations. You shall keep it in the seventh month. 42 You shall dwell in temporary shelters[*] for seven days. All who are native-born in Israel shall dwell in temporary shelters,[†] 43 that your generations may know that I made the children of Israel to dwell in temporary shelters[‡] when I brought them out of the land of Egypt. I am Yahweh your God.’ ”

44 So Moses declared to the children of Israel the appointed feasts of Yahweh.

24

1 Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, 2 “Command the children of Israel, that they bring to you pure olive oil beaten for the light, to cause a lamp to burn continually. 3 Outside of the veil of the Testimony, in the Tent of Meeting, Aaron shall keep it in order from evening to morning before Yahweh continually. It shall be a statute forever throughout your generations. 4 He shall keep in order the lamps on the pure gold lamp stand before Yahweh continually.

5 “You shall take fine flour, and bake twelve cakes of it: two tenths of an ephah[*] shall be in one cake. 6 You shall set them in two rows, six on a row, on the pure gold table before Yahweh. 7 You shall put pure frankincense on each row, that it may be to the bread for a memorial, even an offering made by fire to Yahweh. 8 Every Sabbath day he shall set it in order before Yahweh continually. It is an everlasting covenant on the behalf of the children of Israel. 9 It shall be for Aaron and his sons. They shall eat it in a holy place; for it is most holy to him of the offerings of Yahweh made by fire by a perpetual statute.”

10 The son of an Israelite woman, whose father was an Egyptian, went out among the children of Israel; and the son of the Israelite woman and a man of Israel strove together in the camp. 11 The son of the Israelite woman blasphemed the Name, and cursed; and they brought him to Moses. His mother’s name was Shelomith, the daughter of Dibri, of the tribe of Dan. 12 They put him in custody until Yahweh’s will should be declared to them. 13 Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, 14 “Bring him who cursed out of the camp; and let all who heard him lay their hands on his head, and let all the congregation stone him. 15 You shall speak to the children of Israel, saying, ‘Whoever curses his God shall bear his sin. 16 He who blasphemes Yahweh’s name, he shall surely be put to death. All the congregation shall certainly stone him. The foreigner as well as the native-born shall be put to death when he blasphemes the Name.

17 “ ‘He who strikes any man mortally shall surely be put to death. 18 He who strikes an animal mortally shall make it good, life for life. 19 If anyone injures his neighbor, it shall be done to him as he has done: 20 fracture for fracture, eye for eye, tooth for tooth. It shall be done to him as he has injured someone. 21 He who kills an animal shall make it good; and he who kills a man shall be put to death. 22 You shall have one kind of law for the foreigner as well as the native-born; for I am Yahweh your God.’ ”

23 Moses spoke to the children of Israel; and they brought him who had cursed out of the camp, and stoned him with stones. The children of Israel did as Yahweh commanded Moses.

25

1 Yahweh said to Moses on Mount Sinai, 2 “Speak to the children of Israel, and tell them, ‘When you come into the land which I give you, then the land shall keep a Sabbath to Yahweh. 3 You shall sow your field six years, and you shall prune your vineyard six years, and gather in its fruits; 4 but in the seventh year there shall be a Sabbath of solemn rest for the land, a Sabbath to Yahweh. You shall not sow your field or prune your vineyard. 5 What grows of itself in your harvest you shall not reap, and you shall not gather the grapes of your undressed vine. It shall be a year of solemn rest for the land. 6 The Sabbath of the land shall be for food for you; for yourself, for your servant, for your maid, for your hired servant, and for your stranger, who lives as a foreigner with you. 7 For your livestock also, and for the animals that are in your land, shall all its increase be for food.

8 “ ‘You shall count off seven Sabbaths of years, seven times seven years; and there shall be to you the days of seven Sabbaths of years, even forty-nine years. 9 Then you shall sound the loud trumpet on the tenth day of the seventh month. On the Day of Atonement you shall sound the trumpet throughout all your land. 10 You shall make the fiftieth year holy, and proclaim liberty throughout the land to all its inhabitants. It shall be a jubilee to you; and each of you shall return to his own property, and each of you shall return to his family. 11 That fiftieth year shall be a jubilee to you. In it you shall not sow, neither reap that which grows of itself, nor gather from the undressed vines. 12 For it is a jubilee; it shall be holy to you. You shall eat of its increase out of the field.

13 “ ‘In this Year of Jubilee each of you shall return to his property.

14 “ ‘If you sell anything to your neighbor, or buy from your neighbor, you shall not wrong one another. 15 According to the number of years after the Jubilee you shall buy from your neighbor. According to the number of years of the crops he shall sell to you. 16 According to the length of the years you shall increase its price, and according to the shortness of the years you shall diminish its price; for he is selling the number of the crops to you. 17 You shall not wrong one another, but you shall fear your God; for I am Yahweh your God.

18 “ ‘Therefore you shall do my statutes, and keep my ordinances and do them; and you shall dwell in the land in safety. 19 The land shall yield its fruit, and you shall eat your fill, and dwell therein in safety. 20 If you said, “What shall we eat the seventh year? Behold, we shall not sow, nor gather in our increase;” 21 then I will command my blessing on you in the sixth year, and it shall bear fruit for the three years. 22 You shall sow the eighth year, and eat of the fruits from the old store until the ninth year. Until its fruits come in, you shall eat the old store.

23 “ ‘The land shall not be sold in perpetuity, for the land is mine; for you are strangers and live as foreigners with me. 24 In all the land of your possession you shall grant a redemption for the land.

25 “ ‘If your brother becomes poor, and sells some of his possessions, then his kinsman who is next to him shall come, and redeem that which his brother has sold. 26 If a man has no one to redeem it, and he becomes prosperous and finds sufficient means to redeem it, 27 then let him reckon the years since its sale, and restore the surplus to the man to whom he sold it; and he shall return to his property. 28 But if he isn’t able to get it back for himself, then what he has sold shall remain in the hand of him who has bought it until the Year of Jubilee. In the Jubilee it shall be released, and he shall return to his property.

29 “ ‘If a man sells a dwelling house in a walled city, then he may redeem it within a whole year after it has been sold. For a full year he shall have the right of redemption. 30 If it isn’t redeemed within the space of a full year, then the house that is in the walled city shall be made sure in perpetuity to him who bought it, throughout his generations. It shall not be released in the Jubilee. 31 But the houses of the villages which have no wall around them shall be accounted for with the fields of the country: they may be redeemed, and they shall be released in the Jubilee.

32 “ ‘Nevertheless, in the cities of the Levites, the Levites may redeem the houses in the cities of their possession at any time. 33 The Levites may redeem the house that was sold, and the city of his possession, and it shall be released in the Jubilee; for the houses of the cities of the Levites are their possession among the children of Israel. 34 But the field of the pasture lands of their cities may not be sold, for it is their perpetual possession.

35 “ ‘If your brother has become poor, and his hand can’t support himself among you, then you shall uphold him. He shall live with you like an alien and a temporary resident. 36 Take no interest from him or profit; but fear your God, that your brother may live among you. 37 You shall not lend him your money at interest, nor give him your food for profit. 38 I am Yahweh your God, who brought you out of the land of Egypt, to give you the land of Canaan, and to be your God.

39 “ ‘If your brother has grown poor among you, and sells himself to you, you shall not make him to serve as a slave. 40 As a hired servant, and as a temporary resident, he shall be with you; he shall serve with you until the Year of Jubilee. 41 Then he shall go out from you, he and his children with him, and shall return to his own family, and to the possession of his fathers. 42 For they are my servants, whom I brought out of the land of Egypt. They shall not be sold as slaves. 43 You shall not rule over him with harshness, but shall fear your God.

44 “ ‘As for your male and your female slaves, whom you may have from the nations that are around you, from them you may buy male and female slaves. 45 Moreover, of the children of the aliens who live among you, of them you may buy, and of their families who are with you, which they have conceived in your land; and they will be your property. 46 You may make them an inheritance for your children after you, to hold for a possession. Of them you may take your slaves forever, but over your brothers the children of Israel you shall not rule, one over another, with harshness.

47 “ ‘If an alien or temporary resident with you becomes rich, and your brother beside him has grown poor, and sells himself to the stranger or foreigner living among you, or to a member of the stranger’s family, 48 after he is sold he may be redeemed. One of his brothers may redeem him; 49 or his uncle, or his uncle’s son, may redeem him, or any who is a close relative to him of his family may redeem him; or if he has grown rich, he may redeem himself. 50 He shall reckon with him who bought him from the year that he sold himself to him to the Year of Jubilee. The price of his sale shall be according to the number of years; he shall be with him according to the time of a hired servant. 51 If there are yet many years, according to them he shall give back the price of his redemption out of the money that he was bought for. 52 If there remain but a few years to the year of jubilee, then he shall reckon with him; according to his years of service he shall give back the price of his redemption. 53 As a servant hired year by year shall he be with him. He shall not rule with harshness over him in your sight. 54 If he isn’t redeemed by these means, then he shall be released in the Year of Jubilee: he and his children with him. 55 For to me the children of Israel are servants; they are my servants whom I brought out of the land of Egypt. I am Yahweh your God.

26

1 “ ‘You shall make for yourselves no idols, and you shall not raise up a carved image or a pillar, and you shall not place any figured stone in your land, to bow down to it; for I am Yahweh your God.

2 “ ‘You shall keep my Sabbaths, and have reverence for my sanctuary. I am Yahweh.

3 “ ‘If you walk in my statutes and keep my commandments, and do them, 4 then I will give you your rains in their season, and the land shall yield its increase, and the trees of the field shall yield their fruit. 5 Your threshing shall continue until the vintage, and the vintage shall continue until the sowing time. You shall eat your bread to the full, and dwell in your land safely.

6 “ ‘I will give peace in the land, and you shall lie down, and no one will make you afraid. I will remove evil animals out of the land, neither shall the sword go through your land. 7 You shall chase your enemies, and they shall fall before you by the sword. 8 Five of you shall chase a hundred, and a hundred of you shall chase ten thousand; and your enemies shall fall before you by the sword.

9 “ ‘I will have respect for you, make you fruitful, multiply you, and will establish my covenant with you. 10 You shall eat old supplies long kept, and you shall move out the old because of the new. 11 I will set my tent among you, and my soul won’t abhor you. 12 I will walk among you, and will be your God, and you will be my people. 13 I am Yahweh your God, who brought you out of the land of Egypt, that you should not be their slaves. I have broken the bars of your yoke, and made you walk upright.

14 “ ‘But if you will not listen to me, and will not do all these commandments, 15 and if you shall reject my statutes, and if your soul abhors my ordinances, so that you will not do all my commandments, but break my covenant, 16 I also will do this to you: I will appoint terror over you, even consumption and fever, that shall consume the eyes, and make the soul to pine away. You will sow your seed in vain, for your enemies will eat it. 17 I will set my face against you, and you will be struck before your enemies. Those who hate you will rule over you; and you will flee when no one pursues you.

18 “ ‘If you in spite of these things will not listen to me, then I will chastise you seven times more for your sins. 19 I will break the pride of your power, and I will make your sky like iron, and your soil like bronze. 20 Your strength will be spent in vain; for your land won’t yield its increase, neither will the trees of the land yield their fruit.

21 “ ‘If you walk contrary to me, and won’t listen to me, then I will bring seven times more plagues on you according to your sins. 22 I will send the wild animals among you, which will rob you of your children, destroy your livestock, and make you few in number. Your roads will become desolate.

23 “ ‘If by these things you won’t be turned back to me, but will walk contrary to me, 24 then I will also walk contrary to you; and I will strike you, even I, seven times for your sins. 25 I will bring a sword upon you that will execute the vengeance of the covenant. You will be gathered together within your cities, and I will send the pestilence among you. You will be delivered into the hand of the enemy. 26 When I break your staff of bread, ten women shall bake your bread in one oven, and they shall deliver your bread again by weight. You shall eat, and not be satisfied.

27 “ ‘If you in spite of this won’t listen to me, but walk contrary to me, 28 then I will walk contrary to you in wrath. I will also chastise you seven times for your sins. 29 You will eat the flesh of your sons, and you will eat the flesh of your daughters. 30 I will destroy your high places, and cut down your incense altars, and cast your dead bodies upon the bodies of your idols; and my soul will abhor you. 31 I will lay your cities waste, and will bring your sanctuaries to desolation. I will not take delight in the sweet fragrance of your offerings. 32 I will bring the land into desolation, and your enemies who dwell in it will be astonished at it. 33 I will scatter you among the nations, and I will draw out the sword after you. Your land will be a desolation, and your cities shall be a waste. 34 Then the land will enjoy its Sabbaths as long as it lies desolate and you are in your enemies’ land. Even then the land will rest and enjoy its Sabbaths. 35 As long as it lies desolate it shall have rest, even the rest which it didn’t have in your Sabbaths when you lived on it.

36 “ ‘As for those of you who are left, I will send a faintness into their hearts in the lands of their enemies. The sound of a driven leaf will put them to flight; and they shall flee, as one flees from the sword. They will fall when no one pursues. 37 They will stumble over one another, as it were before the sword, when no one pursues. You will have no power to stand before your enemies. 38 You will perish among the nations. The land of your enemies will eat you up. 39 Those of you who are left will pine away in their iniquity in your enemies’ lands; and also in the iniquities of their fathers they shall pine away with them.

40 “ ‘If they confess their iniquity and the iniquity of their fathers, in their trespass which they trespassed against me; and also that because they walked contrary to me, 41 I also walked contrary to them, and brought them into the land of their enemies; if then their uncircumcised heart is humbled, and they then accept the punishment of their iniquity, 42 then I will remember my covenant with Jacob, my covenant with Isaac, and also my covenant with Abraham; and I will remember the land. 43 The land also will be left by them, and will enjoy its Sabbaths while it lies desolate without them; and they will accept the punishment of their iniquity because they rejected my ordinances, and their soul abhorred my statutes. 44 Yet for all that, when they are in the land of their enemies, I will not reject them, neither will I abhor them, to destroy them utterly and to break my covenant with them; for I am Yahweh their God. 45 But I will for their sake remember the covenant of their ancestors, whom I brought out of the land of Egypt in the sight of the nations, that I might be their God. I am Yahweh.’ ”

46 These are the statutes, ordinances, and laws, which Yahweh made between him and the children of Israel in Mount Sinai by Moses.

27

1 Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, 2 “Speak to the children of Israel, and say to them, ‘When a man consecrates a person to Yahweh in a vow, according to your valuation, 3 your valuation of a male from twenty years old to sixty years old shall be fifty shekels of silver, according to the shekel[*] of the sanctuary. 4 If she is a female, then your valuation shall be thirty shekels. 5 If the person is from five years old to twenty years old, then your valuation shall be for a male twenty shekels, and for a female ten shekels. 6 If the person is from a month old to five years old, then your valuation shall be for a male five shekels of silver, and for a female your valuation shall be three shekels of silver. 7 If the person is from sixty years old and upward; if he is a male, then your valuation shall be fifteen shekels, and for a female ten shekels. 8 But if he is poorer than your valuation, then he shall be set before the priest, and the priest shall assign a value to him. The priest shall assign a value according to his ability to pay.

9 “ ‘If it is an animal of which men offer an offering to Yahweh, all that any man gives of such to Yahweh becomes holy. 10 He shall not alter it, nor exchange it, a good for a bad, or a bad for a good. If he shall at all exchange animal for animal, then both it and that for which it is exchanged shall be holy. 11 If it is any unclean animal, of which they do not offer as an offering to Yahweh, then he shall set the animal before the priest; 12 and the priest shall evaluate it, whether it is good or bad. As the priest evaluates it, so it shall be. 13 But if he will indeed redeem it, then he shall add the fifth part of it to its valuation.

14 “ ‘When a man dedicates his house to be holy to Yahweh, then the priest shall evaluate it, whether it is good or bad. As the priest evaluates it, so it shall stand. 15 If he who dedicates it will redeem his house, then he shall add the fifth part of the money of your valuation to it, and it shall be his.

16 “ ‘If a man dedicates to Yahweh part of the field of his possession, then your valuation shall be according to the seed for it. The sowing of a homer[†] of barley shall be valued at fifty shekels[‡] of silver. 17 If he dedicates his field from the Year of Jubilee, according to your valuation it shall stand. 18 But if he dedicates his field after the Jubilee, then the priest shall reckon to him the money according to the years that remain to the Year of Jubilee; and an abatement shall be made from your valuation. 19 If he who dedicated the field will indeed redeem it, then he shall add the fifth part of the money of your valuation to it, and it shall remain his. 20 If he will not redeem the field, or if he has sold the field to another man, it shall not be redeemed any more; 21 but the field, when it goes out in the Jubilee, shall be holy to Yahweh, as a devoted field. It shall be owned by the priests.

22 “ ‘If he dedicates a field to Yahweh which he has bought, which is not of the field of his possession, 23 then the priest shall reckon to him the worth of your valuation up to the Year of Jubilee; and he shall give your valuation on that day, as a holy thing to Yahweh. 24 In the Year of Jubilee the field shall return to him from whom it was bought, even to him to whom the possession of the land belongs. 25 All your valuations shall be according to the shekel of the sanctuary: twenty gerahs[§] to the shekel.[*]

26 “ ‘However the firstborn among animals, which belongs to Yahweh as a firstborn, no man may dedicate, whether an ox or a sheep. It is Yahweh’s. 27 If it is an unclean animal, then he shall buy it back according to your valuation, and shall add to it the fifth part of it; or if it isn’t redeemed, then it shall be sold according to your valuation.

28 “ ‘Notwithstanding, no devoted thing that a man devotes to Yahweh of all that he has, whether of man or animal, or of the field of his possession, shall be sold or redeemed. Everything that is permanently devoted is most holy to Yahweh.

29 “ ‘No one devoted to destruction, who shall be devoted from among men, shall be ransomed. He shall surely be put to death.

30 “ ‘All the tithe of the land, whether of the seed of the land or of the fruit of the trees, is Yahweh’s. It is holy to Yahweh. 31 If a man redeems anything of his tithe, he shall add a fifth part to it. 32 All the tithe of the herds or the flocks, whatever passes under the rod, the tenth shall be holy to Yahweh. 33 He shall not examine whether it is good or bad, neither shall he exchange it. If he exchanges it at all, then both it and that for which it is exchanged shall be holy. It shall not be redeemed.’ ”

34 These are the commandments which Yahweh commanded Moses for the children of Israel on Mount Sinai.

* 1:1 “Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

* 2:13 The Hebrew word rendered “God” is “אֱלֹהִ֑ים” (Elohim).

* 5:11 1 ephah is about 22 liters or about 2/3 of a bushel

† 5:15 A shekel is about 10 grams or about 0.35 ounces.

* 6:20 1 ephah is about 22 liters or about 2/3 of a bushel

* 10:16 “Behold”, from “הִנֵּה”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.

* 11:5 or rock badger, or cony

* 13:48 warp and woof are the vertical and horizontal threads in woven cloth

* 14:10 1 ephah is about 22 liters or about 2/3 of a bushel

† 14:10 a log is a liquid measure of about 300 ml or 10 ounces

‡ 14:21 1 ephah is about 22 liters or about 2/3 of a bushel

§ 14:21 a log is a liquid measure of about 300 ml or 10 ounces

* 19:16 literally, “blood”

† 19:23 literally, “uncircumcised”

‡ 19:36 1 ephah is about 22 liters or about 2/3 of a bushel

§ 19:36 A hin is about 6.5 liters or 1.7 gallons.

* 20:2 or, seed

* 23:13 1 ephah is about 22 liters or about 2/3 of a bushel

† 23:13 A hin is about 6.5 liters or 1.7 gallons.

‡ 23:17 1 ephah is about 22 liters or about 2/3 of a bushel

§ 23:34 or, feast of tents, or Succoth

* 23:42 or, booths

† 23:42 or, booths

‡ 23:43 or, booths

* 24:5 1 ephah is about 22 liters or about 2/3 of a bushel

* 27:3 A shekel is about 10 grams or about 0.35 ounces.

† 27:16 1 homer is about 220 liters or 6 bushels

‡ 27:16 A shekel is about 10 grams or about 0.35 ounces.

§ 27:25 A gerah is about 0.5 grams or about 7.7 grains.

* 27:25 A shekel is about 10 grams or about 0.35 ounces.

Malachi

1
2
3
4

The Book of

Malachi

1

1 A revelation, Yahweh’s[*] word to Israel by Malachi.

2 “I have loved you,” says Yahweh.

Yet you say, “How have you loved us?”

“Wasn’t Esau Jacob’s brother?” says Yahweh, “Yet I loved Jacob; 3 but Esau I hated, and made his mountains a desolation, and gave his heritage to the jackals of the wilderness.” 4 Whereas Edom says, “We are beaten down, but we will return and build the waste places,” Yahweh of Armies says, “They shall build, but I will throw down; and men will call them ‘The Wicked Land,’ even the people against whom Yahweh shows wrath forever.”

5 Your eyes will see, and you will say, “Yahweh is great—even beyond the border of Israel!”

6 “A son honors his father, and a servant his master. If I am a father, then where is my honor? And if I am a master, where is the respect due me?” says Yahweh of Armies to you priests who despise my name. “You say, ‘How have we despised your name?’ 7 You offer polluted bread on my altar. You say, ‘How have we polluted you?’ In that you say, ‘Yahweh’s table is contemptible.’ 8 When you offer the blind for sacrifice, isn’t that evil? And when you offer the lame and sick, isn’t that evil? Present it now to your governor! Will he be pleased with you? Or will he accept your person?” says Yahweh of Armies.

9 “Now, please entreat the favor of God,[†] that he may be gracious to us. With this, will he accept any of you?” says Yahweh of Armies.

10 “Oh that there were one among you who would shut the doors, that you might not kindle fire on my altar in vain! I have no pleasure in you,” says Yahweh of Armies, “neither will I accept an offering at your hand. 11 For from the rising of the sun even to its going down, my name is great among the nations, and in every place incense will be offered to my name, and a pure offering; for my name is great among the nations,” says Yahweh of Armies. 12 “But you profane it when you say, ‘Yahweh’s table is polluted, and its fruit, even its food, is contemptible.’ 13 You say also, ‘Behold,[‡] what a weariness it is!’ And you have sniffed at it”, says Yahweh of Armies; “and you have brought that which was taken by violence, the lame, and the sick; thus you bring the offering. Should I accept this at your hand?” says Yahweh.

14 “But the deceiver is cursed who has in his flock a male, and vows and sacrifices to the Lord[§] a defective thing; for I am a great King,” says Yahweh of Armies, “and my name is awesome among the nations.”

2

1 “Now, you priests, this commandment is for you. 2 If you will not listen, and if you will not take it to heart, to give glory to my name,” says Yahweh of Armies, “then I will send the curse on you, and I will curse your blessings. Indeed, I have cursed them already, because you do not take it to heart. 3 Behold, I will rebuke your offspring,[*] and will spread dung on your faces, even the dung of your feasts; and you will be taken away with it. 4 You will know that I have sent this commandment to you, that my covenant may be with Levi,” says Yahweh of Armies. 5 “My covenant was with him of life and peace; and I gave them to him that he might be reverent toward me; and he was reverent toward me, and stood in awe of my name. 6 The law of truth was in his mouth, and unrighteousness was not found in his lips. He walked with me in peace and uprightness, and turned many away from iniquity. 7 For the priest’s lips should keep knowledge, and they should seek the law at his mouth; for he is the messenger of Yahweh of Armies. 8 But you have turned away from the path. You have caused many to stumble in the law. You have corrupted the covenant of Levi,” says Yahweh of Armies. 9 “Therefore I have also made you contemptible and wicked before all the people, according to the way you have not kept my ways, but have had respect for persons in the law. 10 Don’t we all have one father? Hasn’t one God created us? Why do we deal treacherously every man against his brother, profaning the covenant of our fathers? 11 Judah has dealt treacherously, and an abomination is committed in Israel and in Jerusalem; for Judah has profaned the holiness of Yahweh which he loves, and has married the daughter of a foreign god. 12 Yahweh will cut off the man who does this, him who wakes and him who answers, out of the tents of Jacob and him who offers an offering to Yahweh of Armies.

13 “This again you do: you cover Yahweh’s altar with tears, with weeping, and with sighing, because he doesn’t regard the offering any more, neither receives it with good will at your hand. 14 Yet you say, ‘Why?’ Because Yahweh has been witness between you and the wife of your youth, against whom you have dealt treacherously, though she is your companion and the wife of your covenant. 15 Did he not make you one, although he had the residue of the Spirit? Why one? He sought godly offspring. Therefore take heed to your spirit, and let no one deal treacherously against the wife of his youth. 16 One who hates and divorces”, says Yahweh, the God of Israel, “covers his garment with violence!” says Yahweh of Armies. “Therefore pay attention to your spirit, that you don’t be unfaithful.

17 You have wearied Yahweh with your words. Yet you say, ‘How have we wearied him?’ In that you say, ‘Everyone who does evil is good in Yahweh’s sight, and he delights in them;’ or ‘Where is the God of justice?’

3

1 “Behold, I send my messenger, and he will prepare the way before me! The Lord, whom you seek, will suddenly come to his temple. Behold, the messenger of the covenant, whom you desire, is coming!” says Yahweh of Armies. 2 “But who can endure the day of his coming? And who will stand when he appears? For he is like a refiner’s fire, and like launderers’ soap; 3 and he will sit as a refiner and purifier of silver, and he will purify the sons of Levi, and refine them as gold and silver; and they shall offer to Yahweh offerings in righteousness. 4 Then the offering of Judah and Jerusalem will be pleasant to Yahweh as in the days of old and as in ancient years.

5 I will come near to you to judgment. I will be a swift witness against the sorcerers, against the adulterers, against the perjurers, and against those who oppress the hireling in his wages, the widow, and the fatherless, and who deprive the foreigner of justice, and don’t fear me,” says Yahweh of Armies.

6 “For I, Yahweh, don’t change; therefore you, sons of Jacob, are not consumed. 7 From the days of your fathers you have turned away from my ordinances and have not kept them. Return to me, and I will return to you,” says Yahweh of Armies. “But you say, ‘How shall we return?’

8 Will a man rob God? Yet you rob me! But you say, ‘How have we robbed you?’ In tithes and offerings. 9 You are cursed with the curse; for you rob me, even this whole nation. 10 Bring the whole tithe into the storehouse, that there may be food in my house, and test me now in this,” says Yahweh of Armies, “if I will not open you the windows of heaven, and pour you out a blessing, that there will not be enough room for. 11 I will rebuke the devourer for your sakes, and he shall not destroy the fruits of your ground; neither shall your vine cast its fruit before its time in the field,” says Yahweh of Armies. 12 “All nations shall call you blessed, for you will be a delightful land,” says Yahweh of Armies.

13 “Your words have been harsh against me,” says Yahweh. “Yet you say, ‘What have we spoken against you?’ 14 You have said, ‘It is vain to serve God,’ and ‘What profit is it that we have followed his instructions and that we have walked mournfully before Yahweh of Armies? 15 Now we call the proud happy; yes, those who work wickedness are built up; yes, they tempt God, and escape.’

16 Then those who feared Yahweh spoke one with another; and Yahweh listened and heard, and a book of memory was written before him for those who feared Yahweh and who honored his name. 17 They shall be mine,” says Yahweh of Armies, “my own possession in the day that I make. I will spare them, as a man spares his own son who serves him. 18 Then you shall return and discern between the righteous and the wicked, between him who serves God and him who doesn’t serve him.

4

1 “For behold, the day comes, burning like a furnace, when all the proud and all who work wickedness will be stubble. The day that comes will burn them up,” says Yahweh of Armies, “so that it will leave them neither root nor branch. 2 But to you who fear my name shall the sun of righteousness arise with healing in its wings. You will go out and leap like calves of the stall. 3 You shall tread down the wicked; for they will be ashes under the soles of your feet in the day that I make,” says Yahweh of Armies.

4 “Remember the law of Moses my servant, which I commanded to him in Horeb for all Israel, even statutes and ordinances.

5 Behold, I will send you Elijah the prophet before the great and terrible day of Yahweh comes. 6 He will turn the hearts of the fathers to the children and the hearts of the children to their fathers, lest I come and strike the earth with a curse.”

* 1:1 “Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

† 1:9 The Hebrew word rendered “God” is “אֱלֹהִ֑ים” (Elohim).

‡ 1:13 “Behold”, from “הִנֵּה”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.

§ 1:14 The word translated “Lord” is “Adonai.”

* 2:3 or, seed

Prayer of Manasses

THE

PRAYER OF MANASSES

KING OF JUDAH,

WHEN HE WAS HELD CAPTIVE IN BABYLON

The Prayer of Manasses is recognized as Deuterocanonical Scripture by the Greek Orthodox and Russian Orthodox Churches. It is included in an appendix to the Latin Vulgate Bible.

1

1 O LORD Almighty in heaven, God of our fathers Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, and of their righteous offspring, 2 you who have made heaven and earth, with all their order, 3 who have bound the sea by the word of your commandment, who have shut up the deep, and sealed it by your terrible and glorious name, 4 whom all things fear, yes, tremble before your power, 5 for the majesty of your glory can’t be borne, and the anger of your threatening toward sinners is unbearable. 6 Your merciful promise is unmeasurable and unsearchable, 7 for you are the Lord Most High, of great compassion, patient and abundant in mercy, and relent at human suffering. 8  [*]You, O Lord, according to your great goodness have promised repentance and forgiveness to those who have sinned against you. Of your infinite mercies, you have appointed repentance to sinners, that they may be saved. You therefore, O Lord, who are the God of the just, have not appointed repentance to the just, to Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, which have not sinned against you, but you have appointed repentance to me who am a sinner. 9 For I have sinned more than the number of the sands of the sea. My transgressions are multiplied,[†] O Lord, my transgressions are multiplied, and I am not worthy to behold and see the height of heaven for the multitude of my iniquities. 10 I am bowed down with many iron bands, so that I can’t lift up my head[‡]by reason of my sins, neither have I any relief; for I have provoked your wrath, and done that which is evil before you:[§] I didn’t do your will, neither did I keep your commandments. I have set up abominations, and have multiplied detestable things. 11 Now therefore I bow the knee of my heart, asking you for grace. 12 I have sinned, O Lord, I have sinned, and I acknowledge my iniquities; 13 but, I humbly ask you, forgive me, O Lord, forgive me, and please don’t destroy me with my iniquities. Don’t be angry with me forever, by reserving evil for me. Don’t condemn me into the lower parts of the earth. For you, O Lord, are the God of those who repent. 14 In me you will show all your goodness, for you will save me, who am unworthy, according to your great mercy. 15 Then I will praise you forever all the days of my life; for all the army of heaven sings your praise, and yours is the glory forever and ever. Amen.

* 1:8 The Alex. MS. omits You... saved.

† 1:9 The Alex. MS. omits O Lord... multiplied.

‡ 1:10 Some authorities omit by reason of my sins.

§ 1:10 The Alex. MS. omits I did... commandments.

Micah

1
2
3
4
5
6
7

The Book of

Micah

1

1 Yahweh’s[*] word that came to Micah of Morasheth in the days of Jotham, Ahaz, and Hezekiah, kings of Judah, which he saw concerning Samaria and Jerusalem.

2 Hear, you peoples, all of you!

Listen, O earth, and all that is therein.

Let the Lord[†] Yahweh be witness against you,

the Lord from his holy temple.

3 For behold,[‡] Yahweh comes out of his place,

and will come down and tread on the high places of the earth.

4 The mountains melt under him,

and the valleys split apart like wax before the fire,

like waters that are poured down a steep place.

5 “All this is for the disobedience of Jacob,

and for the sins of the house of Israel.

What is the disobedience of Jacob?

Isn’t it Samaria?

And what are the high places of Judah?

Aren’t they Jerusalem?

6 Therefore I will make Samaria like a rubble heap of the field,

like places for planting vineyards;

and I will pour down its stones into the valley,

and I will uncover its foundations.

7 All her idols will be beaten to pieces,

all her temple gifts will be burned with fire,

and I will destroy all her images;

for of the hire of a prostitute has she gathered them,

and to the hire of a prostitute shall they return.”

8 For this I will lament and wail.

I will go stripped and naked.

I will howl like the jackals

and mourn like the ostriches.

9 For her wounds are incurable;

for it has come even to Judah.

It reaches to the gate of my people,

even to Jerusalem.

10 Don’t tell it in Gath.

Don’t weep at all.

At Beth Ophrah[§] I have rolled myself in the dust.

11 Pass on, inhabitant of Shaphir, in nakedness and shame.

The inhabitant of Zaanan won’t come out.

The wailing of Beth Ezel will take from you his protection.

12 For the inhabitant of Maroth waits anxiously for good,

because evil has come down from Yahweh to the gate of Jerusalem.

13 Harness the chariot to the swift steed, inhabitant of Lachish.

She was the beginning of sin to the daughter of Zion;

For the transgressions of Israel were found in you.

14 Therefore you will give a parting gift to Moresheth Gath.

The houses of Achzib will be a deceitful thing to the kings of Israel.

15 I will yet bring a conqueror to you, inhabitants of Mareshah.

The glory of Israel will come to Adullam.

16 Shave your heads,

and cut off your hair for the children of your delight.

Enlarge your baldness like the vulture,

for they have gone into captivity from you!

2

1 Woe to those who devise iniquity

and work evil on their beds!

When the morning is light, they practice it,

because it is in the power of their hand.

2 They covet fields and seize them,

and houses, then take them away.

They oppress a man and his house,

even a man and his heritage.

3 Therefore Yahweh says:

“Behold, I am planning against these people a disaster,

from which you will not remove your necks,

neither will you walk haughtily,

for it is an evil time.

4 In that day they will take up a parable against you,

and lament with a doleful lamentation, saying,

‘We are utterly ruined!

My people’s possession is divided up.

Indeed he takes it from me and assigns our fields to traitors!’ ”

5 Therefore you will have no one who divides the land by lot in Yahweh’s assembly.

6 “Don’t prophesy!”—they prophesy—

“Don’t prophesy about these things.

Disgrace won’t overtake us.”

7 Shall it be said, O house of Jacob,

“Is Yahweh’s Spirit angry?

Are these his doings?

Don’t my words do good to him who walks blamelessly?”

8 But lately my people have risen up as an enemy.

You strip the robe and clothing from those who pass by without a care, returning from battle.

9 You drive the women of my people out from their pleasant houses;

from their young children you take away my blessing forever.

10 Arise, and depart!

For this is not your resting place,

because of uncleanness that destroys,

even with a grievous destruction.

11 If a man walking in a spirit of falsehood lies, saying,

“I will prophesy to you of wine and of strong drink,”

he would be the prophet of this people.

12 I will surely assemble all of you, Jacob.

I will surely gather the remnant of Israel.

I will put them together as the sheep of Bozrah,

as a flock in the middle of their pasture.

They will swarm with people.

13 He who breaks open the way goes up before them.

They break through the gate, and go out.

Their king passes on before them,

with Yahweh at their head.

3

1 I said,

“Please listen, you heads of Jacob,

and rulers of the house of Israel:

Isn’t it for you to know justice?

2 You who hate the good,

and love the evil;

who tear off their skin,

and their flesh from off their bones;

3 who also eat the flesh of my people,

and peel their skin from off them,

and break their bones,

and chop them in pieces, as for the pot,

and as meat within the cauldron.

4 Then they will cry to Yahweh,

but he will not answer them.

Yes, he will hide his face from them at that time,

because they made their deeds evil.”

5 Yahweh says concerning the prophets who lead my people astray—for those who feed their teeth, they proclaim, “Peace!” and whoever doesn’t provide for their mouths, they prepare war against him:

6 “Therefore night is over you, with no vision,

and it is dark to you, that you may not divine;

and the sun will go down on the prophets,

and the day will be black over them.

7 The seers shall be disappointed,

and the diviners confounded.

Yes, they shall all cover their lips,

for there is no answer from God.”[*]

8 But as for me, I am full of power by Yahweh’s Spirit,

and of judgment, and of might,

to declare to Jacob his disobedience,

and to Israel his sin.

9 Please listen to this, you heads of the house of Jacob,

and rulers of the house of Israel,

who abhor justice,

and pervert all equity,

10 who build up Zion with blood,

and Jerusalem with iniquity.

11 Her leaders judge for bribes,

and her priests teach for a price,

and her prophets of it tell fortunes for money;

yet they lean on Yahweh, and say,

“Isn’t Yahweh among us?

No disaster will come on us.”

12 Therefore Zion for your sake will be plowed like a field,

and Jerusalem will become heaps of rubble,

and the mountain of the temple like the high places of a forest.

4

1 But in the latter days,

it will happen that the mountain of Yahweh’s temple will be established on the top of the mountains,

and it will be exalted above the hills;

and peoples will stream to it.

2 Many nations will go and say,

“Come! Let’s go up to the mountain of Yahweh,

and to the house of the God of Jacob;

and he will teach us of his ways,

and we will walk in his paths.”

For the law will go out of Zion,

and Yahweh’s word from Jerusalem;

3 and he will judge between many peoples,

and will decide concerning strong nations afar off.

They will beat their swords into plowshares,

and their spears into pruning hooks.

Nation will not lift up sword against nation,

neither will they learn war any more.

4 But every man will sit under his vine and under his fig tree.

No one will make them afraid,

for the mouth of Yahweh of Armies has spoken. 5 Indeed all the nations may walk in the name of their gods,

but we will walk in the name of Yahweh our God forever and ever.

6 “In that day,” says Yahweh,

“I will assemble that which is lame,

and I will gather that which is driven away,

and that which I have afflicted;

7 and I will make that which was lame a remnant,

and that which was cast far off a strong nation:

and Yahweh will reign over them on Mount Zion from then on, even forever.”

8 You, tower of the flock, the hill of the daughter of Zion,

to you it will come.

Yes, the former dominion will come,

the kingdom of the daughter of Jerusalem.

9 Now why do you cry out aloud?

Is there no king in you?

Has your counselor perished,

that pains have taken hold of you as of a woman in travail?

10 Be in pain, and labor to give birth, daughter of Zion,

like a woman in travail;

for now you will go out of the city,

and will dwell in the field,

and will come even to Babylon.

There you will be rescued.

There Yahweh will redeem you from the hand of your enemies.

11 Now many nations have assembled against you, that say,

“Let her be defiled,

and let our eye gloat over Zion.”

12 But they don’t know the thoughts of Yahweh,

neither do they understand his counsel;

for he has gathered them like the sheaves to the threshing floor.

13 Arise and thresh, daughter of Zion,

for I will make your horn iron,

and I will make your hoofs bronze.

You will beat in pieces many peoples.

I will devote their gain to Yahweh,

and their substance to the Lord of the whole earth.

5

1 Now you shall gather yourself in troops,

daughter of troops.

He has laid siege against us.

They will strike the judge of Israel with a rod on the cheek.

2 But you, Bethlehem Ephrathah,

being small among the clans of Judah,

out of you one will come out to me who is to be ruler in Israel;

whose goings out are from of old, from ancient times.

3 Therefore he will abandon them until the time that she who is in labor gives birth.

Then the rest of his brothers will return to the children of Israel.

4 He shall stand, and shall shepherd in the strength of Yahweh,

in the majesty of the name of Yahweh his God.

They will live, for then he will be great to the ends of the earth.

5 He will be our peace when Assyria invades our land

and when he marches through our fortresses,

then we will raise against him seven shepherds,

and eight leaders of men.

6 They will rule the land of Assyria with the sword,

and the land of Nimrod in its gates.

He will deliver us from the Assyrian,

when he invades our land,

and when he marches within our border.

7 The remnant of Jacob will be among many peoples

like dew from Yahweh,

like showers on the grass,

that don’t wait for man

nor wait for the sons of men.

8 The remnant of Jacob will be among the nations,

among many peoples,

like a lion among the animals of the forest,

like a young lion among the flocks of sheep;

who, if he goes through, treads down and tears in pieces,

and there is no one to deliver.

9 Let your hand be lifted up above your adversaries,

and let all of your enemies be cut off.

10 “It will happen in that day”, says Yahweh,

“that I will cut off your horses from among you

and will destroy your chariots.

11 I will cut off the cities of your land

and will tear down all your strongholds.

12 I will destroy witchcraft from your hand.

You shall have no soothsayers.

13 I will cut off your engraved images and your pillars from among you;

and you shall no more worship the work of your hands.

14 I will uproot your Asherah poles from among you;

and I will destroy your cities.

15 I will execute vengeance in anger

and wrath on the nations that didn’t listen.”

6

1 Listen now to what Yahweh says:

“Arise, plead your case before the mountains,

and let the hills hear what you have to say.

2 Hear, you mountains, Yahweh’s indictment,

and you enduring foundations of the earth;

for Yahweh has a case against his people,

and he will contend with Israel.

3 My people, what have I done to you?

How have I burdened you?

Answer me!

4 For I brought you up out of the land of Egypt,

and redeemed you out of the house of bondage.

I sent before you Moses, Aaron, and Miriam.

5 My people, remember now what Balak king of Moab devised,

and what Balaam the son of Beor answered him from Shittim to Gilgal,

that you may know the righteous acts of Yahweh.”

6 How shall I come before Yahweh,

and bow myself before the exalted God?

Shall I come before him with burnt offerings,

with calves a year old?

7 Will Yahweh be pleased with thousands of rams?

With tens of thousands of rivers of oil?

Shall I give my firstborn for my disobedience?

The fruit of my body for the sin of my soul?

8 He has shown you, O man, what is good.

What does Yahweh require of you, but to act justly,

to love mercy, and to walk humbly with your God?

9 Yahweh’s voice calls to the city—

and wisdom fears your name—

“Listen to the rod,

and he who appointed it.

10 Are there yet treasures of wickedness in the house of the wicked,

and a short ephah[*] that is accursed?

11 Shall I tolerate dishonest scales,

and a bag of deceitful weights?

12 Her rich men are full of violence,

her inhabitants speak lies,

and their tongue is deceitful in their speech.

13 Therefore I also have struck you with a grievous wound.

I have made you desolate because of your sins.

14 You shall eat, but not be satisfied.

Your hunger will be within you.

You will store up, but not save,

and that which you save I will give up to the sword.

15 You will sow, but won’t reap.

You will tread the olives, but won’t anoint yourself with oil;

and crush grapes, but won’t drink the wine.

16 For the statutes of Omri are kept,

and all the works of Ahab’s house.

You walk in their counsels,

that I may make you a ruin,

and your inhabitants a hissing.

You will bear the reproach of my people.”

7

1 Misery is mine!

Indeed, I am like one who gathers the summer fruits, as gleanings of the vineyard.

There is no cluster of grapes to eat.

My soul desires to eat the early fig.

2 The godly man has perished out of the earth,

and there is no one upright among men.

They all lie in wait for blood;

every man hunts his brother with a net.

3 Their hands are on that which is evil to do it diligently.

The ruler and judge ask for a bribe.

The powerful man dictates the evil desire of his soul.

Thus they conspire together.

4 The best of them is like a brier.

The most upright is worse than a thorn hedge.

The day of your watchmen,

even your visitation, has come;

now is the time of their confusion.

5 Don’t trust in a neighbor.

Don’t put confidence in a friend.

With the woman lying in your embrace,

be careful of the words of your mouth!

6 For the son dishonors the father,

the daughter rises up against her mother,

the daughter-in-law against her mother-in-law;

a man’s enemies are the men of his own house.

7 But as for me, I will look to Yahweh.

I will wait for the God of my salvation.

My God will hear me.

8 Don’t rejoice against me, my enemy.

When I fall, I will arise.

When I sit in darkness, Yahweh will be a light to me.

9 I will bear the indignation of Yahweh,

because I have sinned against him,

until he pleads my case and executes judgment for me.

He will bring me out to the light.

I will see his righteousness.

10 Then my enemy will see it,

and shame will cover her who said to me,

“Where is Yahweh your God?”

My eyes will see her.

Now she will be trodden down like the mire of the streets.

11 A day to build your walls!

In that day, he will extend your boundary.

12 In that day they will come to you from Assyria and the cities of Egypt,

and from Egypt even to the River,

and from sea to sea,

and mountain to mountain.

13 Yet the land will be desolate because of those who dwell therein,

for the fruit of their doings.

14 Shepherd your people with your staff,

the flock of your heritage,

who dwell by themselves in a forest.

Let them feed in the middle of fertile pasture land,

in Bashan and Gilead, as in the days of old.

15 “As in the days of your coming out of the land of Egypt,

I will show them marvelous things.”

16 The nations will see and be ashamed of all their might.

They will lay their hand on their mouth.

Their ears will be deaf.

17 They will lick the dust like a serpent.

Like crawling things of the earth, they will come trembling out of their dens.

They will come with fear to Yahweh our God,

and will be afraid because of you.

18 Who is a God like you, who pardons iniquity,

and passes over the disobedience of the remnant of his heritage?

He doesn’t retain his anger forever,

because he delights in loving kindness.

19 He will again have compassion on us.

He will tread our iniquities under foot.

You will cast all their sins into the depths of the sea.

20 You will give truth to Jacob,

and mercy to Abraham,

as you have sworn to our fathers from the days of old.

* 1:1 “Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

† 1:2 The word translated “Lord” is “Adonai.”

‡ 1:3 “Behold”, from “הִנֵּה”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.

§ 1:10 Beth Ophrah means literally “House of Dust.”

* 3:7 The Hebrew word rendered “God” is “אֱלֹהִ֑ים” (Elohim).

* 6:10 An ephah is a measure of volume (about 22 liters or about 2/3 of a bushel), and a short ephah is made smaller than a full ephah for the purpose of cheating customers.

Philippians

1
2
3
4

Paul’s Letter to the Philippians

1

1 Paul and Timothy, servants of Jesus Christ,[*] to all the saints in Christ Jesus who are at Philippi, with the overseers[†] and servants:[‡] 2 Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.

3 I thank my God whenever I remember you, 4 always in every request of mine on behalf of you all, making my requests with joy, 5 for your partnership[§] in furtherance of the Good News from the first day until now; 6 being confident of this very thing, that he who began a good work in you will complete it until the day of Jesus Christ. 7 It is even right for me to think this way on behalf of all of you, because I have you in my heart, because both in my bonds and in the defense and confirmation of the Good News, you all are partakers with me of grace. 8 For God is my witness, how I long after all of you in the tender mercies of Christ Jesus.

9 This I pray, that your love may abound yet more and more in knowledge and all discernment, 10 so that you may approve the things that are excellent, that you may be sincere and without offense to the day of Christ, 11 being filled with the fruits of righteousness which are through Jesus Christ, to the glory and praise of God.

12 Now I desire to have you know, brothers,[*] that the things which happened to me have turned out rather to the progress of the Good News, 13 so that it became evident to the whole palace[†] guard, and to all the rest, that my bonds are in Christ, 14 and that most of the brothers in the Lord, being confident through my bonds, are more abundantly bold to speak the word of God without fear. 15 Some indeed preach Christ even out of envy and strife, and some also out of good will. 16 The former insincerely preach Christ from selfish ambition, thinking that they add affliction to my chains; 17 but the latter out of love, knowing that I am appointed for the defense of the Good News.

18 What does it matter? Only that in every way, whether in pretense or in truth, Christ is proclaimed. I rejoice in this, yes, and will rejoice. 19 For I know that this will turn out to my salvation through your prayers and the supply of the Spirit of Jesus Christ, 20 according to my earnest expectation and hope, that I will in no way be disappointed, but with all boldness, as always, now also Christ will be magnified in my body, whether by life or by death. 21 For to me to live is Christ, and to die is gain. 22 But if I live on in the flesh, this will bring fruit from my work; yet I don’t know what I will choose. 23 But I am hard pressed between the two, having the desire to depart and be with Christ, which is far better. 24 Yet to remain in the flesh is more needful for your sake. 25 Having this confidence, I know that I will remain, yes, and remain with you all for your progress and joy in the faith, 26 that your boasting[‡] may abound in Christ Jesus in me through my presence with you again.

27 Only let your way of life be worthy of the Good News of Christ, that whether I come and see you or am absent, I may hear of your state, that you stand firm in one spirit, with one soul striving for the faith of the Good News; 28 and in nothing frightened by the adversaries, which is for them a proof of destruction, but to you of salvation, and that from God. 29 Because it has been granted to you on behalf of Christ, not only to believe in him, but also to suffer on his behalf, 30 having the same conflict which you saw in me and now hear is in me.

2

1 If therefore there is any exhortation in Christ, if any consolation of love, if any fellowship of the Spirit, if any tender mercies and compassion, 2 make my joy full by being like-minded, having the same love, being of one accord, of one mind; 3 doing nothing through rivalry or through conceit, but in humility, each counting others better than himself; 4 each of you not just looking to his own things, but each of you also to the things of others.

5 Have this in your mind, which was also in Christ Jesus, 6 who, existing in the form of God, didn’t consider equality with God a thing to be grasped, 7 but emptied himself, taking the form of a servant, being made in the likeness of men. 8 And being found in human form, he humbled himself, becoming obedient to the point of death, yes, the death of the cross. 9 Therefore God also highly exalted him, and gave to him the name which is above every name, 10 that at the name of Jesus every knee should bow, of those in heaven, those on earth, and those under the earth, 11 and that every tongue should confess that Jesus Christ is Lord, to the glory of God the Father.

12 So then, my beloved, even as you have always obeyed, not only in my presence, but now much more in my absence, work out your own salvation with fear and trembling. 13 For it is God who works in you both to will and to work for his good pleasure.

14 Do all things without complaining and arguing, 15 that you may become blameless and harmless, children of God without defect in the middle of a crooked and perverse generation, among whom you are seen as lights in the world, 16 holding up the word of life, that I may have something to boast in the day of Christ that I didn’t run in vain nor labor in vain. 17 Yes, and if I am poured out on the sacrifice and service of your faith, I am glad and rejoice with you all. 18 In the same way, you also should be glad and rejoice with me.

19 But I hope in the Lord Jesus to send Timothy to you soon, that I also may be cheered up when I know how you are doing. 20 For I have no one else like-minded, who will truly care about you. 21 For they all seek their own, not the things of Jesus Christ. 22 But you know that he has proved himself. As a child serves a father, so he served with me in furtherance of the Good News. 23 Therefore I hope to send him at once, as soon as I see how it will go with me. 24 But I trust in the Lord that I myself also will come shortly.

25 But I thought it necessary to send to you Epaphroditus, my brother, fellow worker, fellow soldier, and your apostle and servant of my need, 26 since he longed for you all, and was very troubled because you had heard that he was sick. 27 For indeed he was sick nearly to death, but God had mercy on him, and not on him only, but on me also, that I might not have sorrow on sorrow. 28 I have sent him therefore the more diligently, that when you see him again, you may rejoice, and that I may be the less sorrowful. 29 Receive him therefore in the Lord with all joy, and hold such people in honor, 30 because for the work of Christ he came near to death, risking his life to supply that which was lacking in your service toward me.

3

1 Finally, my brothers, rejoice in the Lord! To write the same things to you, to me indeed is not tiresome, but for you it is safe.

2 Beware of the dogs; beware of the evil workers; beware of the false circumcision. 3 For we are the circumcision, who worship God in the Spirit, and rejoice in Christ Jesus, and have no confidence in the flesh; 4 though I myself might have confidence even in the flesh. If any other man thinks that he has confidence in the flesh, I yet more: 5 circumcised the eighth day, of the stock of Israel, of the tribe of Benjamin, a Hebrew of Hebrews; concerning the law, a Pharisee; 6 concerning zeal, persecuting the assembly; concerning the righteousness which is in the law, found blameless.

7 However, I consider those things that were gain to me as a loss for Christ. 8 Yes most certainly, and I count all things to be a loss for the excellency of the knowledge of Christ Jesus, my Lord, for whom I suffered the loss of all things, and count them nothing but refuse, that I may gain Christ 9 and be found in him, not having a righteousness of my own, that which is of the law, but that which is through faith in Christ, the righteousness which is from God by faith, 10 that I may know him and the power of his resurrection, and the fellowship of his sufferings, becoming conformed to his death, 11 if by any means I may attain to the resurrection from the dead. 12 Not that I have already obtained, or am already made perfect; but I press on, that I may take hold of that for which also I was taken hold of by Christ Jesus.

13 Brothers, I don’t regard myself as yet having taken hold, but one thing I do: forgetting the things which are behind and stretching forward to the things which are before, 14 I press on toward the goal for the prize of the high calling of God in Christ Jesus. 15 Let us therefore, as many as are perfect, think this way. If in anything you think otherwise, God will also reveal that to you. 16 Nevertheless, to the extent that we have already attained, let’s walk by the same rule. Let’s be of the same mind.

17 Brothers, be imitators together of me, and note those who walk this way, even as you have us for an example. 18 For many walk, of whom I told you often, and now tell you even weeping, as the enemies of the cross of Christ, 19 whose end is destruction, whose god is the belly, and whose glory is in their shame, who think about earthly things. 20 For our citizenship is in heaven, from where we also wait for a Savior, the Lord Jesus Christ, 21 who will change the body of our humiliation to be conformed to the body of his glory, according to the working by which he is able even to subject all things to himself.

4

1 Therefore, my brothers, beloved and longed for, my joy and crown, stand firm in the Lord in this way, my beloved.

2 I exhort Euodia, and I exhort Syntyche, to think the same way in the Lord. 3 Yes, I beg you also, true partner, help these women, for they labored with me in the Good News with Clement also, and the rest of my fellow workers, whose names are in the book of life.

4 Rejoice in the Lord always! Again I will say, “Rejoice!” 5 Let your gentleness be known to all men. The Lord is at hand. 6 In nothing be anxious, but in everything, by prayer and petition with thanksgiving, let your requests be made known to God. 7 And the peace of God, which surpasses all understanding, will guard your hearts and your thoughts in Christ Jesus.

8 Finally, brothers, whatever things are true, whatever things are honorable, whatever things are just, whatever things are pure, whatever things are lovely, whatever things are of good report: if there is any virtue and if there is anything worthy of praise, think about these things. 9 Do the things which you learned, received, heard, and saw in me, and the God of peace will be with you.

10 But I rejoice in the Lord greatly that now at length you have revived your thought for me; in which you did indeed take thought, but you lacked opportunity. 11 Not that I speak because of lack, for I have learned in whatever state I am, to be content in it. 12 I know how to be humbled, and I also know how to abound. In any and all circumstances I have learned the secret both to be filled and to be hungry, both to abound and to be in need. 13 I can do all things through Christ who strengthens me. 14 However you did well that you shared in my affliction. 15 You yourselves also know, you Philippians, that in the beginning of the Good News, when I departed from Macedonia, no assembly shared with me in the matter of giving and receiving but you only. 16 For even in Thessalonica you sent once and again to my need. 17 Not that I seek for the gift, but I seek for the fruit that increases to your account. 18 But I have all things and abound. I am filled, having received from Epaphroditus the things that came from you, a sweet-smelling fragrance, an acceptable and well-pleasing sacrifice to God. 19 My God will supply every need of yours according to his riches in glory in Christ Jesus. 20 Now to our God and Father be the glory forever and ever! Amen.

21 Greet every saint in Christ Jesus. The brothers who are with me greet you. 22 All the saints greet you, especially those who are of Caesar’s household.

23 The grace of the Lord Jesus Christ be with you all. Amen.

* 1:1 “Christ” means “Anointed One”.

† 1:1 or, superintendents, or bishops

‡ 1:1 Or, deacons

§ 1:5 The word translated “partnership” (κοινωνίᾳ) also means “fellowship” and “sharing”.

* 1:12 The word for “brothers” here and where context allows may also be correctly translated “brothers and sisters” or “siblings.”

† 1:13 or, praetorian

‡ 1:26 or, rejoicing

Proverbs

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10

11
12
13
14
15
16
17
18
19
20

21
22
23
24
25
26
27
28
29
30

31

The Proverbs

1

1 The proverbs of Solomon, the son of David, king of Israel:

2 to know wisdom and instruction;

to discern the words of understanding;

3 to receive instruction in wise dealing,

in righteousness, justice, and equity;

4 to give prudence to the simple,

knowledge and discretion to the young man—

5 that the wise man may hear, and increase in learning;

that the man of understanding may attain to sound counsel;

6 to understand a proverb and parables,

the words and riddles of the wise.

7 The fear of Yahweh[*] is the beginning of knowledge,

but the foolish despise wisdom and instruction.

8 My son, listen to your father’s instruction,

and don’t forsake your mother’s teaching;

9 for they will be a garland to grace your head,

and chains around your neck.

10 My son, if sinners entice you,

don’t consent.

11 If they say, “Come with us.

Let’s lie in wait for blood.

Let’s lurk secretly for the innocent without cause.

12 Let’s swallow them up alive like Sheol,[†]

and whole, like those who go down into the pit.

13 We’ll find all valuable wealth.

We’ll fill our houses with plunder.

14 You shall cast your lot among us.

We’ll all have one purse”—

15 my son, don’t walk on the path with them.

Keep your foot from their path,

16 for their feet run to evil.

They hurry to shed blood.

17 For the net is spread in vain in the sight of any bird;

18 but these lay in wait for their own blood.

They lurk secretly for their own lives.

19 So are the ways of everyone who is greedy for gain.

It takes away the life of its owners.

20 Wisdom calls aloud in the street.

She utters her voice in the public squares.

21 She calls at the head of noisy places.

At the entrance of the city gates, she utters her words:

22 “How long, you simple ones, will you love simplicity?

How long will mockers delight themselves in mockery,

and fools hate knowledge?

23 Turn at my reproof.

Behold,[‡] I will pour out my spirit on you.

I will make known my words to you.

24 Because I have called, and you have refused;

I have stretched out my hand, and no one has paid attention;

25 but you have ignored all my counsel,

and wanted none of my reproof;

26 I also will laugh at your disaster.

I will mock when calamity overtakes you,

27 when calamity overtakes you like a storm,

when your disaster comes on like a whirlwind,

when distress and anguish come on you.

28 Then they will call on me, but I will not answer.

They will seek me diligently, but they will not find me,

29 because they hated knowledge,

and didn’t choose the fear of Yahweh.

30 They wanted none of my counsel.

They despised all my reproof.

31 Therefore they will eat of the fruit of their own way,

and be filled with their own schemes.

32 For the backsliding of the simple will kill them.

The careless ease of fools will destroy them.

33 But whoever listens to me will dwell securely,

and will be at ease, without fear of harm.”

2

1 My son, if you will receive my words,

and store up my commandments within you,

2 so as to turn your ear to wisdom,

and apply your heart to understanding;

3 yes, if you call out for discernment,

and lift up your voice for understanding;

4 if you seek her as silver,

and search for her as for hidden treasures;

5 then you will understand the fear of Yahweh,

and find the knowledge of God.[*]

6 For Yahweh gives wisdom.

Out of his mouth comes knowledge and understanding.

7 He lays up sound wisdom for the upright.

He is a shield to those who walk in integrity,

8 that he may guard the paths of justice,

and preserve the way of his saints.

9 Then you will understand righteousness and justice,

equity and every good path.

10 For wisdom will enter into your heart.

Knowledge will be pleasant to your soul.

11 Discretion will watch over you.

Understanding will keep you,

12 to deliver you from the way of evil,

from the men who speak perverse things,

13 who forsake the paths of uprightness,

to walk in the ways of darkness,

14 who rejoice to do evil,

and delight in the perverseness of evil,

15 who are crooked in their ways,

and wayward in their paths,

16 to deliver you from the strange woman,

even from the foreigner who flatters with her words,

17 who forsakes the friend of her youth,

and forgets the covenant of her God;

18 for her house leads down to death,

her paths to the departed spirits.

19 None who go to her return again,

neither do they attain to the paths of life.

20 Therefore walk in the way of good men,

and keep the paths of the righteous.

21 For the upright will dwell in the land.

The perfect will remain in it.

22 But the wicked will be cut off from the land.

The treacherous will be rooted out of it.

3

1 My son, don’t forget my teaching,

but let your heart keep my commandments,

2 for they will add to you length of days,

years of life, and peace.

3 Don’t let kindness and truth forsake you.

Bind them around your neck.

Write them on the tablet of your heart.

4 So you will find favor,

and good understanding in the sight of God and man.

5 Trust in Yahweh with all your heart,

and don’t lean on your own understanding.

6 In all your ways acknowledge him,

and he will make your paths straight.

7 Don’t be wise in your own eyes.

Fear Yahweh, and depart from evil.

8 It will be health to your body,

and nourishment to your bones.

9 Honor Yahweh with your substance,

with the first fruits of all your increase;

10 so your barns will be filled with plenty,

and your vats will overflow with new wine.

11 My son, don’t despise Yahweh’s discipline,

neither be weary of his correction;

12 for whom Yahweh loves, he corrects,

even as a father reproves the son in whom he delights.

13 Happy is the man who finds wisdom,

the man who gets understanding.

14 For her good profit is better than getting silver,

and her return is better than fine gold.

15 She is more precious than rubies.

None of the things you can desire are to be compared to her.

16 Length of days is in her right hand.

In her left hand are riches and honor.

17 Her ways are ways of pleasantness.

All her paths are peace.

18 She is a tree of life to those who lay hold of her.

Happy is everyone who retains her.

19 By wisdom Yahweh founded the earth.

By understanding, he established the heavens.

20 By his knowledge, the depths were broken up,

and the skies drop down the dew.

21 My son, let them not depart from your eyes.

Keep sound wisdom and discretion,

22 so they will be life to your soul,

and grace for your neck.

23 Then you shall walk in your way securely.

Your foot won’t stumble.

24 When you lie down, you will not be afraid.

Yes, you will lie down, and your sleep will be sweet.

25 Don’t be afraid of sudden fear,

neither of the desolation of the wicked, when it comes;

26 for Yahweh will be your confidence,

and will keep your foot from being taken.

27 Don’t withhold good from those to whom it is due,

when it is in the power of your hand to do it.

28 Don’t say to your neighbor, “Go, and come again;

tomorrow I will give it to you,”

when you have it by you.

29 Don’t devise evil against your neighbor,

since he dwells securely by you.

30 Don’t strive with a man without cause,

if he has done you no harm.

31 Don’t envy the man of violence.

Choose none of his ways.

32 For the perverse is an abomination to Yahweh,

but his friendship is with the upright.

33 Yahweh’s curse is in the house of the wicked,

but he blesses the habitation of the righteous.

34 Surely he mocks the mockers,

but he gives grace to the humble.

35 The wise will inherit glory,

but shame will be the promotion of fools.

4

1 Listen, sons, to a father’s instruction.

Pay attention and know understanding;

2 for I give you sound learning.

Don’t forsake my law.

3 For I was a son to my father,

tender and an only child in the sight of my mother.

4 He taught me, and said to me:

“Let your heart retain my words.

Keep my commandments, and live.

5 Get wisdom.

Get understanding.

Don’t forget, and don’t deviate from the words of my mouth.

6 Don’t forsake her, and she will preserve you.

Love her, and she will keep you.

7 Wisdom is supreme.

Get wisdom.

Yes, though it costs all your possessions, get understanding.

8 Esteem her, and she will exalt you.

She will bring you to honor when you embrace her.

9 She will give to your head a garland of grace.

She will deliver a crown of splendor to you.”

10 Listen, my son, and receive my sayings.

The years of your life will be many.

11 I have taught you in the way of wisdom.

I have led you in straight paths.

12 When you go, your steps will not be hampered.

When you run, you will not stumble.

13 Take firm hold of instruction.

Don’t let her go.

Keep her, for she is your life.

14 Don’t enter into the path of the wicked.

Don’t walk in the way of evil men.

15 Avoid it, and don’t pass by it.

Turn from it, and pass on.

16 For they don’t sleep unless they do evil.

Their sleep is taken away, unless they make someone fall.

17 For they eat the bread of wickedness

and drink the wine of violence.

18 But the path of the righteous is like the dawning light

that shines more and more until the perfect day.

19 The way of the wicked is like darkness.

They don’t know what they stumble over.

20 My son, attend to my words.

Turn your ear to my sayings.

21 Let them not depart from your eyes.

Keep them in the center of your heart.

22 For they are life to those who find them,

and health to their whole body.

23 Keep your heart with all diligence,

for out of it is the wellspring of life.

24 Put away from yourself a perverse mouth.

Put corrupt lips far from you.

25 Let your eyes look straight ahead.

Fix your gaze directly before you.

26 Make the path of your feet level.

Let all of your ways be established.

27 Don’t turn to the right hand nor to the left.

Remove your foot from evil.

5

1 My son, pay attention to my wisdom.

Turn your ear to my understanding,

2 that you may maintain discretion,

that your lips may preserve knowledge.

3 For the lips of an adulteress drip honey.

Her mouth is smoother than oil,

4 but in the end she is as bitter as wormwood,

and as sharp as a two-edged sword.

5 Her feet go down to death.

Her steps lead straight to Sheol.[*]

6 She gives no thought to the way of life.

Her ways are crooked, and she doesn’t know it.

7 Now therefore, my sons, listen to me.

Don’t depart from the words of my mouth.

8 Remove your way far from her.

Don’t come near the door of her house,

9 lest you give your honor to others,

and your years to the cruel one;

10 lest strangers feast on your wealth,

and your labors enrich another man’s house.

11 You will groan at your latter end,

when your flesh and your body are consumed,

12 and say, “How I have hated instruction,

and my heart despised reproof.

13 I haven’t obeyed the voice of my teachers,

nor turned my ear to those who instructed me!

14 I have come to the brink of utter ruin,

among the gathered assembly.”

15 Drink water out of your own cistern,

running water out of your own well.

16 Should your springs overflow in the streets,

streams of water in the public squares?

17 Let them be for yourself alone,

not for strangers with you.

18 Let your spring be blessed.

Rejoice in the wife of your youth.

19 A loving doe and a graceful deer—

let her breasts satisfy you at all times.

Be captivated always with her love.

20 For why should you, my son, be captivated with an adulteress?

Why embrace the bosom of another?

21 For the ways of man are before Yahweh’s eyes.

He examines all his paths.

22 The evil deeds of the wicked ensnare him.

The cords of his sin hold him firmly.

23 He will die for lack of instruction.

In the greatness of his folly, he will go astray.

6

1 My son, if you have become collateral for your neighbor,

if you have struck your hands in pledge for a stranger,

2 you are trapped by the words of your mouth;

you are ensnared with the words of your mouth.

3 Do this now, my son, and deliver yourself,

since you have come into the hand of your neighbor.

Go, humble yourself.

Press your plea with your neighbor.

4 Give no sleep to your eyes,

nor slumber to your eyelids.

5 Free yourself, like a gazelle from the hand of the hunter,

like a bird from the snare of the fowler.

6 Go to the ant, you sluggard.

Consider her ways, and be wise;

7 which having no chief, overseer, or ruler,

8 provides her bread in the summer,

and gathers her food in the harvest.

9 How long will you sleep, sluggard?

When will you arise out of your sleep?

10 A little sleep, a little slumber,

a little folding of the hands to sleep—

11 so your poverty will come as a robber,

and your scarcity as an armed man.

12 A worthless person, a man of iniquity,

is he who walks with a perverse mouth,

13 who winks with his eyes, who signals with his feet,

who motions with his fingers,

14 in whose heart is perverseness,

who devises evil continually,

who always sows discord.

15 Therefore his calamity will come suddenly.

He will be broken suddenly, and that without remedy.

16 There are six things which Yahweh hates;

yes, seven which are an abomination to him:

17 arrogant eyes, a lying tongue,

hands that shed innocent blood,

18 a heart that devises wicked schemes,

feet that are swift in running to mischief,

19 a false witness who utters lies,

and he who sows discord among brothers.

20 My son, keep your father’s commandment,

and don’t forsake your mother’s teaching.

21 Bind them continually on your heart.

Tie them around your neck.

22 When you walk, it will lead you.

When you sleep, it will watch over you.

When you awake, it will talk with you.

23 For the commandment is a lamp,

and the law is light.

Reproofs of instruction are the way of life,

24 to keep you from the immoral woman,

from the flattery of the wayward wife’s tongue.

25 Don’t lust after her beauty in your heart,

neither let her captivate you with her eyelids.

26 For a prostitute reduces you to a piece of bread.

The adulteress hunts for your precious life.

27 Can a man scoop fire into his lap,

and his clothes not be burned?

28 Or can one walk on hot coals,

and his feet not be scorched?

29 So is he who goes in to his neighbor’s wife.

Whoever touches her will not be unpunished.

30 Men don’t despise a thief

if he steals to satisfy himself when he is hungry,

31 but if he is found, he shall restore seven times.

He shall give all the wealth of his house.

32 He who commits adultery with a woman is void of understanding.

He who does it destroys his own soul.

33 He will get wounds and dishonor.

His reproach will not be wiped away.

34 For jealousy arouses the fury of the husband.

He won’t spare in the day of vengeance.

35 He won’t regard any ransom,

neither will he rest content, though you give many gifts.

7

1 My son, keep my words.

Lay up my commandments within you.

2 Keep my commandments and live!

Guard my teaching as the apple of your eye.

3 Bind them on your fingers.

Write them on the tablet of your heart.

4 Tell wisdom, “You are my sister.”

Call understanding your relative,

5 that they may keep you from the strange woman,

from the foreigner who flatters with her words.

6 For at the window of my house,

I looked out through my lattice.

7 I saw among the simple ones.

I discerned among the youths a young man void of understanding,

8 passing through the street near her corner,

he went the way to her house,

9 in the twilight, in the evening of the day,

in the middle of the night and in the darkness.

10 Behold, there a woman met him with the attire of a prostitute,

and with crafty intent.

11 She is loud and defiant.

Her feet don’t stay in her house.

12 Now she is in the streets, now in the squares,

and lurking at every corner.

13 So she caught him, and kissed him.

With an impudent face she said to him:

14 “Sacrifices of peace offerings are with me.

Today I have paid my vows.

15 Therefore I came out to meet you,

to diligently seek your face,

and I have found you.

16 I have spread my couch with carpets of tapestry,

with striped cloths of the yarn of Egypt.

17 I have perfumed my bed with myrrh, aloes, and cinnamon.

18 Come, let’s take our fill of loving until the morning.

Let’s solace ourselves with loving.

19 For my husband isn’t at home.

He has gone on a long journey.

20 He has taken a bag of money with him.

He will come home at the full moon.”

21 With persuasive words, she led him astray.

With the flattering of her lips, she seduced him.

22 He followed her immediately,

as an ox goes to the slaughter,

as a fool stepping into a noose.

23 Until an arrow strikes through his liver,

as a bird hurries to the snare,

and doesn’t know that it will cost his life.

24 Now therefore, sons, listen to me.

Pay attention to the words of my mouth.

25 Don’t let your heart turn to her ways.

Don’t go astray in her paths,

26 for she has thrown down many wounded.

Yes, all her slain are a mighty army.

27 Her house is the way to Sheol,[*]

going down to the rooms of death.

8

1 Doesn’t wisdom cry out?

Doesn’t understanding raise her voice?

2 On the top of high places by the way,

where the paths meet, she stands.

3 Beside the gates, at the entry of the city,

at the entry doors, she cries aloud:

4 “I call to you men!

I send my voice to the sons of mankind.

5 You simple, understand prudence!

You fools, be of an understanding heart!

6 Hear, for I will speak excellent things.

The opening of my lips is for right things.

7 For my mouth speaks truth.

Wickedness is an abomination to my lips.

8 All the words of my mouth are in righteousness.

There is nothing crooked or perverse in them.

9 They are all plain to him who understands,

right to those who find knowledge.

10 Receive my instruction rather than silver,

knowledge rather than choice gold.

11 For wisdom is better than rubies.

All the things that may be desired can’t be compared to it.

12 “I, wisdom, have made prudence my dwelling.

Find out knowledge and discretion.

13 The fear of Yahweh is to hate evil.

I hate pride, arrogance, the evil way, and the perverse mouth.

14 Counsel and sound knowledge are mine.

I have understanding and power.

15 By me kings reign,

and princes decree justice.

16 By me princes rule,

nobles, and all the righteous rulers of the earth.

17 I love those who love me.

Those who seek me diligently will find me.

18 With me are riches, honor,

enduring wealth, and prosperity.

19 My fruit is better than gold, yes, than fine gold,

my yield than choice silver.

20 I walk in the way of righteousness,

in the middle of the paths of justice,

21 that I may give wealth to those who love me.

I fill their treasuries.

22 “Yahweh possessed me in the beginning of his work,

before his deeds of old.

23 I was set up from everlasting, from the beginning,

before the earth existed.

24 When there were no depths, I was born,

when there were no springs abounding with water.

25 Before the mountains were settled in place,

before the hills, I was born;

26 while as yet he had not made the earth, nor the fields,

nor the beginning of the dust of the world.

27 When he established the heavens, I was there.

When he set a circle on the surface of the deep,

28 when he established the clouds above,

when the springs of the deep became strong,

29 when he gave to the sea its boundary,

that the waters should not violate his commandment,

when he marked out the foundations of the earth,

30 then I was the craftsman by his side.

I was a delight day by day,

always rejoicing before him,

31 rejoicing in his whole world.

My delight was with the sons of men.

32 “Now therefore, my sons, listen to me,

for blessed are those who keep my ways.

33 Hear instruction, and be wise.

Don’t refuse it.

34 Blessed is the man who hears me,

watching daily at my gates,

waiting at my door posts.

35 For whoever finds me finds life,

and will obtain favor from Yahweh.

36 But he who sins against me wrongs his own soul.

All those who hate me love death.”

9

1 Wisdom has built her house.

She has carved out her seven pillars.

2 She has prepared her meat.

She has mixed her wine.

She has also set her table.

3 She has sent out her maidens.

She cries from the highest places of the city:

4 “Whoever is simple, let him turn in here!”

As for him who is void of understanding, she says to him,

5 “Come, eat some of my bread,

Drink some of the wine which I have mixed!

6 Leave your simple ways, and live.

Walk in the way of understanding.”

7 One who corrects a mocker invites insult.

One who reproves a wicked man invites abuse.

8 Don’t reprove a scoffer, lest he hate you.

Reprove a wise person, and he will love you.

9 Instruct a wise person, and he will be still wiser.

Teach a righteous person, and he will increase in learning.

10 The fear of Yahweh is the beginning of wisdom.

The knowledge of the Holy One is understanding.

11 For by me your days will be multiplied.

The years of your life will be increased.

12 If you are wise, you are wise for yourself.

If you mock, you alone will bear it.

13 The foolish woman is loud,

undisciplined, and knows nothing.

14 She sits at the door of her house,

on a seat in the high places of the city,

15 to call to those who pass by,

who go straight on their ways,

16 “Whoever is simple, let him turn in here.”

As for him who is void of understanding, she says to him,

17 “Stolen water is sweet.

Food eaten in secret is pleasant.”

18 But he doesn’t know that the departed spirits are there,

that her guests are in the depths of Sheol.[*]

10

1 The proverbs of Solomon.

A wise son makes a glad father;

but a foolish son brings grief to his mother.

2 Treasures of wickedness profit nothing,

but righteousness delivers from death.

3 Yahweh will not allow the soul of the righteous to go hungry,

but he thrusts away the desire of the wicked.

4 He becomes poor who works with a lazy hand,

but the hand of the diligent brings wealth.

5 He who gathers in summer is a wise son,

but he who sleeps during the harvest is a son who causes shame.

6 Blessings are on the head of the righteous,

but violence covers the mouth of the wicked.

7 The memory of the righteous is blessed,

but the name of the wicked will rot.

8 The wise in heart accept commandments,

but a chattering fool will fall.

9 He who walks blamelessly walks surely,

but he who perverts his ways will be found out.

10 One who winks with the eye causes sorrow,

but a chattering fool will fall.

11 The mouth of the righteous is a spring of life,

but violence covers the mouth of the wicked.

12 Hatred stirs up strife,

but love covers all wrongs.

13 Wisdom is found on the lips of him who has discernment,

but a rod is for the back of him who is void of understanding.

14 Wise men lay up knowledge,

but the mouth of the foolish is near ruin.

15 The rich man’s wealth is his strong city.

The destruction of the poor is their poverty.

16 The labor of the righteous leads to life.

The increase of the wicked leads to sin.

17 He is in the way of life who heeds correction,

but he who forsakes reproof leads others astray.

18 He who hides hatred has lying lips.

He who utters a slander is a fool.

19 In the multitude of words there is no lack of disobedience,

but he who restrains his lips does wisely.

20 The tongue of the righteous is like choice silver.

The heart of the wicked is of little worth.

21 The lips of the righteous feed many,

but the foolish die for lack of understanding.

22 Yahweh’s blessing brings wealth,

and he adds no trouble to it.

23 It is a fool’s pleasure to do wickedness,

but wisdom is a man of understanding’s pleasure.

24 What the wicked fear will overtake them,

but the desire of the righteous will be granted.

25 When the whirlwind passes, the wicked is no more;

but the righteous stand firm forever.

26 As vinegar to the teeth, and as smoke to the eyes,

so is the sluggard to those who send him.

27 The fear of Yahweh prolongs days,

but the years of the wicked shall be shortened.

28 The prospect of the righteous is joy,

but the hope of the wicked will perish.

29 The way of Yahweh is a stronghold to the upright,

but it is a destruction to the workers of iniquity.

30 The righteous will never be removed,

but the wicked will not dwell in the land.

31 The mouth of the righteous produces wisdom,

but the perverse tongue will be cut off.

32 The lips of the righteous know what is acceptable,

but the mouth of the wicked is perverse.

11

1 A false balance is an abomination to Yahweh,

but accurate weights are his delight.

2 When pride comes, then comes shame,

but with humility comes wisdom.

3 The integrity of the upright shall guide them,

but the perverseness of the treacherous shall destroy them.

4 Riches don’t profit in the day of wrath,

but righteousness delivers from death.

5 The righteousness of the blameless will direct his way,

but the wicked shall fall by his own wickedness.

6 The righteousness of the upright shall deliver them,

but the unfaithful will be trapped by evil desires.

7 When a wicked man dies, hope perishes,

and expectation of power comes to nothing.

8 A righteous person is delivered out of trouble,

and the wicked takes his place.

9 With his mouth the godless man destroys his neighbor,

but the righteous will be delivered through knowledge.

10 When it goes well with the righteous, the city rejoices.

When the wicked perish, there is shouting.

11 By the blessing of the upright, the city is exalted,

but it is overthrown by the mouth of the wicked.

12 One who despises his neighbor is void of wisdom,

but a man of understanding holds his peace.

13 One who brings gossip betrays a confidence,

but one who is of a trustworthy spirit is one who keeps a secret.

14 Where there is no wise guidance, the nation falls,

but in the multitude of counselors there is victory.

15 He who is collateral for a stranger will suffer for it,

but he who refuses pledges of collateral is secure.

16 A gracious woman obtains honor,

but violent men obtain riches.

17 The merciful man does good to his own soul,

but he who is cruel troubles his own flesh.

18 Wicked people earn deceitful wages,

but one who sows righteousness reaps a sure reward.

19 He who is truly righteous gets life.

He who pursues evil gets death.

20 Those who are perverse in heart are an abomination to Yahweh,

but those whose ways are blameless are his delight.

21 Most certainly, the evil man will not be unpunished,

but the offspring[*] of the righteous will be delivered.

22 Like a gold ring in a pig’s snout,

is a beautiful woman who lacks discretion.

23 The desire of the righteous is only good.

The expectation of the wicked is wrath.

24 There is one who scatters, and increases yet more.

There is one who withholds more than is appropriate, but gains poverty.

25 The liberal soul shall be made fat.

He who waters shall be watered also himself.

26 People curse someone who withholds grain,

but blessing will be on the head of him who sells it.

27 He who diligently seeks good seeks favor,

but he who searches after evil, it shall come to him.

28 He who trusts in his riches will fall,

but the righteous shall flourish as the green leaf.

29 He who troubles his own house shall inherit the wind.

The foolish shall be servant to the wise of heart.

30 The fruit of the righteous is a tree of life.

He who is wise wins souls.

31 Behold, the righteous shall be repaid in the earth,

how much more the wicked and the sinner!

12

1 Whoever loves correction loves knowledge,

but he who hates reproof is stupid.

2 A good man shall obtain favor from Yahweh,

but he will condemn a man of wicked plans.

3 A man shall not be established by wickedness,

but the root of the righteous shall not be moved.

4 A worthy woman is the crown of her husband,

but a disgraceful wife is as rottenness in his bones.

5 The thoughts of the righteous are just,

but the advice of the wicked is deceitful.

6 The words of the wicked are about lying in wait for blood,

but the speech of the upright rescues them.

7 The wicked are overthrown, and are no more,

but the house of the righteous shall stand.

8 A man shall be commended according to his wisdom,

but he who has a warped mind shall be despised.

9 Better is he who is little known, and has a servant,

than he who honors himself and lacks bread.

10 A righteous man respects the life of his animal,

but the tender mercies of the wicked are cruel.

11 He who tills his land shall have plenty of bread,

but he who chases fantasies is void of understanding.

12 The wicked desires the plunder of evil men,

but the root of the righteous flourishes.

13 An evil man is trapped by sinfulness of lips,

but the righteous shall come out of trouble.

14 A man shall be satisfied with good by the fruit of his mouth.

The work of a man’s hands shall be rewarded to him.

15 The way of a fool is right in his own eyes,

but he who is wise listens to counsel.

16 A fool shows his annoyance the same day,

but one who overlooks an insult is prudent.

17 He who is truthful testifies honestly,

but a false witness lies.

18 There is one who speaks rashly like the piercing of a sword,

but the tongue of the wise heals.

19 Truth’s lips will be established forever,

but a lying tongue is only momentary.

20 Deceit is in the heart of those who plot evil,

but joy comes to the promoters of peace.

21 No mischief shall happen to the righteous,

but the wicked shall be filled with evil.

22 Lying lips are an abomination to Yahweh,

but those who do the truth are his delight.

23 A prudent man keeps his knowledge,

but the hearts of fools proclaim foolishness.

24 The hands of the diligent ones shall rule,

but laziness ends in slave labor.

25 Anxiety in a man’s heart weighs it down,

but a kind word makes it glad.

26 A righteous person is cautious in friendship,

but the way of the wicked leads them astray.

27 The slothful man doesn’t roast his game,

but the possessions of diligent men are prized.

28 In the way of righteousness is life;

in its path there is no death.

13

1 A wise son listens to his father’s instruction,

but a scoffer doesn’t listen to rebuke.

2 By the fruit of his lips, a man enjoys good things,

but the unfaithful crave violence.

3 He who guards his mouth guards his soul.

One who opens wide his lips comes to ruin.

4 The soul of the sluggard desires, and has nothing,

but the desire of the diligent shall be fully satisfied.

5 A righteous man hates lies,

but a wicked man brings shame and disgrace.

6 Righteousness guards the way of integrity,

but wickedness overthrows the sinner.

7 There are some who pretend to be rich, yet have nothing.

There are some who pretend to be poor, yet have great wealth.

8 The ransom of a man’s life is his riches,

but the poor hear no threats.

9 The light of the righteous shines brightly,

but the lamp of the wicked is snuffed out.

10 Pride only breeds quarrels,

but wisdom is with people who take advice.

11 Wealth gained dishonestly dwindles away,

but he who gathers by hand makes it grow.

12 Hope deferred makes the heart sick,

but when longing is fulfilled, it is a tree of life.

13 Whoever despises instruction will pay for it,

but he who respects a command will be rewarded.

14 The teaching of the wise is a spring of life,

to turn from the snares of death.

15 Good understanding wins favor,

but the way of the unfaithful is hard.

16 Every prudent man acts from knowledge,

but a fool exposes folly.

17 A wicked messenger falls into trouble,

but a trustworthy envoy gains healing.

18 Poverty and shame come to him who refuses discipline,

but he who heeds correction shall be honored.

19 Longing fulfilled is sweet to the soul,

but fools detest turning from evil.

20 One who walks with wise men grows wise,

but a companion of fools suffers harm.

21 Misfortune pursues sinners,

but prosperity rewards the righteous.

22 A good man leaves an inheritance to his children’s children,

but the wealth of the sinner is stored for the righteous.

23 An abundance of food is in poor people’s fields,

but injustice sweeps it away.

24 One who spares the rod hates his son,

but one who loves him is careful to discipline him.

25 The righteous one eats to the satisfying of his soul,

but the belly of the wicked goes hungry.

14

1 Every wise woman builds her house,

but the foolish one tears it down with her own hands.

2 He who walks in his uprightness fears Yahweh,

but he who is perverse in his ways despises him.

3 The fool’s talk brings a rod to his back,

but the lips of the wise protect them.

4 Where no oxen are, the crib is clean,

but much increase is by the strength of the ox.

5 A truthful witness will not lie,

but a false witness pours out lies.

6 A scoffer seeks wisdom, and doesn’t find it,

but knowledge comes easily to a discerning person.

7 Stay away from a foolish man,

for you won’t find knowledge on his lips.

8 The wisdom of the prudent is to think about his way,

but the folly of fools is deceit.

9 Fools mock at making atonement for sins,

but among the upright there is good will.

10 The heart knows its own bitterness and joy;

he will not share these with a stranger.

11 The house of the wicked will be overthrown,

but the tent of the upright will flourish.

12 There is a way which seems right to a man,

but in the end it leads to death.

13 Even in laughter the heart may be sorrowful,

and mirth may end in heaviness.

14 The unfaithful will be repaid for his own ways;

likewise a good man will be rewarded for his ways.

15 A simple man believes everything,

but the prudent man carefully considers his ways.

16 A wise man fears and shuns evil,

but the fool is hot headed and reckless.

17 He who is quick to become angry will commit folly,

and a crafty man is hated.

18 The simple inherit folly,

but the prudent are crowned with knowledge.

19 The evil bow down before the good,

and the wicked at the gates of the righteous.

20 The poor person is shunned even by his own neighbor,

but the rich person has many friends.

21 He who despises his neighbor sins,

but he who has pity on the poor is blessed.

22 Don’t they go astray who plot evil?

But love and faithfulness belong to those who plan good.

23 In all hard work there is profit,

but the talk of the lips leads only to poverty.

24 The crown of the wise is their riches,

but the folly of fools crowns them with folly.

25 A truthful witness saves souls,

but a false witness is deceitful.

26 In the fear of Yahweh is a secure fortress,

and he will be a refuge for his children.

27 The fear of Yahweh is a fountain of life,

turning people from the snares of death.

28 In the multitude of people is the king’s glory,

but in the lack of people is the destruction of the prince.

29 He who is slow to anger has great understanding,

but he who has a quick temper displays folly.

30 The life of the body is a heart at peace,

but envy rots the bones.

31 He who oppresses the poor shows contempt for his Maker,

but he who is kind to the needy honors him.

32 The wicked is brought down in his calamity,

but in death, the righteous has a refuge.

33 Wisdom rests in the heart of one who has understanding,

and is even made known in the inward part of fools.

34 Righteousness exalts a nation,

but sin is a disgrace to any people.

35 The king’s favor is toward a servant who deals wisely,

but his wrath is toward one who causes shame.

15

1 A gentle answer turns away wrath,

but a harsh word stirs up anger.

2 The tongue of the wise commends knowledge,

but the mouths of fools gush out folly.

3 Yahweh’s eyes are everywhere,

keeping watch on the evil and the good.

4 A gentle tongue is a tree of life,

but deceit in it crushes the spirit.

5 A fool despises his father’s correction,

but he who heeds reproof shows prudence.

6 In the house of the righteous is much treasure,

but the income of the wicked brings trouble.

7 The lips of the wise spread knowledge;

not so with the heart of fools.

8 The sacrifice made by the wicked is an abomination to Yahweh,

but the prayer of the upright is his delight.

9 The way of the wicked is an abomination to Yahweh,

but he loves him who follows after righteousness.

10 There is stern discipline for one who forsakes the way.

Whoever hates reproof shall die.

11 Sheol[*] and Abaddon are before Yahweh—

how much more then the hearts of the children of men!

12 A scoffer doesn’t love to be reproved;

he will not go to the wise.

13 A glad heart makes a cheerful face,

but an aching heart breaks the spirit.

14 The heart of one who has understanding seeks knowledge,

but the mouths of fools feed on folly.

15 All the days of the afflicted are wretched,

but one who has a cheerful heart enjoys a continual feast.

16 Better is little, with the fear of Yahweh,

than great treasure with trouble.

17 Better is a dinner of herbs, where love is,

than a fattened calf with hatred.

18 A wrathful man stirs up contention,

but one who is slow to anger appeases strife.

19 The way of the sluggard is like a thorn patch,

but the path of the upright is a highway.

20 A wise son makes a father glad,

but a foolish man despises his mother.

21 Folly is joy to one who is void of wisdom,

but a man of understanding keeps his way straight.

22 Where there is no counsel, plans fail;

but in a multitude of counselors they are established.

23 Joy comes to a man with the reply of his mouth.

How good is a word at the right time!

24 The path of life leads upward for the wise,

to keep him from going downward to Sheol.[†]

25 Yahweh will uproot the house of the proud,

but he will keep the widow’s borders intact.

26 Yahweh detests the thoughts of the wicked,

but the thoughts of the pure are pleasing.

27 He who is greedy for gain troubles his own house,

but he who hates bribes will live.

28 The heart of the righteous weighs answers,

but the mouth of the wicked gushes out evil.

29 Yahweh is far from the wicked,

but he hears the prayer of the righteous.

30 The light of the eyes rejoices the heart.

Good news gives health to the bones.

31 The ear that listens to reproof lives,

and will be at home among the wise.

32 He who refuses correction despises his own soul,

but he who listens to reproof gets understanding.

33 The fear of Yahweh teaches wisdom.

Before honor is humility.

16

1 The plans of the heart belong to man,

but the answer of the tongue is from Yahweh.

2 All the ways of a man are clean in his own eyes,

but Yahweh weighs the motives.

3 Commit your deeds to Yahweh,

and your plans shall succeed.

4 Yahweh has made everything for its own end—

yes, even the wicked for the day of evil.

5 Everyone who is proud in heart is an abomination to Yahweh;

they shall certainly not be unpunished.

6 By mercy and truth iniquity is atoned for.

By the fear of Yahweh men depart from evil.

7 When a man’s ways please Yahweh,

he makes even his enemies to be at peace with him.

8 Better is a little with righteousness,

than great revenues with injustice.

9 A man’s heart plans his course,

but Yahweh directs his steps.

10 Inspired judgments are on the lips of the king.

He shall not betray his mouth.

11 Honest balances and scales are Yahweh’s;

all the weights in the bag are his work.

12 It is an abomination for kings to do wrong,

for the throne is established by righteousness.

13 Righteous lips are the delight of kings.

They value one who speaks the truth.

14 The king’s wrath is a messenger of death,

but a wise man will pacify it.

15 In the light of the king’s face is life.

His favor is like a cloud of the spring rain.

16 How much better it is to get wisdom than gold!

Yes, to get understanding is to be chosen rather than silver.

17 The highway of the upright is to depart from evil.

He who keeps his way preserves his soul.

18 Pride goes before destruction,

and an arrogant spirit before a fall.

19 It is better to be of a lowly spirit with the poor,

than to divide the plunder with the proud.

20 He who heeds the Word finds prosperity.

Whoever trusts in Yahweh is blessed.

21 The wise in heart shall be called prudent.

Pleasantness of the lips promotes instruction.

22 Understanding is a fountain of life to one who has it,

but the punishment of fools is their folly.

23 The heart of the wise instructs his mouth,

and adds learning to his lips.

24 Pleasant words are a honeycomb,

sweet to the soul, and health to the bones.

25 There is a way which seems right to a man,

but in the end it leads to death.

26 The appetite of the laboring man labors for him,

for his mouth urges him on.

27 A worthless man devises mischief.

His speech is like a scorching fire.

28 A perverse man stirs up strife.

A whisperer separates close friends.

29 A man of violence entices his neighbor,

and leads him in a way that is not good.

30 One who winks his eyes to plot perversities,

one who compresses his lips, is bent on evil.

31 Gray hair is a crown of glory.

It is attained by a life of righteousness.

32 One who is slow to anger is better than the mighty;

one who rules his spirit, than he who takes a city.

33 The lot is cast into the lap,

but its every decision is from Yahweh.

17

1 Better is a dry morsel with quietness,

than a house full of feasting with strife.

2 A servant who deals wisely will rule over a son who causes shame,

and shall have a part in the inheritance among the brothers.

3 The refining pot is for silver, and the furnace for gold,

but Yahweh tests the hearts.

4 An evildoer heeds wicked lips.

A liar gives ear to a mischievous tongue.

5 Whoever mocks the poor reproaches his Maker.

He who is glad at calamity shall not be unpunished.

6 Children’s children are the crown of old men;

the glory of children is their parents.

7 Excellent speech isn’t fitting for a fool,

much less do lying lips fit a prince.

8 A bribe is a precious stone in the eyes of him who gives it;

wherever he turns, he prospers.

9 He who covers an offense promotes love;

but he who repeats a matter separates best friends.

10 A rebuke enters deeper into one who has understanding

than a hundred lashes into a fool.

11 An evil man seeks only rebellion;

therefore a cruel messenger shall be sent against him.

12 Let a bear robbed of her cubs meet a man,

rather than a fool in his folly.

13 Whoever rewards evil for good,

evil shall not depart from his house.

14 The beginning of strife is like breaching a dam,

therefore stop contention before quarreling breaks out.

15 He who justifies the wicked, and he who condemns the righteous,

both of them alike are an abomination to Yahweh.

16 Why is there money in the hand of a fool to buy wisdom,

since he has no understanding?

17 A friend loves at all times;

and a brother is born for adversity.

18 A man void of understanding strikes hands,

and becomes collateral in the presence of his neighbor.

19 He who loves disobedience loves strife.

One who builds a high gate seeks destruction.

20 One who has a perverse heart doesn’t find prosperity,

and one who has a deceitful tongue falls into trouble.

21 He who becomes the father of a fool grieves.

The father of a fool has no joy.

22 A cheerful heart makes good medicine,

but a crushed spirit dries up the bones.

23 A wicked man receives a bribe in secret,

to pervert the ways of justice.

24 Wisdom is before the face of one who has understanding,

but the eyes of a fool wander to the ends of the earth.

25 A foolish son brings grief to his father,

and bitterness to her who bore him.

26 Also to punish the righteous is not good,

nor to flog officials for their integrity.

27 He who spares his words has knowledge.

He who is even tempered is a man of understanding.

28 Even a fool, when he keeps silent, is counted wise.

When he shuts his lips, he is thought to be discerning.

18

1 A man who isolates himself pursues selfishness,

and defies all sound judgment.

2 A fool has no delight in understanding,

but only in revealing his own opinion.

3 When wickedness comes, contempt also comes,

and with shame comes disgrace.

4 The words of a man’s mouth are like deep waters.

The fountain of wisdom is like a flowing brook.

5 To be partial to the faces of the wicked is not good,

nor to deprive the innocent of justice.

6 A fool’s lips come into strife,

and his mouth invites beatings.

7 A fool’s mouth is his destruction,

and his lips are a snare to his soul.

8 The words of a gossip are like dainty morsels:

they go down into a person’s innermost parts.

9 One who is slack in his work

is brother to him who is a master of destruction.

10 Yahweh’s name is a strong tower:

the righteous run to him, and are safe.

11 The rich man’s wealth is his strong city,

like an unscalable wall in his own imagination.

12 Before destruction the heart of man is proud,

but before honor is humility.

13 He who answers before he hears,

that is folly and shame to him.

14 A man’s spirit will sustain him in sickness,

but a crushed spirit, who can bear?

15 The heart of the discerning gets knowledge.

The ear of the wise seeks knowledge.

16 A man’s gift makes room for him,

and brings him before great men.

17 He who pleads his cause first seems right—

until another comes and questions him.

18 The lot settles disputes,

and keeps strong ones apart.

19 A brother offended is more difficult than a fortified city.

Disputes are like the bars of a fortress.

20 A man’s stomach is filled with the fruit of his mouth.

With the harvest of his lips he is satisfied.

21 Death and life are in the power of the tongue;

those who love it will eat its fruit.

22 Whoever finds a wife finds a good thing,

and obtains favor of Yahweh.

23 The poor plead for mercy,

but the rich answer harshly.

24 A man of many companions may be ruined,

but there is a friend who sticks closer than a brother.

19

1 Better is the poor who walks in his integrity

than he who is perverse in his lips and is a fool.

2 It isn’t good to have zeal without knowledge,

nor being hasty with one’s feet and missing the way.

3 The foolishness of man subverts his way;

his heart rages against Yahweh.

4 Wealth adds many friends,

but the poor is separated from his friend.

5 A false witness shall not be unpunished.

He who pours out lies shall not go free.

6 Many will entreat the favor of a ruler,

and everyone is a friend to a man who gives gifts.

7 All the relatives of the poor shun him;

how much more do his friends avoid him!

He pursues them with pleas, but they are gone.

8 He who gets wisdom loves his own soul.

He who keeps understanding shall find good.

9 A false witness shall not be unpunished.

He who utters lies shall perish.

10 Delicate living is not appropriate for a fool,

much less for a servant to have rule over princes.

11 The discretion of a man makes him slow to anger.

It is his glory to overlook an offense.

12 The king’s wrath is like the roaring of a lion,

but his favor is like dew on the grass.

13 A foolish son is the calamity of his father.

A wife’s quarrels are a continual dripping.

14 House and riches are an inheritance from fathers,

but a prudent wife is from Yahweh.

15 Slothfulness casts into a deep sleep.

The idle soul shall suffer hunger.

16 He who keeps the commandment keeps his soul,

but he who is contemptuous in his ways shall die.

17 He who has pity on the poor lends to Yahweh;

he will reward him.

18 Discipline your son, for there is hope;

don’t be a willing party to his death.

19 A hot-tempered man must pay the penalty,

for if you rescue him, you must do it again.

20 Listen to counsel and receive instruction,

that you may be wise in your latter end.

21 There are many plans in a man’s heart,

but Yahweh’s counsel will prevail.

22 That which makes a man to be desired is his kindness.

A poor man is better than a liar.

23 The fear of Yahweh leads to life, then contentment;

he rests and will not be touched by trouble.

24 The sluggard buries his hand in the dish;

he will not so much as bring it to his mouth again.

25 Flog a scoffer, and the simple will learn prudence;

rebuke one who has understanding, and he will gain knowledge.

26 He who robs his father and drives away his mother

is a son who causes shame and brings reproach.

27 If you stop listening to instruction, my son,

you will stray from the words of knowledge.

28 A corrupt witness mocks justice,

and the mouth of the wicked gulps down iniquity.

29 Penalties are prepared for scoffers,

and beatings for the backs of fools.

20

1 Wine is a mocker and beer is a brawler.

Whoever is led astray by them is not wise.

2 The terror of a king is like the roaring of a lion.

He who provokes him to anger forfeits his own life.

3 It is an honor for a man to keep aloof from strife,

but every fool will be quarreling.

4 The sluggard will not plow by reason of the winter;

therefore he shall beg in harvest, and have nothing.

5 Counsel in the heart of man is like deep water,

but a man of understanding will draw it out.

6 Many men claim to be men of unfailing love,

but who can find a faithful man?

7 A righteous man walks in integrity.

Blessed are his children after him.

8 A king who sits on the throne of judgment

scatters away all evil with his eyes.

9 Who can say, “I have made my heart pure.

I am clean and without sin?”

10 Differing weights and differing measures,

both of them alike are an abomination to Yahweh.

11 Even a child makes himself known by his doings,

whether his work is pure, and whether it is right.

12 The hearing ear, and the seeing eye,

Yahweh has made even both of them.

13 Don’t love sleep, lest you come to poverty.

Open your eyes, and you shall be satisfied with bread.

14 “It’s no good, it’s no good,” says the buyer;

but when he is gone his way, then he boasts.

15 There is gold and abundance of rubies,

but the lips of knowledge are a rare jewel.

16 Take the garment of one who puts up collateral for a stranger;

and hold him in pledge for a wayward woman.

17 Fraudulent food is sweet to a man,

but afterwards his mouth is filled with gravel.

18 Plans are established by advice;

by wise guidance you wage war!

19 He who goes about as a tale-bearer reveals secrets;

therefore don’t keep company with him who opens wide his lips.

20 Whoever curses his father or his mother,

his lamp shall be put out in blackness of darkness.

21 An inheritance quickly gained at the beginning

won’t be blessed in the end.

22 Don’t say, “I will pay back evil.”

Wait for Yahweh, and he will save you.

23 Yahweh detests differing weights,

and dishonest scales are not pleasing.

24 A man’s steps are from Yahweh;

how then can man understand his way?

25 It is a snare to a man to make a rash dedication,

then later to consider his vows.

26 A wise king winnows out the wicked,

and drives the threshing wheel over them.

27 The spirit of man is Yahweh’s lamp,

searching all his innermost parts.

28 Love and faithfulness keep the king safe.

His throne is sustained by love.

29 The glory of young men is their strength.

The splendor of old men is their gray hair.

30 Wounding blows cleanse away evil,

and beatings purge the innermost parts.

21

1 The king’s heart is in Yahweh’s hand like the watercourses.

He turns it wherever he desires.

2 Every way of a man is right in his own eyes,

but Yahweh weighs the hearts.

3 To do righteousness and justice

is more acceptable to Yahweh than sacrifice.

4 A high look and a proud heart,

the lamp of the wicked, is sin.

5 The plans of the diligent surely lead to profit;

and everyone who is hasty surely rushes to poverty.

6 Getting treasures by a lying tongue

is a fleeting vapor for those who seek death.

7 The violence of the wicked will drive them away,

because they refuse to do what is right.

8 The way of the guilty is devious,

but the conduct of the innocent is upright.

9 It is better to dwell in the corner of the housetop

than to share a house with a contentious woman.

10 The soul of the wicked desires evil;

his neighbor finds no mercy in his eyes.

11 When the mocker is punished, the simple gains wisdom.

When the wise is instructed, he receives knowledge.

12 The Righteous One considers the house of the wicked,

and brings the wicked to ruin.

13 Whoever stops his ears at the cry of the poor,

he will also cry out, but shall not be heard.

14 A gift in secret pacifies anger,

and a bribe in the cloak, strong wrath.

15 It is joy to the righteous to do justice;

but it is a destruction to the workers of iniquity.

16 The man who wanders out of the way of understanding

shall rest in the assembly of the departed spirits.

17 He who loves pleasure will be a poor man.

He who loves wine and oil won’t be rich.

18 The wicked is a ransom for the righteous,

the treacherous for the upright.

19 It is better to dwell in a desert land,

than with a contentious and fretful woman.

20 There is precious treasure and oil in the dwelling of the wise,

but a foolish man swallows it up.

21 He who follows after righteousness and kindness

finds life, righteousness, and honor.

22 A wise man scales the city of the mighty,

and brings down the strength of its confidence.

23 Whoever guards his mouth and his tongue

keeps his soul from troubles.

24 The proud and arrogant man—“Scoffer” is his name—

he works in the arrogance of pride.

25 The desire of the sluggard kills him,

for his hands refuse to labor.

26 There are those who covet greedily all day long;

but the righteous give and don’t withhold.

27 The sacrifice of the wicked is an abomination—

how much more, when he brings it with a wicked mind!

28 A false witness will perish.

A man who listens speaks to eternity.

29 A wicked man hardens his face;

but as for the upright, he establishes his ways.

30 There is no wisdom nor understanding

nor counsel against Yahweh.

31 The horse is prepared for the day of battle;

but victory is with Yahweh.

22

1 A good name is more desirable than great riches,

and loving favor is better than silver and gold.

2 The rich and the poor have this in common:

Yahweh is the maker of them all.

3 A prudent man sees danger and hides himself;

but the simple pass on, and suffer for it.

4 The result of humility and the fear of Yahweh

is wealth, honor, and life.

5 Thorns and snares are in the path of the wicked;

whoever guards his soul stays from them.

6 Train up a child in the way he should go,

and when he is old he will not depart from it.

7 The rich rule over the poor.

The borrower is servant to the lender.

8 He who sows wickedness reaps trouble,

and the rod of his fury will be destroyed.

9 He who has a generous eye will be blessed,

for he shares his food with the poor.

10 Drive out the mocker, and strife will go out;

yes, quarrels and insults will stop.

11 He who loves purity of heart and speaks gracefully

is the king’s friend.

12 Yahweh’s eyes watch over knowledge,

but he frustrates the words of the unfaithful.

13 The sluggard says, “There is a lion outside!

I will be killed in the streets!”

14 The mouth of an adulteress is a deep pit.

He who is under Yahweh’s wrath will fall into it.

15 Folly is bound up in the heart of a child;

the rod of discipline drives it far from him.

16 Whoever oppresses the poor for his own increase and whoever gives to the rich,

both come to poverty.

17 Turn your ear, and listen to the words of the wise.

Apply your heart to my teaching.

18 For it is a pleasant thing if you keep them within you,

if all of them are ready on your lips.

19  I teach you today, even you,

so that your trust may be in Yahweh.

20 Haven’t I written to you thirty excellent things

of counsel and knowledge,

21 To teach you truth, reliable words,

to give sound answers to the ones who sent you?

22 Don’t exploit the poor because he is poor;

and don’t crush the needy in court;

23 for Yahweh will plead their case,

and plunder the life of those who plunder them.

24 Don’t befriend a hot-tempered man.

Don’t associate with one who harbors anger,

25 lest you learn his ways

and ensnare your soul.

26 Don’t you be one of those who strike hands,

of those who are collateral for debts.

27 If you don’t have means to pay,

why should he take away your bed from under you?

28 Don’t move the ancient boundary stone

which your fathers have set up.

29 Do you see a man skilled in his work?

He will serve kings.

He won’t serve obscure men.

23

1 When you sit to eat with a ruler,

consider diligently what is before you;

2 put a knife to your throat

if you are a man given to appetite.

3 Don’t be desirous of his dainties,

since they are deceitful food.

4 Don’t weary yourself to be rich.

In your wisdom, show restraint.

5 Why do you set your eyes on that which is not?

For it certainly sprouts wings like an eagle and flies in the sky.

6 Don’t eat the food of him who has a stingy eye,

and don’t crave his delicacies,

7 for as he thinks about the cost, so he is.

“Eat and drink!” he says to you,

but his heart is not with you.

8 You will vomit up the morsel which you have eaten

and waste your pleasant words.

9 Don’t speak in the ears of a fool,

for he will despise the wisdom of your words.

10 Don’t move the ancient boundary stone.

Don’t encroach on the fields of the fatherless,

11 for their Defender is strong.

He will plead their case against you.

12 Apply your heart to instruction,

and your ears to the words of knowledge.

13 Don’t withhold correction from a child.

If you punish him with the rod, he will not die.

14 Punish him with the rod,

and save his soul from Sheol.[*]

15 My son, if your heart is wise,

then my heart will be glad, even mine.

16 Yes, my heart will rejoice

when your lips speak what is right.

17 Don’t let your heart envy sinners,

but rather fear Yahweh all day long.

18 Indeed surely there is a future hope,

and your hope will not be cut off.

19 Listen, my son, and be wise,

and keep your heart on the right path!

20 Don’t be among ones drinking too much wine,

or those who gorge themselves on meat;

21 for the drunkard and the glutton shall become poor;

and drowsiness clothes them in rags.

22 Listen to your father who gave you life,

and don’t despise your mother when she is old.

23 Buy the truth, and don’t sell it.

Get wisdom, discipline, and understanding.

24 The father of the righteous has great joy.

Whoever fathers a wise child delights in him.

25 Let your father and your mother be glad!

Let her who bore you rejoice!

26 My son, give me your heart;

and let your eyes keep in my ways.

27 For a prostitute is a deep pit;

and a wayward wife is a narrow well.

28 Yes, she lies in wait like a robber,

and increases the unfaithful among men.

29 Who has woe?

Who has sorrow?

Who has strife?

Who has complaints?

Who has needless bruises?

Who has bloodshot eyes?

30 Those who stay long at the wine;

those who go to seek out mixed wine.

31 Don’t look at the wine when it is red,

when it sparkles in the cup,

when it goes down smoothly.

32 In the end, it bites like a snake,

and poisons like a viper.

33 Your eyes will see strange things,

and your mind will imagine confusing things.

34 Yes, you will be as he who lies down in the middle of the sea,

or as he who lies on top of the rigging:

35 “They hit me, and I was not hurt!

They beat me, and I don’t feel it!

When will I wake up? I can do it again.

I will look for more.”

24

1 Don’t be envious of evil men,

neither desire to be with them;

2 for their hearts plot violence

and their lips talk about mischief.

3 Through wisdom a house is built;

by understanding it is established;

4 by knowledge the rooms are filled

with all rare and beautiful treasure.

5 A wise man has great power.

A knowledgeable man increases strength,

6 for by wise guidance you wage your war,

and victory is in many advisors.

7 Wisdom is too high for a fool.

He doesn’t open his mouth in the gate.

8 One who plots to do evil

will be called a schemer.

9 The schemes of folly are sin.

The mocker is detested by men.

10 If you falter in the time of trouble,

your strength is small.

11 Rescue those who are being led away to death!

Indeed, hold back those who are staggering to the slaughter!

12 If you say, “Behold, we didn’t know this,”

doesn’t he who weighs the hearts consider it?

He who keeps your soul, doesn’t he know it?

Shall he not render to every man according to his work?

13 My son, eat honey, for it is good,

the droppings of the honeycomb, which are sweet to your taste;

14 so you shall know wisdom to be to your soul.

If you have found it, then there will be a reward:

Your hope will not be cut off.

15 Don’t lay in wait, wicked man, against the habitation of the righteous.

Don’t destroy his resting place;

16 for a righteous man falls seven times and rises up again,

but the wicked are overthrown by calamity.

17 Don’t rejoice when your enemy falls.

Don’t let your heart be glad when he is overthrown,

18 lest Yahweh see it, and it displease him,

and he turn away his wrath from him.

19 Don’t fret yourself because of evildoers,

neither be envious of the wicked;

20 for there will be no reward to the evil man.

The lamp of the wicked will be snuffed out.

21 My son, fear Yahweh and the king.

Don’t join those who are rebellious,

22 for their calamity will rise suddenly.

Who knows what destruction may come from them both?

23 These also are sayings of the wise:

To show partiality in judgment is not good.

24 He who says to the wicked, “You are righteous,”

peoples will curse him, and nations will abhor him—

25 but it will go well with those who convict the guilty,

and a rich blessing will come on them.

26 An honest answer

is like a kiss on the lips.

27 Prepare your work outside,

and get your fields ready.

Afterwards, build your house.

28 Don’t be a witness against your neighbor without cause.

Don’t deceive with your lips.

29 Don’t say, “I will do to him as he has done to me;

I will repay the man according to his work.”

30 I went by the field of the sluggard,

by the vineyard of the man void of understanding.

31 Behold, it was all grown over with thorns.

Its surface was covered with nettles,

and its stone wall was broken down.

32 Then I saw, and considered well.

I saw, and received instruction:

33 a little sleep, a little slumber,

a little folding of the hands to sleep,

34 so your poverty will come as a robber

and your want as an armed man.

25

1 These also are proverbs of Solomon, which the men of Hezekiah king of Judah copied out.

2 It is the glory of God to conceal a thing,

but the glory of kings is to search out a matter.

3 As the heavens for height, and the earth for depth,

so the hearts of kings are unsearchable.

4 Take away the dross from the silver,

and material comes out for the refiner.

5 Take away the wicked from the king’s presence,

and his throne will be established in righteousness.

6 Don’t exalt yourself in the presence of the king,

or claim a place among great men;

7 for it is better that it be said to you, “Come up here,”

than that you should be put lower in the presence of the prince,

whom your eyes have seen.

8 Don’t be hasty in bringing charges to court.

What will you do in the end when your neighbor shames you?

9 Debate your case with your neighbor,

and don’t betray the confidence of another,

10 lest one who hears it put you to shame,

and your bad reputation never depart.

11 A word fitly spoken

is like apples of gold in settings of silver.

12 As an earring of gold, and an ornament of fine gold,

so is a wise reprover to an obedient ear.

13 As the cold of snow in the time of harvest,

so is a faithful messenger to those who send him;

for he refreshes the soul of his masters.

14 As clouds and wind without rain,

so is he who boasts of gifts deceptively.

15 By patience a ruler is persuaded.

A soft tongue breaks the bone.

16 Have you found honey?

Eat as much as is sufficient for you,

lest you eat too much, and vomit it.

17 Let your foot be seldom in your neighbor’s house,

lest he be weary of you, and hate you.

18 A man who gives false testimony against his neighbor

is like a club, a sword, or a sharp arrow.

19 Confidence in someone unfaithful in time of trouble

is like a bad tooth or a lame foot.

20 As one who takes away a garment in cold weather,

or vinegar on soda,

so is one who sings songs to a heavy heart.

21 If your enemy is hungry, give him food to eat.

If he is thirsty, give him water to drink;

22 for you will heap coals of fire on his head,

and Yahweh will reward you.

23 The north wind produces rain;

so a backbiting tongue brings an angry face.

24 It is better to dwell in the corner of the housetop

than to share a house with a contentious woman.

25 Like cold water to a thirsty soul,

so is good news from a far country.

26 Like a muddied spring and a polluted well,

so is a righteous man who gives way before the wicked.

27 It is not good to eat much honey,

nor is it honorable to seek one’s own honor.

28 Like a city that is broken down and without walls

is a man whose spirit is without restraint.

26

1 Like snow in summer, and as rain in harvest,

so honor is not fitting for a fool.

2 Like a fluttering sparrow,

like a darting swallow,

so the undeserved curse doesn’t come to rest.

3 A whip is for the horse,

a bridle for the donkey,

and a rod for the back of fools!

4 Don’t answer a fool according to his folly,

lest you also be like him.

5 Answer a fool according to his folly,

lest he be wise in his own eyes.

6 One who sends a message by the hand of a fool

is cutting off feet and drinking violence.

7 Like the legs of the lame that hang loose,

so is a parable in the mouth of fools.

8 As one who binds a stone in a sling,

so is he who gives honor to a fool.

9 Like a thorn bush that goes into the hand of a drunkard,

so is a parable in the mouth of fools.

10 As an archer who wounds all,

so is he who hires a fool

or he who hires those who pass by.

11 As a dog that returns to his vomit,

so is a fool who repeats his folly.

12 Do you see a man wise in his own eyes?

There is more hope for a fool than for him.

13 The sluggard says, “There is a lion in the road!

A fierce lion roams the streets!”

14 As the door turns on its hinges,

so does the sluggard on his bed.

15 The sluggard buries his hand in the dish.

He is too lazy to bring it back to his mouth.

16 The sluggard is wiser in his own eyes

than seven men who answer with discretion.

17 Like one who grabs a dog’s ears

is one who passes by and meddles in a quarrel not his own.

18 Like a madman who shoots torches, arrows, and death,

19 is the man who deceives his neighbor and says, “Am I not joking?”

20 For lack of wood a fire goes out.

Without gossip, a quarrel dies down.

21 As coals are to hot embers,

and wood to fire,

so is a contentious man to kindling strife.

22 The words of a whisperer are as dainty morsels,

they go down into the innermost parts.

23 Like silver dross on an earthen vessel

are the lips of a fervent one with an evil heart.

24 A malicious man disguises himself with his lips,

but he harbors evil in his heart.

25 When his speech is charming, don’t believe him,

for there are seven abominations in his heart.

26 His malice may be concealed by deception,

but his wickedness will be exposed in the assembly.

27 Whoever digs a pit shall fall into it.

Whoever rolls a stone, it will come back on him.

28 A lying tongue hates those it hurts;

and a flattering mouth works ruin.

27

1 Don’t boast about tomorrow;

for you don’t know what a day may bring.

2 Let another man praise you,

and not your own mouth;

a stranger, and not your own lips.

3 A stone is heavy,

and sand is a burden;

but a fool’s provocation is heavier than both.

4 Wrath is cruel,

and anger is overwhelming;

but who is able to stand before jealousy?

5 Better is open rebuke

than hidden love.

6 The wounds of a friend are faithful,

although the kisses of an enemy are profuse.

7 A full soul loathes a honeycomb;

but to a hungry soul, every bitter thing is sweet.

8 As a bird that wanders from her nest,

so is a man who wanders from his home.

9 Perfume and incense bring joy to the heart;

so does earnest counsel from a man’s friend.

10 Don’t forsake your friend and your father’s friend.

Don’t go to your brother’s house in the day of your disaster.

A neighbor who is near is better than a distant brother.

11 Be wise, my son,

and bring joy to my heart,

then I can answer my tormentor.

12 A prudent man sees danger and takes refuge;

but the simple pass on, and suffer for it.

13 Take his garment when he puts up collateral for a stranger.

Hold it for a wayward woman!

14 He who blesses his neighbor with a loud voice early in the morning,

it will be taken as a curse by him.

15 A continual dropping on a rainy day

and a contentious wife are alike:

16 restraining her is like restraining the wind,

or like grasping oil in his right hand.

17 Iron sharpens iron;

so a man sharpens his friend’s countenance.

18 Whoever tends the fig tree shall eat its fruit.

He who looks after his master shall be honored.

19 Like water reflects a face,

so a man’s heart reflects the man.

20 Sheol[*] and Abaddon are never satisfied;

and a man’s eyes are never satisfied.

21 The crucible is for silver,

and the furnace for gold;

but man is refined by his praise.

22 Though you grind a fool in a mortar with a pestle along with grain,

yet his foolishness will not be removed from him.

23 Know well the state of your flocks,

and pay attention to your herds,

24 for riches are not forever,

nor does the crown endure to all generations.

25 The hay is removed, and the new growth appears,

the grasses of the hills are gathered in.

26 The lambs are for your clothing,

and the goats are the price of a field.

27 There will be plenty of goats’ milk for your food,

for your family’s food,

and for the nourishment of your servant girls.

28

1 The wicked flee when no one pursues;

but the righteous are as bold as a lion.

2 In rebellion, a land has many rulers,

but order is maintained by a man of understanding and knowledge.

3 A needy man who oppresses the poor

is like a driving rain which leaves no crops.

4 Those who forsake the law praise the wicked;

but those who keep the law contend with them.

5 Evil men don’t understand justice;

but those who seek Yahweh understand it fully.

6 Better is the poor who walks in his integrity

than he who is perverse in his ways, and he is rich.

7 Whoever keeps the law is a wise son;

but he who is a companion of gluttons shames his father.

8 He who increases his wealth by excessive interest

gathers it for one who has pity on the poor.

9 He who turns away his ear from hearing the law,

even his prayer is an abomination.

10 Whoever causes the upright to go astray in an evil way,

he will fall into his own trap;

but the blameless will inherit good.

11 The rich man is wise in his own eyes;

but the poor who has understanding sees through him.

12 When the righteous triumph, there is great glory;

but when the wicked rise, men hide themselves.

13 He who conceals his sins doesn’t prosper,

but whoever confesses and renounces them finds mercy.

14 Blessed is the man who always fears;

but one who hardens his heart falls into trouble.

15 As a roaring lion or a charging bear,

so is a wicked ruler over helpless people.

16 A tyrannical ruler lacks judgment.

One who hates ill-gotten gain will have long days.

17 A man who is tormented by blood guilt will be a fugitive until death.

No one will support him.

18 Whoever walks blamelessly is kept safe;

but one with perverse ways will fall suddenly.

19 One who works his land will have an abundance of food;

but one who chases fantasies will have his fill of poverty.

20 A faithful man is rich with blessings;

but one who is eager to be rich will not go unpunished.

21 To show partiality is not good,

yet a man will do wrong for a piece of bread.

22 A stingy man hurries after riches,

and doesn’t know that poverty waits for him.

23 One who rebukes a man will afterward find more favor

than one who flatters with the tongue.

24 Whoever robs his father or his mother and says, “It’s not wrong,”

is a partner with a destroyer.

25 One who is greedy stirs up strife;

but one who trusts in Yahweh will prosper.

26 One who trusts in himself is a fool;

but one who walks in wisdom is kept safe.

27 One who gives to the poor has no lack;

but one who closes his eyes will have many curses.

28 When the wicked rise, men hide themselves;

but when they perish, the righteous thrive.

29

1 He who is often rebuked and stiffens his neck

will be destroyed suddenly, with no remedy.

2 When the righteous thrive, the people rejoice;

but when the wicked rule, the people groan.

3 Whoever loves wisdom brings joy to his father;

but a companion of prostitutes squanders his wealth.

4 The king by justice makes the land stable,

but he who takes bribes tears it down.

5 A man who flatters his neighbor

spreads a net for his feet.

6 An evil man is snared by his sin,

but the righteous can sing and be glad.

7 The righteous care about justice for the poor.

The wicked aren’t concerned about knowledge.

8 Mockers stir up a city,

but wise men turn away anger.

9 If a wise man goes to court with a foolish man,

the fool rages or scoffs, and there is no peace.

10 The bloodthirsty hate a man of integrity;

and they seek the life of the upright.

11 A fool vents all of his anger,

but a wise man brings himself under control.

12 If a ruler listens to lies,

all of his officials are wicked.

13 The poor man and the oppressor have this in common:

Yahweh gives sight to the eyes of both.

14 The king who fairly judges the poor,

his throne shall be established forever.

15 The rod of correction gives wisdom,

but a child left to himself causes shame to his mother.

16 When the wicked increase, sin increases;

but the righteous will see their downfall.

17 Correct your son, and he will give you peace;

yes, he will bring delight to your soul.

18 Where there is no revelation, the people cast off restraint;

but one who keeps the law is blessed.

19 A servant can’t be corrected by words.

Though he understands, yet he will not respond.

20 Do you see a man who is hasty in his words?

There is more hope for a fool than for him.

21 He who pampers his servant from youth

will have him become a son in the end.

22 An angry man stirs up strife,

and a wrathful man abounds in sin.

23 A man’s pride brings him low,

but one of lowly spirit gains honor.

24 Whoever is an accomplice of a thief is an enemy of his own soul.

He takes an oath, but dares not testify.

25 The fear of man proves to be a snare,

but whoever puts his trust in Yahweh is kept safe.

26 Many seek the ruler’s favor,

but a man’s justice comes from Yahweh.

27 A dishonest man detests the righteous,

and the upright in their ways detest the wicked.

30

1 The words of Agur the son of Jakeh, the revelation:

the man says to Ithiel,

to Ithiel and Ucal:

2 “Surely I am the most ignorant man,

and don’t have a man’s understanding.

3 I have not learned wisdom,

neither do I have the knowledge of the Holy One.

4 Who has ascended up into heaven, and descended?

Who has gathered the wind in his fists?

Who has bound the waters in his garment?

Who has established all the ends of the earth?

What is his name, and what is his son’s name, if you know?

5 “Every word of God is flawless.

He is a shield to those who take refuge in him.

6 Don’t you add to his words,

lest he reprove you, and you be found a liar.

7 “Two things I have asked of you.

Don’t deny me before I die.

8 Remove far from me falsehood and lies.

Give me neither poverty nor riches.

Feed me with the food that is needful for me,

9 lest I be full, deny you, and say, ‘Who is Yahweh?’

or lest I be poor, and steal,

and so dishonor the name of my God.

10 “Don’t slander a servant to his master,

lest he curse you, and you be held guilty.

11 There is a generation that curses their father,

and doesn’t bless their mother.

12 There is a generation that is pure in their own eyes,

yet are not washed from their filthiness.

13 There is a generation, oh how lofty are their eyes!

Their eyelids are lifted up.

14 There is a generation whose teeth are like swords,

and their jaws like knives,

to devour the poor from the earth, and the needy from among men.

15 “The leech has two daughters:

‘Give, give.’

“There are three things that are never satisfied;

four that don’t say, ‘Enough!’:

16 Sheol,[*]

the barren womb,

the earth that is not satisfied with water,

and the fire that doesn’t say, ‘Enough!’

17 “The eye that mocks at his father,

and scorns obedience to his mother,

the ravens of the valley shall pick it out,

the young eagles shall eat it.

18 “There are three things which are too amazing for me,

four which I don’t understand:

19 The way of an eagle in the air,

the way of a serpent on a rock,

the way of a ship in the middle of the sea,

and the way of a man with a maiden.

20 “So is the way of an adulterous woman:

She eats and wipes her mouth,

and says, ‘I have done nothing wrong.’

21 “For three things the earth trembles,

and under four, it can’t bear up:

22 For a servant when he is king,

a fool when he is filled with food,

23 for an unloved woman when she is married,

and a servant who is heir to her mistress.

24 “There are four things which are little on the earth,

but they are exceedingly wise:

25 The ants are not a strong people,

yet they provide their food in the summer.

26 The hyraxes are but a feeble folk,

yet make they their houses in the rocks.

27 The locusts have no king,

yet they advance in ranks.

28 You can catch a lizard with your hands,

yet it is in kings’ palaces.

29 “There are three things which are stately in their march,

four which are stately in going:

30 The lion, which is mightiest among animals,

and doesn’t turn away for any;

31 the greyhound;

the male goat;

and the king against whom there is no rising up.

32 “If you have done foolishly in lifting up yourself,

or if you have thought evil,

put your hand over your mouth.

33 For as the churning of milk produces butter,

and the wringing of the nose produces blood,

so the forcing of wrath produces strife.”

31

1 The words of king Lemuel—the revelation which his mother taught him:

2 “Oh, my son!

Oh, son of my womb!

Oh, son of my vows!

3 Don’t give your strength to women,

nor your ways to that which destroys kings.

4 It is not for kings, Lemuel,

it is not for kings to drink wine,

nor for princes to say, ‘Where is strong drink?’

5 lest they drink, and forget the law,

and pervert the justice due to anyone who is afflicted.

6 Give strong drink to him who is ready to perish,

and wine to the bitter in soul.

7 Let him drink, and forget his poverty,

and remember his misery no more.

8 Open your mouth for the mute,

in the cause of all who are left desolate.

9 Open your mouth, judge righteously,

and serve justice to the poor and needy.”

10  [*]Who can find a worthy woman?

For her value is far above rubies.

11 The heart of her husband trusts in her.

He shall have no lack of gain.

12 She does him good, and not harm,

all the days of her life.

13 She seeks wool and flax,

and works eagerly with her hands.

14 She is like the merchant ships.

She brings her bread from afar.

15 She rises also while it is yet night,

gives food to her household,

and portions for her servant girls.

16 She considers a field, and buys it.

With the fruit of her hands, she plants a vineyard.

17 She arms her waist with strength,

and makes her arms strong.

18 She perceives that her merchandise is profitable.

Her lamp doesn’t go out by night.

19 She lays her hands to the distaff,

and her hands hold the spindle.

20 She opens her arms to the poor;

yes, she extends her hands to the needy.

21 She is not afraid of the snow for her household,

for all her household are clothed with scarlet.

22 She makes for herself carpets of tapestry.

Her clothing is fine linen and purple.

23 Her husband is respected in the gates,

when he sits among the elders of the land.

24 She makes linen garments and sells them,

and delivers sashes to the merchant.

25 Strength and dignity are her clothing.

She laughs at the time to come.

26 She opens her mouth with wisdom.

Kind instruction is on her tongue.

27 She looks well to the ways of her household,

and doesn’t eat the bread of idleness.

28 Her children rise up and call her blessed.

Her husband also praises her:

29 “Many women do noble things,

but you excel them all.”

30 Charm is deceitful, and beauty is vain;

but a woman who fears Yahweh, she shall be praised.

31 Give her of the fruit of her hands!

Let her works praise her in the gates!

* 1:7 “Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

† 1:12 Sheol is the place of the dead.

‡ 1:23 “Behold”, from “הִנֵּה”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.

* 2:5 The Hebrew word rendered “God” is “אֱלֹהִ֑ים” (Elohim).

* 5:5 Sheol is the place of the dead.

* 7:27 Sheol is the place of the dead.

* 9:18 Sheol is the place of the dead.

* 11:21 or, seed

* 15:11 Sheol is the place of the dead.

† 15:24 Sheol is the place of the dead.

* 23:14 Sheol is the place of the dead.

* 27:20 Sheol is the place of the dead.

* 30:16 Sheol is the place of the dead.

* 31:10 Proverbs 31:10-31 form an acrostic, with each verse starting with each letter of the Hebrew alphabet, in order.

Ruth

1
2
3
4

The Book of

Ruth

1

1 In the days when the judges judged, there was a famine in the land. A certain man of Bethlehem Judah went to live in the country of Moab with his wife and his two sons. 2 The name of the man was Elimelech, and the name of his wife Naomi. The names of his two sons were Mahlon and Chilion, Ephrathites of Bethlehem Judah. They came into the country of Moab and lived there. 3 Elimelech, Naomi’s husband, died; and she was left with her two sons. 4 They took for themselves wives of the women of Moab. The name of the one was Orpah, and the name of the other was Ruth. They lived there about ten years. 5 Mahlon and Chilion both died, and the woman was bereaved of her two children and of her husband. 6 Then she arose with her daughters-in-law, that she might return from the country of Moab; for she had heard in the country of Moab how Yahweh[*] had visited his people in giving them bread. 7 She went out of the place where she was, and her two daughters-in-law with her. They went on the way to return to the land of Judah. 8 Naomi said to her two daughters-in-law, “Go, return each of you to her mother’s house. May Yahweh deal kindly with you, as you have dealt with the dead and with me. 9 May Yahweh grant you that you may find rest, each of you in the house of her husband.”

Then she kissed them, and they lifted up their voices, and wept. 10 They said to her, “No, but we will return with you to your people.”

11 Naomi said, “Go back, my daughters. Why do you want to go with me? Do I still have sons in my womb, that they may be your husbands? 12 Go back, my daughters, go your way; for I am too old to have a husband. If I should say, ‘I have hope,’ if I should even have a husband tonight, and should also bear sons, 13 would you then wait until they were grown? Would you then refrain from having husbands? No, my daughters, for it grieves me seriously for your sakes, for Yahweh’s hand has gone out against me.”

14 They lifted up their voices and wept again; then Orpah kissed her mother-in-law, but Ruth stayed with her. 15 She said, “Behold,[†] your sister-in-law has gone back to her people and to her god. Follow your sister-in-law.”

16 Ruth said, “Don’t urge me to leave you, and to return from following you, for where you go, I will go; and where you stay, I will stay. Your people will be my people, and your God[‡] my God. 17 Where you die, I will die, and there I will be buried. May Yahweh do so to me, and more also, if anything but death parts you and me.”

18 When Naomi saw that she was determined to go with her, she stopped urging her.

19 So they both went until they came to Bethlehem. When they had come to Bethlehem, all the city was excited about them, and they asked, “Is this Naomi?”

20 She said to them, “Don’t call me Naomi.[§] Call me Mara,[*] for the Almighty has dealt very bitterly with me. 21 I went out full, and Yahweh has brought me home again empty. Why do you call me Naomi, since Yahweh has testified against me, and the Almighty has afflicted me?” 22 So Naomi returned, and Ruth the Moabitess, her daughter-in-law, with her, who returned out of the country of Moab. They came to Bethlehem in the beginning of barley harvest.

2

1 Naomi had a relative of her husband’s, a mighty man of wealth, of the family of Elimelech, and his name was Boaz. 2 Ruth the Moabitess said to Naomi, “Let me now go to the field, and glean among the ears of grain after him in whose sight I find favor.”

She said to her, “Go, my daughter.” 3 She went, and came and gleaned in the field after the reapers; and she happened to come to the portion of the field belonging to Boaz, who was of the family of Elimelech.

4 Behold, Boaz came from Bethlehem, and said to the reapers, “May Yahweh be with you.”

They answered him, “May Yahweh bless you.”

5 Then Boaz said to his servant who was set over the reapers, “Whose young lady is this?”

6 The servant who was set over the reapers answered, “It is the Moabite lady who came back with Naomi out of the country of Moab. 7 She said, ‘Please let me glean and gather after the reapers among the sheaves.’ So she came, and has continued even from the morning until now, except that she rested a little in the house.”

8 Then Boaz said to Ruth, “Listen, my daughter. Don’t go to glean in another field, and don’t go from here, but stay here close to my maidens. 9 Let your eyes be on the field that they reap, and go after them. Haven’t I commanded the young men not to touch you? When you are thirsty, go to the vessels, and drink from that which the young men have drawn.”

10 Then she fell on her face and bowed herself to the ground, and said to him, “Why have I found favor in your sight, that you should take knowledge of me, since I am a foreigner?”

11 Boaz answered her, “I have been told all about what you have done for your mother-in-law since the death of your husband, and how you have left your father, your mother, and the land of your birth, and have come to a people that you didn’t know before. 12 May Yahweh repay your work, and a full reward be given to you from Yahweh, the God of Israel, under whose wings you have come to take refuge.”

13 Then she said, “Let me find favor in your sight, my lord, because you have comforted me, and because you have spoken kindly to your servant, though I am not as one of your servants.”

14 At meal time Boaz said to her, “Come here, and eat some bread, and dip your morsel in the vinegar.”

She sat beside the reapers, and they passed her parched grain. She ate, was satisfied, and left some of it. 15 When she had risen up to glean, Boaz commanded his young men, saying, “Let her glean even among the sheaves, and don’t reproach her. 16 Also pull out some for her from the bundles, and leave it. Let her glean, and don’t rebuke her.”

17 So she gleaned in the field until evening; and she beat out that which she had gleaned, and it was about an ephah[*] of barley. 18 She took it up, and went into the city. Then her mother-in-law saw what she had gleaned; and she brought out and gave to her that which she had left after she had enough.

19 Her mother-in-law said to her, “Where have you gleaned today? Where have you worked? Blessed be he who noticed you.”

She told her mother-in-law with whom she had worked, “The man’s name with whom I worked today is Boaz.” 20 Naomi said to her daughter-in-law, “May he be blessed by Yahweh, who has not abandoned his kindness to the living and to the dead.” Naomi said to her, “The man is a close relative to us, one of our near kinsmen.”

21 Ruth the Moabitess said, “Yes, he said to me, ‘You shall stay close to my young men until they have finished all my harvest.’ ”

22 Naomi said to Ruth her daughter-in-law, “It is good, my daughter, that you go out with his maidens, and that they not meet you in any other field.” 23 So she stayed close to the maidens of Boaz, to glean to the end of barley harvest and of wheat harvest; and she lived with her mother-in-law.

3

1 Naomi her mother-in-law said to her, “My daughter, shall I not seek rest for you, that it may be well with you? 2 Now isn’t Boaz our kinsman, with whose maidens you were? Behold, he will be winnowing barley tonight on the threshing floor. 3 Therefore wash yourself, anoint yourself, get dressed, and go down to the threshing floor; but don’t make yourself known to the man until he has finished eating and drinking. 4 It shall be, when he lies down, that you shall note the place where he is lying. Then you shall go in, uncover his feet, and lie down. Then he will tell you what to do.”

5 She said to her, “All that you say, I will do.” 6 She went down to the threshing floor, and did everything that her mother-in-law told her. 7 When Boaz had eaten and drunk, and his heart was merry, he went to lie down at the end of the heap of grain. She came softly, uncovered his feet, and lay down. 8 At midnight, the man was startled and turned himself; and behold, a woman lay at his feet. 9 He said, “Who are you?”

She answered, “I am Ruth your servant. Therefore spread the corner of your garment over your servant; for you are a near kinsman.”

10 He said, “You are blessed by Yahweh, my daughter. You have shown more kindness in the latter end than at the beginning, because you didn’t follow young men, whether poor or rich. 11 Now, my daughter, don’t be afraid. I will do to you all that you say; for all the city of my people knows that you are a worthy woman. 12 Now it is true that I am a near kinsman. However, there is a kinsman nearer than I. 13 Stay this night, and in the morning, if he will perform for you the part of a kinsman, good. Let him do the kinsman’s duty. But if he will not do the duty of a kinsman for you, then I will do the duty of a kinsman for you, as Yahweh lives. Lie down until the morning.”

14 She lay at his feet until the morning, then she rose up before one could discern another. For he said, “Let it not be known that the woman came to the threshing floor.” 15 He said, “Bring the mantle that is on you, and hold it.” She held it; and he measured six measures of barley, and laid it on her; then he went into the city.

16 When she came to her mother-in-law, she said, “How did it go, my daughter?”

She told her all that the man had done for her. 17 She said, “He gave me these six measures of barley; for he said, ‘Don’t go empty to your mother-in-law.’ ”

18 Then she said, “Wait, my daughter, until you know what will happen; for the man will not rest until he has settled this today.”

4

1 Now Boaz went up to the gate and sat down there. Behold, the near kinsman of whom Boaz spoke came by. Boaz said to him, “Come over here, friend, and sit down!” He came over, and sat down. 2 Boaz took ten men of the elders of the city, and said, “Sit down here,” and they sat down. 3 He said to the near kinsman, “Naomi, who has come back out of the country of Moab, is selling the parcel of land, which was our brother Elimelech’s. 4 I thought I should tell you, saying, ‘Buy it before those who sit here, and before the elders of my people.’ If you will redeem it, redeem it; but if you will not redeem it, then tell me, that I may know. For there is no one to redeem it besides you; and I am after you.”

He said, “I will redeem it.”

5 Then Boaz said, “On the day you buy the field from the hand of Naomi, you must buy it also from Ruth the Moabitess, the wife of the dead, to raise up the name of the dead on his inheritance.”

6 The near kinsman said, “I can’t redeem it for myself, lest I endanger my own inheritance. Take my right of redemption for yourself; for I can’t redeem it.”

7 Now this was the custom in former time in Israel concerning redeeming and concerning exchanging, to confirm all things: a man took off his sandal, and gave it to his neighbor; and this was the way of formalizing transactions in Israel. 8 So the near kinsman said to Boaz, “Buy it for yourself,” then he took off his sandal.

9 Boaz said to the elders and to all the people, “You are witnesses today, that I have bought all that was Elimelech’s, and all that was Chilion’s and Mahlon’s, from the hand of Naomi. 10 Moreover, Ruth the Moabitess, the wife of Mahlon, I have purchased to be my wife, to raise up the name of the dead on his inheritance, that the name of the dead may not be cut off from among his brothers and from the gate of his place. You are witnesses today.”

11 All the people who were in the gate, and the elders, said, “We are witnesses. May Yahweh make the woman who has come into your house like Rachel and like Leah, which both built the house of Israel; and treat you worthily in Ephrathah, and be famous in Bethlehem. 12 Let your house be like the house of Perez, whom Tamar bore to Judah, of the offspring[*] which Yahweh will give you by this young woman.”

13 So Boaz took Ruth and she became his wife; and he went in to her, and Yahweh enabled her to conceive, and she bore a son. 14 The women said to Naomi, “Blessed be Yahweh, who has not left you today without a near kinsman. Let his name be famous in Israel. 15 He shall be to you a restorer of life and sustain you in your old age; for your daughter-in-law, who loves you, who is better to you than seven sons, has given birth to him.” 16 Naomi took the child, laid him in her bosom, and became nurse to him. 17 The women, her neighbors, gave him a name, saying, “A son is born to Naomi”. They named him Obed. He is the father of Jesse, the father of David.

18 Now this is the history of the generations of Perez: Perez became the father of Hezron, 19 and Hezron became the father of Ram, and Ram became the father of Amminadab, 20 and Amminadab became the father of Nahshon, and Nahshon became the father of Salmon, 21 and Salmon became the father of Boaz, and Boaz became the father of Obed, 22 and Obed became the father of Jesse, and Jesse became the father of David.

* 1:6 “Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

† 1:15 “Behold”, from “הִנֵּה”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.

‡ 1:16 The Hebrew word rendered “God” is “אֱלֹהִ֑ים” (Elohim).

§ 1:20 “Naomi” means “pleasant”.

* 1:20 “Mara” means “bitter”.

* 2:17 1 ephah is about 22 liters or about 2/3 of a bushel

* 4:12 or, seed

Wisdom of Solomon

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10

11
12
13
14
15
16
17
18
19

THE WISDOM OF SOLOMON

The Wisdom of Solomon is recognized as Deuterocanonical Scripture by the Roman Catholic, Greek Orthodox, and Russian Orthodox Churches.

1

1 Love righteousness, all you who are judges of the earth.

Think of the Lord[*] with a good mind.

Seek him in singleness of heart,

2 because he is found by those who don’t put him to the test,

and is manifested to those who trust him.

3 for crooked thoughts separate from God.

His Power convicts when it is tested,

and exposes the foolish;

4 because wisdom will not enter into a soul that devises evil,

nor dwell in a body that is enslaved by sin.

5 For a holy spirit of discipline will flee deceit,

and will depart from thoughts that are without understanding,

and will be ashamed when unrighteousness has come in.

6 For[†] wisdom is a spirit who loves man,

and she will not hold a[‡] blasphemer guiltless for his lips,

because God is witness of his inmost self,

and is a true overseer of his heart,

and a hearer of his tongue.

7 Because the spirit of the Lord has filled[§] the world,

and that which holds all things together knows what is said.

8 Therefore no one who utters unrighteous things will be unseen;

[*] neither will Justice, when it convicts, pass him by.

9 For in his counsels the ungodly will be searched out,

and the sound of his words will come to the Lord to bring his lawless deeds to conviction;

10 because a jealous ear listens to all things,

and the noise of murmurings is not hidden.

11 Beware then of unprofitable murmuring,

and keep your tongue from slander;

because no secret utterance will go on its way void,

and a lying mouth destroys a soul.

12 Don’t court death in the error of your life.

Don’t draw destruction upon yourselves by the works of your hands;

13 because God didn’t make death,

neither does he delight when the living perish.

14 For he created all things that they might have being.

[†]The generative powers of the world are wholesome,

and there is no poison of destruction in them,

nor has Hades[‡] royal dominion upon earth;

15 for righteousness is immortal,

16 but ungodly men by their hands and their words summon[§]death;

deeming him a friend they[*] pined away.

They made a covenant with him,

because they are worthy to belong with him.

2

1 For they said[*] within themselves, with unsound reasoning,

“Our life is short and sorrowful.

There is no healing when a man comes to his end,

and no one was ever known who[†] was released from Hades.

2 Because we were born by mere chance,

and hereafter we will be as though we had never been,

because the breath in our nostrils is smoke,

and reason is a spark kindled by the beating of our heart,

3 which being extinguished, the body will be turned into ashes,

and the spirit will be dispersed as thin air.

4 Our name will be forgotten in time.

No one will remember our works.

Our life will pass away as the traces of a cloud,

and will be scattered as is a mist,

when it is chased by the rays of the sun,

and[‡] overcome by its heat.

5 For our allotted time is the passing of a shadow,

and our end doesn’t retreat,

because it is securely sealed, and no one[§] turns it back.

6 “Come therefore and let’s enjoy the good things that exist.

Let’s use the creation earnestly as in our youth.

7 Let’s fill ourselves with costly wine and perfumes,

and let no spring flower pass us by.

8 Let’s crown ourselves with rosebuds before they wither.

9 Let none of us go without his share in our proud revelry.

Let’s leave tokens of mirth everywhere,

because this is our portion, and this is our lot.

10 Let’s oppress the righteous poor.

Let’s not spare the widow,

nor regard the gray hair of the old man.

11 But let our strength be a law of righteousness;

for that which is weak is proven useless.

12 But let’s lie in wait for the righteous man,

because he annoys us,

is contrary to our works,

reproaches us with sins against the law,

and charges us with sins against our training.

13 He professes to have knowledge of God,

and calls himself a child of the Lord.

14 He became to us a reproof of our thoughts.

15 He is grievous to us even to look at,

because his life is unlike other men’s,

and his paths are strange.

16 We were regarded by him as something worthless,

and he abstains from our ways as from uncleanness.

He calls the latter end of the righteous happy.

He boasts that God is his father.

17 Let’s see if his words are true.

Let’s test what will happen at the end of his life.

18 For if the righteous man is God’s son, he will uphold him,

and he will deliver him out of the hand of his adversaries.

19 Let’s test him with insult and torture,

that we may find out how gentle he is,

and test his patience.

20 Let’s condemn him to a shameful death,

for he will be protected, according to his words.”

21 Thus they reasoned, and they were led astray;

for their wickedness blinded them,

22 and they didn’t know the mysteries of God,

neither did they hope for wages of holiness,

nor did they discern that there is a prize for blameless souls.

23 Because God created man for incorruption,

and made him an image of his own everlastingness;

24 but death entered into the world by the envy of the devil,

and those who belong to him experience it.

3

1 But the souls of the righteous are in the hand of God,

and no torment will touch them.

2 In the eyes of the foolish they seemed to have died.

Their departure was considered a disaster,

3 and their travel away from us ruin,

but they are in peace.

4 For even if in the sight of men they are punished,

their hope is full of immortality.

5 Having borne a little chastening, they will receive great good;

because God tested them, and found them worthy of himself.

6 He tested them like gold in the furnace,

and he accepted them as a whole burnt offering.

7 In the time of their visitation they will shine.

They will run back and forth like sparks among stubble.

8 They will judge nations and have dominion over peoples.

The Lord will reign over them forever.

9 Those who trust him will understand truth.

[*] The faithful will live with him in love,

because grace and mercy are with his chosen ones.

10 But the ungodly will be punished even as their reasoning deserves,

those who neglected righteousness and revolted from the Lord;

11 for he who despises wisdom and discipline is miserable.

Their hope is void and their toils unprofitable.

Their works are useless.

12 Their wives are foolish and their children are wicked.

13 Their descendants are cursed.

For the barren woman who is undefiled is happy,

she who has not conceived in transgression.

She will have fruit when God examines of souls.

14 So is the eunuch which has done no lawless deed with his hands,

nor imagined wicked things against the Lord;

for a precious gift will be given to him for his faithfulness,

and a delightful inheritance in the Lord’s sanctuary.

15 For good labors have fruit of great renown.

The root of understanding can’t fail.

16 But children of adulterers will not come to maturity.

The seed of an unlawful union will vanish away.

17 For if they live long, they will not be esteemed,

and in the end, their old age will be without honor.

18 If they die young, they will have no hope,

nor consolation in the day of judgment.

19 For the end of an unrighteous generation is always grievous.

4

1 It is better to be childless with virtue,

for immortality is in the memory of virtue,

because it is recognized both before God and before men.

2 When it is present, people imitate it.

They long after it when it has departed.

[*]Throughout all time it marches, crowned in triumph,

victorious in the competition for the prizes that are undefiled.

3 But the multiplying brood of the ungodly will be of no profit,

and their illegitimate offshoots won’t take deep root,

nor will they establish a sure hold.

4 For even if they grow branches and flourish for a season,

standing unsure, they will be shaken by the wind.

They will be uprooted by the violence of winds.

5 Their branches will be broken off before they come to maturity.

Their fruit will be useless,

never ripe to eat, and fit for nothing.

6 For unlawfully conceived children are witnesses of wickedness

against parents when they are investigated.

7 But a righteous man, even if he dies before his time, will be at rest.

8 For honorable old age is not that which stands in length of time,

nor is its measure given by number of years,

9 but understanding is gray hair to men,

and an unspotted life is ripe old age.

10 Being found well-pleasing to God, someone was loved.

While living among sinners he was transported.

11 He was caught away, lest evil should change his understanding,

or guile deceive his soul.

12 For the fascination of wickedness obscures the things which are good,

and the whirl of desire perverts an innocent mind.

13 Being made perfect quickly,

he filled a long time;

14 for his soul was pleasing to the Lord.

Therefore he hurried out of the midst of wickedness.

15 But the peoples saw and didn’t understand,

not considering this, that grace and mercy are with his chosen,

and that he visits his holy ones;

16 but a righteous man who is dead will condemn the ungodly who are living,

and youth who is quickly perfected will condemn the many years of an unrighteous man’s old age.

17 For the ungodly will see a wise man’s end,

and won’t understand what the Lord planned for him,

and why he safely kept him.

18 They will see, and they will despise;

but the Lord will laugh them to scorn.

After this, they will become a dishonored carcass

and a reproach among the dead forever;

19 because he will dash them speechless to the ground,

and will shake them from the foundations.

They will lie utterly waste.

They will be in anguish

and their memory will perish.

20 They will come with coward fear when their sins are counted.

Their lawless deeds will convict them to their face.

5

1 Then the righteous man will stand in great boldness

before the face of those who afflicted him,

and those who make his labors of no account.

2 When they see him, they will be troubled with terrible fear,

and will be amazed at the marvel of salvation.

3 They will speak among themselves repenting,

and for distress of spirit they will groan,

“This was he whom we used to hold in derision,

as a parable of reproach.

4 We fools considered his life madness,

and his end without honor.

5 How was he counted among sons of God?

How is his lot among saints?

6 Truly we went astray from the way of truth.

The light of righteousness didn’t shine for us.

The sun didn’t rise for us.

7 We[*] took our fill of the paths of lawlessness and destruction.

We traveled through trackless deserts,

but we didn’t know the Lord’s way.

8 What did our arrogance profit us?

What good have riches and boasting brought us?

9 Those things all passed away as a shadow,

like a rumor that runs by,

10 like a ship passing through the billowy water,

which, when it has gone by, there is no trace to be found,

no pathway of its keel in the waves.

11 Or it is like when a bird flies through the air,

no evidence of its passage is found,

but the light wind, lashed with the stroke of its pinions,

and torn apart with the violent rush of the moving wings, is passed through.

Afterwards no sign of its coming remains.

12 Or it is like when an arrow is shot at a mark,

the air it divided closes up again immediately,

so that men don’t know where it passed through.

13 So we also, as soon as we were born, ceased to be;

and we had no sign of virtue to show,

but we were utterly consumed in our wickedness.”

14 Because the hope of the ungodly man is like chaff carried by the wind,

and[†] as[‡] foam vanishing before a tempest;

and is scattered like smoke by the wind,

and passes by as the remembrance of a guest who stays just a day.

15 But the righteous live forever.

Their reward is in the Lord,

and the care for them with the Most High.

16 Therefore they will receive the crown of royal dignity

and the diadem of beauty from the Lord’s hand,

because he will cover them with his right hand,

and he will shield them with his arm.

17 He will take his zeal as complete armor,

and will make the whole creation his weapons to punish his enemies:

18 He will put on righteousness as a breastplate,

and will wear impartial judgment as a helmet.

19 He will take holiness as an invincible shield.

20 He will sharpen stern wrath for a sword.

The universe will go with him to fight against his frenzied foes.

21 Shafts of lightning will fly with true aim.

They will leap to the mark from the clouds, as from a well-drawn bow.

22 Hailstones full of wrath will be hurled as from a catapult.

The water of the sea will be angered against them.

Rivers will sternly overwhelm them.

23 A mighty wind will encounter them.

It will winnow them away like a tempest.

So lawlessness will make all the land desolate.

Their evil-doing will overturn the thrones of princes.

6

1 Hear therefore, you kings, and understand.

Learn, you judges of the ends of the earth.

2 Give ear, you rulers who have dominion over many people,

and make your boast[*] in multitudes of nations,

3 because your dominion was given to you from the Lord,

and your sovereignty from the Most High.

He will search out your works,

and will inquire about your plans,

4 because being officers of his kingdom, you didn’t judge rightly,

nor did you keep the law,

nor did you walk according to God’s counsel.

5 He will come upon you awfully and swiftly,

because a stern judgment comes on those who are in high places.

6 For the man of low estate may be pardoned in mercy,

but mighty men will be mightily tested.

7 For the Sovereign Lord of all will not be impressed with anyone,

neither will he show deference to greatness;

because it is he who made both small and great,

and cares about them all;

8 but the scrutiny that comes upon the powerful is strict.

9 Therefore, my words are to you, O princes,

that you may learn wisdom and not fall away.

10 For those who have kept the things that are holy in holiness will be made holy.

Those who have been taught them will find what to say in defense.

11 Therefore set your desire on my words.

Long for them, and you princes will be instructed.

12 Wisdom is radiant and doesn’t fade away;

and is easily seen by those who love her,

and found by those who seek her.

13 She anticipates those who desire her, making herself known.

14 He who rises up early to seek her won’t have difficulty,

for he will find her sitting at his gates.

15 For to think upon her is perfection of understanding,

and he who watches for her will quickly be free from care;

16 because she herself goes around, seeking those who are worthy of her,

and in their paths she appears to them graciously,

and in every purpose she meets them.

17 For her true beginning is desire for instruction;

and desire for instruction is love.

18 And love is observance of her laws.

To give heed to her laws confirms immortality.

19 Immortality brings closeness to God.

20 So then desire for wisdom promotes to a kingdom.

21 If therefore you delight in thrones and sceptres, you princes of peoples,

honor wisdom, that you may reign forever.

22 But what wisdom is, and how she came into being, I will declare.

I won’t hide mysteries from you;

but I will explore from her first beginning,

bring the knowledge of her into clear light,

and I will not pass by the truth.

23 Indeed, I won’t travel with consuming envy,

because envy will have no fellowship with wisdom.

24 But a multitude of wise men is salvation to the world,

and an understanding king is stability for his people.

25 Therefore be instructed by my words, and you will profit.

7

1 I myself am also[*] mortal, like everyone else,

and am a descendant of one formed first and born of the earth.

2 I molded into flesh in the time of ten months in my mother’s womb,

being compacted in blood from the seed of man and pleasure of marriage.

3 I also, when I was born, drew in the common air,

and fell upon the kindred earth,

uttering, like all, for my first voice, the same cry.

4 I was nursed with care in swaddling clothes.

5 For no king had a different beginning,

6 but all men have one entrance into life, and a common departure.

7 For this cause I prayed, and understanding was given to me.

I asked, and a spirit of wisdom came to me.

8 I preferred her before sceptres and thrones.

I considered riches nothing in comparison to her.

9 Neither did I liken to her any priceless gem,

because all gold in her presence is a little sand,

and silver will be considered as clay before her.

10 I loved her more than health and beauty,

and I chose to have her rather than light,

because her bright shining is never laid to sleep.

11 All good things came to me with her,

and innumerable riches are in her hands.

12 And I rejoiced over them all because wisdom leads them;

although I didn’t know that she was their mother.

13 As I learned without guile, I impart without grudging.

I don’t hide her riches.

14 For she is a treasure for men that doesn’t fail,

and those who use it obtain friendship with God,

commended by the gifts which they present through discipline.

15 But may God grant that I may speak his judgment,

and to conceive thoughts worthy of what has been given me;

because he is one who guides even wisdom and who corrects the wise.

16 For both we and our words are in his hand,

with all understanding and skill in various crafts.

17 For he himself gave me an unerring knowledge of the things that are,

to know the structure of the universe and the operation of the elements;

18 the beginning, end, and middle of times;

the alternations of the solstices and the changes of seasons;

19 the circuits of years and the positions of stars;

20 the natures of living creatures and the raging of wild beasts;

the violence of[†] winds and the thoughts of men;

the diversities of plants and the virtues of roots.

21 All things that are either secret or manifest I learned,

22 for wisdom, that is the architect of all things, taught me.

For there is in her a spirit that is quick to understand, holy,

unique, manifold, subtle, freely moving, clear in utterance, unpolluted,

distinct, invulnerable, loving what is good, keen, unhindered,

23 beneficent, loving toward man, steadfast, sure, free from care, all-powerful, all-surveying,

and penetrating through all spirits that are quick to understand, pure, most subtle.

24 For wisdom is more mobile than any motion.

Yes, she pervades and penetrates all things by reason of her purity.

25 For she is a breath of the power of God,

and a pure emanation of the glory of the Almighty.

Therefore nothing defiled can find entrance into her.

26 For she is a reflection of everlasting light,

an unspotted mirror of the working of God,

and an image of his goodness.

27 Although she is one, she has power to do all things.

Remaining in herself, she renews all things.

From generation to generation passing into holy souls,

she makes friends of God and prophets.

28 For God loves nothing as much as one who dwells with wisdom.

29 For she is fairer than the sun,

and above all the constellations of the stars.

She is better than light.

30 For daylight yields to night,

but evil does not prevail against wisdom.

8

1 But she reaches from one end to the other with full strength,

and orders all things well.

2 I loved her and sought her from my youth.

I sought to take her for my bride.

I became enamoured by her beauty.

3 She glorifies her noble birth by living with God.

The Sovereign Lord of all loves her.

4 For she is initiated into the knowledge of God,

and she chooses his works.

5 But if riches are a desired possession in life,

what is richer than wisdom, which makes all things?

6  And if understanding is effective,

who more than[*] wisdom is an architect of the things that exist?

7 If a man loves righteousness,

[†]the fruits of wisdom’s labor are virtues,

for she teaches soberness, understanding, righteousness, and courage.

There is nothing in life more profitable for people than these.

8 And if anyone longs for wide experience,

she knows the things of old, and infers the things to come.

She understands subtleties of speeches and interpretations of dark sayings.

She foresees signs and wonders, and the issues of seasons and times.

9 Therefore I determined to take her to live with me,

knowing that she is one who would give me good counsel,

and encourage me in cares and grief.

10 Because of her, I will have glory among multitudes,

and honor in the sight of elders, though I am young.

11 I will be found keen when I give judgment.

I will be admired in the presence of rulers.

12 When I am silent, they will wait for me.

When I open my lips, they will heed what I say.

If I continue speaking, they will put their hands on their mouths.

13 Because of her, I will have immortality,

and leave behind an eternal memory to those who come after me.

14 I will govern peoples.

Nations will be subjected to me.

15 Dreaded monarchs will fear me when they hear of me.

Among the people, I will show myself to be good, and courageous in war.

16 When I come into my house, I will find rest with her.

For conversation with her has no bitterness,

and living with her has no pain, but gladness and joy.

17 When I considered these things in myself,

and thought in my heart how immortality is in kinship to wisdom,

18 and in her friendship is good delight,

and in the labors of her hands is wealth that doesn’t fail,

and understanding is in her companionship,

and great renown in having fellowship with her words,

I went about seeking how to take her to myself.

19 Now I was a clever child, and received a good soul.

20 Or rather, being good, I came into an undefiled body.

21 But perceiving that I could not otherwise possess wisdom unless God gave her to me—

yes, and to know and understand by whom the grace is given—

I pleaded with the Lord and implored him, and with my whole heart I said:

9

1 “O God of my ancestors and Lord of mercy,

who made all things by your word;

2 and by your wisdom you formed man,

that he should have dominion over the creatures that were made by you,

3 and rule the world in holiness and righteousness,

and execute judgment in uprightness of soul,

4 give me wisdom, her who sits by you on your thrones.

Don’t reject me from among your[*] servants,

5 because I am your servant and the son of your handmaid,

a weak and short-lived man,

with little power to understand judgment and laws.

6 For even if a man is perfect among the sons of men,

if the wisdom that comes from you is not with him, he will count for nothing.

7 You chose me to be king of your people,

and a judge for your sons and daughters.

8 You gave a command to build a sanctuary on your holy mountain,

and[†] an altar in the city where you live,

a copy of the holy tent which you prepared from the beginning.

9 Wisdom is with you and knows your works,

and was present when you were making the world,

and understands what is pleasing in your eyes,

and what is right according to your commandments.

10 Send her from the holy heavens,

and ask her to come from the throne of your glory,

that being present with me she may work,

and I may learn what pleases you well.

11 For she knows all things and understands,

and she will guide me prudently in my actions.

She will guard me in her glory.

12 So my works will be acceptible.

I will judge your people righteously,

and I will be worthy of my father’s[‡] throne.

13 For what man will know the counsel of God?

Or who will conceive what the Lord wills?

14 For the thoughts of mortals are unstable,

and our plans are prone to fail.

15 For a corruptible body weighs down the soul.

The earthy tent burdens a mind that is full of cares.

16 We can hardly guess the things that are on earth,

and we find the things that are close at hand with labor;

but who has traced out the things that are in the heavens?

17 Who gained knowledge of your counsel, unless you gave wisdom,

and sent your holy spirit from on high?

18 It was thus that the ways of those who are on earth were corrected,

and men were taught the things that are pleasing to you.

They were saved through wisdom.”

10

1  [*] Wisdom guarded to the end the first formed father of the world, who was created alone,

and delivered him out of his own transgression,

2 and gave him strength to rule over all things.

3 But when an unrighteous man fell away from her in his anger,

he perished himself in the rage with which he killed his brother.

4 When for his cause the earth was drowning with a flood,

wisdom again saved it,

guiding the righteous man’s course by a paltry piece of wood.

5 Moreover, when nations consenting together in wickedness had been confounded,

[†] wisdom knew the righteous man, and preserved him blameless to God,

and kept him strong when his heart yearned toward his child.

6 While the ungodly were perishing, [‡] wisdom delivered a righteous man,

when he fled from the fire that descended out of heaven on the five cities.

7 To whose wickedness a smoking waste still witnesses,

and plants bearing fair fruit that doesn’t ripen,

a disbelieving soul has a memorial: a standing pillar of salt.

8 For having passed wisdom by,

not only were they disabled from recognising the things which are good,

but they also left behind them for their life a monument of their folly,

to the end that where they stumbled, they might fail even to be unseen;

9 but wisdom delivered those who waited on her out of troubles.

10 When a righteous man was a fugitive from a brother’s wrath,[§] wisdom guided him in straight paths.

She showed him God’s kingdom, and gave him knowledge of holy things.

She prospered him in his toils, and multiplied the fruits of his labor.

11 When in their covetousness men dealt harshly with him,

she stood by him and made him rich.

12 She guarded him from enemies,

and she kept him safe from those who lay in wait.

Over his severe conflict, she watched as judge,

that he might know that godliness is more powerful than every one.

13 When a righteous man was sold,[*] wisdom didn’t forsake him,

but she delivered him from sin.

She went down with him into a dungeon,

14 and in bonds she didn’t depart from him,

until she brought him the sceptre of a kingdom,

and authority over those that dealt like a tyrant with him.

She also showed those who had mockingly accused him to be false,

and gave him eternal glory.

15  [†] Wisdom delivered a holy people and a blameless seed from a nation of oppressors.

16 She entered into the soul of a servant of the Lord,

and withstood terrible kings in wonders and signs.

17 She rendered to holy men a reward of their toils.

She guided them along a marvelous way,

and became to them a covering in the day-time,

and a starry flame through the night.

18 She brought them over the Red sea,

and led them through much water;

19 but she drowned their enemies,

and she cast them up from the bottom of the deep.

20 Therefore the righteous plundered the ungodly,

and they sang praise to your holy name, O Lord,

and extolled with one accord your hand that fought for them,

21 because wisdom opened the mouth of the mute,

and made the tongues of babes to speak clearly.

11

1 Wisdom prospered their works in the hand of a holy prophet.

2 They traveled through a desert without inhabitant,

and they pitched their tents in trackless regions.

3 They withstood enemies and repelled foes.

4 They thirsted, and they called upon you,

and water was given to them out of the[*] flinty rock,

and healing of their thirst out of the hard stone.

5 For by what things their foes were punished,

by these they in their need were benefited.

6 When enemies were troubled with clotted blood

instead of a river’s ever-flowing fountain,

7 to rebuke the decree for the slaying of babies,

you gave them abundant water beyond all hope,

8 having shown by the thirst which they had suffered

how you punished the adversaries.

9 For when they were tried, although chastened in mercy,

they learned how the ungodly were tormented, being judged with wrath.

10 For you tested these as a father admonishing them;

but you searched out those as a stern king condemning them.

11 Yes and whether they were far off or near,

they were equally distressed;

12 for a double grief seized them,

and a groaning at the memory of things past.

13 For when they heard that through their own punishments the others benefited,

they recognized the Lord.

14 For him who long before was thrown out and exposed they stopped mocking.

In the end of what happened, they marveled,

having thirsted in another manner than the righteous.

15 But in return for the senseless imaginings of their unrighteousness,

wherein they were led astray to worship irrational reptiles and wretched vermin,

you sent upon them a multitude of irrational creatures to punish them,

16 that they might learn that by what things a man sins, by these he is punished.

17 For your all-powerful hand

that created the world out of formless matter

didn’t lack means to send upon them a multitude of bears, fierce lions,

18 or newly-created and unknown wild beasts, full of rage,

either breathing out a blast of fiery breath,

or belching out smoke,

or flashing dreadful sparks from their eyes;

19 which had power not only to consume them by their violence,

but to destroy them even by the terror of their sight.

20 Yes and without these they might have fallen by a single breath,

being pursued by Justice, and scattered abroad by the breath of your power;

but you arranged all things by measure, number, and weight.

21 For to be greatly strong is yours at all times.

Who could withstand the might of your arm?

22 Because the whole world before you is as a grain in a balance,

and as a drop of dew that comes down upon the earth in the morning.

23 But you have mercy on all men, because you have power to do all things,

and you overlook the sins of men to the end that they may repent.

24 For you love all things that are,

and abhor none of the things which you made;

For you never would have formed anything if you hated it.

25 How would anything have endured unless you had willed it?

Or that which was not called by you, how would it have been preserved?

26 But you spare all things, because they are yours,

O Sovereign Lord, you who love the living.

12

1 For your incorruptible spirit is in all things.

2 Therefore you convict little by little those who fall from the right way,

and, putting them in remembrance by the things wherein they sin, you admonish them,

that escaping from their wickedness they may believe in you, O Lord.

3 For truly the old inhabitants of your holy land,

4 hating them because they practiced detestable works of enchantments and unholy rites—

5  [*]merciless slaughters of children

and sacrificial banquets of men’s flesh and of blood—

6 allies in an impious fellowship,

and murderers of their own helpless babes,

it was your counsel to destroy by the hands of our fathers;

7 that the land which in your sight is most precious of all

might receive a worthy colony of God’s servants.[†]

8 Nevertheless you even spared these as men,

and you sent hornets[‡] as forerunners of your army,

to cause them to perish little by little.

9 Not that you were unable to subdue the ungodly under the hand of the righteous in battle,

or by terrible beasts or by a stern word to make away with them at once,

10 but judging them little by little you gave them a chance to repent,

not being ignorant that their nature by birth was evil,

their wickedness inborn,

and that their manner of thought would never be changed.

11 For they were a cursed seed from the beginning.

It wasn’t through fear of any that you left them unpunished for their sins.

12 For who will say, “What have you done?”

Or “Who will withstand your judgment?”

Who will accuse you for the perishing of nations which you caused?

Or who will come and stand before you as an avenger for unrighteous men?

13 For there isn’t any God beside you that cares for all,

that you might show that you didn’t judge unrighteously.

14 No king or prince will be able to confront you

about those whom you have punished.

15 But being righteous, you rule all things righteously,

deeming it a thing alien from your power

to condemn one who doesn’t deserve to be punished.

16 For your strength is the source of righteousness,

and your sovereignty over all makes you to forbear all.

17 For when men don’t believe that you are perfect in power, you show your strength,

[§]and in dealing with those who think this, you confuse their boldness.

18 But you, being sovereign in strength, judge in gentleness,

and with great forbearance you govern us;

for the power is yours whenever you desire it.

19 But you taught your people by such works as these,

how the righteous must be kind.

You made your sons to have good hope,

because you give repentance when men have sinned.

20 For if on those who were enemies of your servants[*] and deserving of death,

you took vengeance with so great deliberation and indulgence,

giving them times and opportunities when they might escape from their wickedness,

21 with how great care you judged your sons,

to whose fathers you gave oaths and covenants of good promises!

22 Therefore while you chasten us, you scourge our enemies ten thousand times more,

to the intent that we may ponder your goodness when we judge,

and when we are judged may look for mercy.

23 Therefore also the unrighteous that lived in a life of folly,

you tormented through their own abominations.

24 For truly they went astray very far in the ways of error,

Taking as gods those animals[†] which even among their enemies were held in dishonor,

deceived like foolish babes.

25 Therefore, as to unreasoning children, you sent your judgment to mock them.

26 But those who would not be admonished by mild correction

will experience the deserved judgment of God.

27 For through the sufferings they were indignant of,

being punished in these creatures which they supposed to be gods,

they saw and recognized as the true God him whom they previously refused to know.

Therefore also the result of extreme condemnation came upon them.

13

1 For truly all men who had no perception of God were foolish by nature,

and didn’t gain power to know him who exists from the good things that are seen.

They didn’t recognize the architect from his works.

2 But they thought that either fire, or wind, or swift air,

or circling stars, or raging water, or luminaries of heaven

were gods that rule the world.

3 If it was through delight in their beauty that they took them to be gods,

let them know how much better their Sovereign Lord is than these,

for the first author of beauty created them.

4 But if it was through astonishment at their power and influence,

then let them understand from them how much more powerful he who formed them is.

5 For from the greatness of the beauty of created things,

mankind forms the corresponding perception of their Maker.[*]

6 But yet for these men there is but small blame,

for they too perhaps go astray

while they are seeking God and desiring to find him.

7 For they diligently search while living among his works,

and they trust their sight that the things that they look at are beautiful.

8 But again even they are not to be excused.

9 For if they had power to know so much,

that they should be able to explore the world,

how is it that they didn’t find the Sovereign Lord sooner?

10 But they were miserable, and their hopes were in dead things,

who called them gods which are works of men’s hands,

gold and silver, skillfully made, and likenesses of animals,

or a useless stone, the work of an ancient hand.

11 Yes and some[†] woodcutter might saw down a tree that is easily moved,

skillfully strip away all its bark,

and fashion it in attractive form, make a useful vessel to serve his life’s needs.

12 Burning the scraps from his handiwork to cook his food,

he eats his fill.

13 Taking a discarded scrap which served no purpose,

a crooked piece of wood and full of knots,

he carves it with the diligence of his idleness,

and shapes it by the skill of his idleness.

He shapes it in the image of a man,

14 or makes it like some worthless animal,

smearing it with something red, painting it red,

and smearing over every stain in it.

15 Having made a worthy chamber for it,

he sets it in a wall, securing it with iron.

16 He plans for it that it may not fall down,

knowing that it is unable to help itself

(for truly it is an image, and needs help).

17 When he makes his prayer concerning goods and his marriage and children,

he is not ashamed to speak to that which has no life.

18 Yes, for health, he calls upon that which is weak.

For life, he implores that which is dead.

For aid, he supplicates that which has no experience.

For a good journey, he asks that which can’t so much as move a step.

19 And for profit in business and good success of his hands,

he asks ability from that which has hands with no ability.

14

1 Again, one preparing to sail, and about to journey over raging waves,

calls upon a piece of wood more fragile than the vessel that carries him.

2 For the hunger for profit planned it,

and wisdom was the craftsman who built it.

3 Your providence, O Father, guides it along,

because even in the sea you gave a way,

and in the waves a sure path,

4 showing that you can save out of every danger,

that even a man without skill may put to sea.

5 It is your will that the works of your wisdom should be not ineffective.

Therefore men also entrust their lives to a little piece of wood,

and passing through the surge on a raft come safely to land.

6 For[*] in the old time also, when proud giants were perishing,

the hope of the world, taking refuge on a raft,

your hand guided the seed of generations of the race of men.

7 For blessed is wood through which comes righteousness;

8 but the idol made with hands is accursed, itself and he that made it;

because his was the working, and the corruptible thing was called a god.

9 For both the ungodly and his ungodliness are alike hateful to God;

10 for truly the deed will be punished together with him who committed it.

11 Therefore also there will be a visitation among the idols of the nation,

because, though formed of things which God created, they were made an abomination,

stumbling blocks to the souls of men,

and a snare to the feet of the foolish.

12 For the devising of idols was the beginning of fornication,

and the invention of them the corruption of life.

13 For they didn’t exist from the beginning, and they won’t exist forever.

14 For by the boastfulness of men they entered into the world,

and therefore a speedy end was planned for them.

15 For a father worn with untimely grief,

making an image of the child quickly taken away,

now honored him as a god which was then a dead human being,

and delivered to those that were under him mysteries and solemn rites.

16 Afterward the ungodly custom, in process of time grown strong, was kept as a law,

and the engraved images received worship by the commandments of princes.

17 And when men could not honor them in presence because they lived far off,

imagining the likeness from afar,

they made a visible image of the king whom they honored,

that by their zeal they might flatter the absent as if present.

18 But worship was raised to a yet higher pitch, even by those who didn’t know him,

urged forward by the ambition of the architect;

19 for he, wishing perhaps to please his ruler,

used his art to force the likeness toward a greater beauty.

20 So the multitude, allured by reason of the grace of his handiwork,

now consider an object of devotion him that a little before was honored as a man.

21 And this became an ambush,

because men, in bondage either to calamity or to tyranny,

invested stones and stocks with the Name that shouldn’t be shared.

22 Afterward it was not enough for them to go astray concerning the knowledge of God,

but also, while they live in a great war of ignorance, they call a multitude of evils peace.

23 For either slaughtering children in solemn rites, or celebrating secret mysteries,

or holding frenzied revels of strange customs,

24 no longer do they guard either life or purity of marriage,

but one brings upon another either death by treachery, or anguish by adultery.

25 And all things confusedly are filled with blood and murder, theft and deceit,

corruption, faithlessness, tumult, perjury,

26 confusion about what is good, forgetfulness of favors,

ingratitude for benefits,

defiling of souls, confusion of sex,

disorder in marriage, adultery and wantonness.

27 For the worship of idols that may not be named [✡]

is a beginning and cause and end of every evil.

28 For their worshipers either make merry to madness, or prophesy lies,

or live unrighteously, or lightly commit perjury.

29 For putting their trust in lifeless idols,

when they have sworn a wicked oath, they expect not to suffer harm.

30 But on both counts, the just doom will pursue them,

because they had evil thoughts of God by giving heed to idols,

and swore unrighteously in deceit through contempt for holiness.

31 For it is not the power of things by which men swear,

but it is the just penalty for those who sin

that always visits the transgression of the unrighteous.

15

1 But you, our God, are gracious and true,

patient, and in mercy ordering all things.

2 For even if we sin, we are yours, knowing your dominion;

but we will not sin, knowing that we have been accounted yours.

3 For to be acquainted with you is[*] perfect righteousness,

and to know your dominion is the root of immortality.

4 For we weren’t led astray by any evil plan of men’s,

nor yet by painters’ fruitless labor,

a form stained with varied colors,

5 the sight of which leads fools into[†] lust.

Their desire is for the breathless form of a dead image.

6 Lovers of evil things, and worthy of such hopes,

are those who make, desire, and worship them.

7 For a potter, kneading soft earth,

laboriously molds each article for our service.

He fashions out of the same clay

both the vessels that minister to clean uses, and those of a contrary sort,

all in like manner.

What shall be the use of each article of either sort,

the potter is the judge.

8 Also, laboring to an evil end, he molds a vain god out of the same clay,

he who, having but a little before been made of earth,

after a short space goes his way to the earth out of which he was taken,

when he is required to render back the[‡] soul which was lent him.

9 However he has anxious care,

not because his powers must fail,

nor because his span of life is short;

But he compares himself with goldsmiths and silversmiths,

and he imitates molders in[§] brass,

and considers it great that he molds counterfeit gods.

10 His heart is ashes.

His hope is of less value than earth.

His life is of less honor than clay,

11 because he was ignorant of him who molded him,

and of him that inspired into him[*] an active[†] soul,

and breathed into him a vital spirit.

12 But[‡] he accounted our life to be a game,

and our[§] lifetime a festival for profit;

for, he says, one must get gain however one can, even if it is by evil.

13 For this man, beyond all others, knows that he sins,

out of earthy matter making brittle vessels and engraved images.

14 But most foolish and more miserable than a baby,

are the enemies of your people, who oppressed them;

15 because they even considered all the idols of the nations to be gods,

which have neither the use of eyes for seeing,

nor nostrils for drawing breath,

nor ears to hear,

nor fingers for handling,

and their feet are helpless for walking.

16 For a man made them,

and one whose own spirit is borrowed molded them;

for no one has power as a man to mold a god like himself.

17 But, being mortal, he makes a dead thing by the work of lawless hands;

for he is better than the objects of his worship,

since he indeed had life, but they never did.

18 Yes, and they worship the creatures that are most hateful,

for, being compared as to lack of sense, these are worse than all others;

19 Neither, as seen beside other creatures, are they beautiful, so that one should desire them,

but they have escaped both the praise of God and his blessing.

16

1 For this cause, they were deservedly punished through creatures like those which they worship,

and tormented through a multitude of vermin.

2 Instead of this punishment, you, giving benefits to your people,

prepared quails for food,

a delicacy to satisfy the desire of their appetite,

3 to the end that your enemies, desiring food,

might for the hideousness of the creatures sent among them,

loathe even the necessary appetite;

but these, your people, having for a short time suffered lack,

might even partake of delicacies.

4 For it was necessary that inescapable lack should come upon those oppressors,

but that to these it should only be showed how their enemies were tormented.

5 For even when terrible raging of wild beasts came upon your people,

and they were perishing by the bites of crooked serpents,

your wrath didn’t continue to the uttermost;

6 but for admonition were they troubled for a short time,

having a token of salvation

to put them in remembrance of the commandment of your law;

7 for he who turned toward it was not saved because of that which was seen,

but because of you, the Savior of all.

8 Yes, and in this you persuaded our enemies

that you are he who delivers out of every evil.

9 For the bites of locusts and flies truly killed them.

No healing for their life was found,

because they were worthy to be punished by such things.

10 But your children weren’t overcome by the very fangs of venomous dragons,

for your mercy passed by where they were and healed them.

11 For they were bitten to put them in remembrance of your oracles,

and were quickly saved, lest, falling into deep forgetfulness,

they should become unable to respond to your kindness.

12 For truly it was neither herb nor poultice that cured them,

but your word, O Lord, which heals all people.

13 For you have authority over life and death,

and you lead down to the gates of Hades, and lead up again.

14 But though a man kills by his wickedness,

he can’t retrieve the spirit that has departed

or release the imprisoned soul.

15 But it is not possible to escape your hand;

16 for ungodly men, refusing to know you, were scourged in the strength of your arm,

pursued with strange rains and hails and relentless storms,

and utterly consumed with fire.

17 For, what was most marvelous,

in the water which quenches all things, the fire burned hotter;

for the world fights for the righteous.

18 For at one time the flame was restrained,

that it might not burn up the creatures sent against the ungodly,

but that these themselves as they looked might see that they were chased by the judgment of God.

19 At another time even in the midst of water it burns more intensely than fire,

that it may destroy the produce of an unrighteous land.

20 Instead of these things, you gave your people angels’ food to eat,

and you provided ready-to-eat bread for them from heaven without toil,

having the virtue of every pleasant flavor,

and agreeable to every taste.

21 For your nature showed your sweetness toward your children,

while that bread, serving the desire of the eater,

changed itself according to every man’s choice.

22 But snow and ice endured fire, and didn’t melt,

that people might know that fire was destroying the fruits of the enemies,

burning in the hail and flashing in the rains;

23 and that this fire, again, in order that righteous people may be nourished,

has even forgotten its own power.

24 For the creation, ministering to you, its maker,

strains its force against the unrighteous for punishment

and in kindness, slackens it on behalf of those who trust in you.

25 Therefore at that time also, converting itself into all forms,

it ministered to your all-nourishing bounty,

according to the desire of those who had need,

26 that your children, whom you loved, O Lord, might learn

that it is not the growth of crops that nourishes a man,

but that your word preserves those who trust you.

27 For that which was not destroyed by fire,

melted away when it was simply warmed by a faint sunbeam,

28 that it might be known that we must rise before the sun to give you thanks,

and must pray to you at the dawning of the light;

29 for the hope of the unthankful will melt as the winter’s hoar frost,

and will flow away as water that has no use.

17

1 For your judgments are great, and hard to interpret;

therefore undisciplined souls went astray.

2 For when lawless men had supposed that they held a holy nation in their power,

they, prisoners of darkness, and bound in the fetters of a long night,

kept close beneath their roofs,

lay exiled from the eternal providence.

3 For while they thought that they were unseen in their secret sins,

they were divided from one another by a dark curtain of forgetfulness,

stricken with terrible awe, and very troubled by apparitions.

4 For neither did the dark recesses that held them guard them from fears,

but terrifying sounds rang around them,

and dismal phantoms appeared with unsmiling faces.

5 And no power of fire prevailed to give light,

neither were the brightest flames of the stars strong enough to illuminate that gloomy night;

6 but only the glimmering of a self-kindled fire appeared to them, full of fear.

In terror, they considered the things which they saw

to be worse than that sight, on which they could not gaze.

7  The mockeries of their magic arts were powerless, now,

and a shameful rebuke of their boasted understanding:

8 For those who promised to drive away terrors and disorders from a sick soul,

these were sick with a ludicrous fearfulness.

9 For even if no troubling thing frighted them,

yet, scared with the creeping of vermin and hissing of serpents,

10 they perished trembling in fear,

refusing even to look at the air, which could not be escaped on any side.

11  For wickedness, condemned by a witness within, is a coward thing,

and, being pressed hard by conscience, always has added forecasts of the worst.

12 For fear is nothing else but a surrender of the help which reason offers;

13 and from within, the expectation of being less

prefers ignorance of the cause that brings the torment.

14 But they, all through the night which was powerless indeed,

and which came upon them out of the recesses of powerless Hades,

sleeping the same sleep,

15 now were haunted by monstrous apparitions,

and now were paralyzed by their soul’s surrendering;

for sudden and unexpected fear came upon them.

16 So then whoever it might be, sinking down in his place,

was kept captive, shut up in that prison which was not barred with iron;

17 for whether he was a farmer, or a shepherd,

or a laborer whose toils were in the wilderness,

he was overtaken, and endured that inescapable sentence;

for they were all bound with one chain of darkness.

18 Whether there was a whistling wind,

or a melodious sound of birds among the spreading branches,

or a measured fall of water running violently,

19 or a harsh crashing of rocks hurled down,

or the swift course of animals bounding along unseen,

or the voice of wild beasts harshly roaring,

or an echo rebounding from the hollows of the mountains,

all these things paralyzed them with terror.

20 For the whole world was illuminated with clear light,

and was occupied with unhindered works,

21 while over them alone was spread a heavy night,

an image of the darkness that should afterward receive them;

but to themselves, they were heavier than darkness.

18

1 But for your holy ones there was great light.

Their enemies, hearing their voice but not seeing their form,

counted it a happy thing that they too had suffered,

2 yet for that they do not hurt them, though wronged by them before, they are thankful;

and because they had been at variance with them, they begged for pardon.

3 Therefore you provided a burning pillar of fire,

to be a guide for your people’s unknown journey,

and a harmless sun for their glorious exile.

4 For the Egyptians well deserved to be deprived of light and imprisoned by darkness,

they who had imprisoned your children,

through whom the incorruptible light of the law was to be given to the race of men.

5 After they had taken counsel to kill the babes of the holy ones,

and when a single child had been abandoned and saved to convict them of their sin,

you took away from them their multitude of children,

and destroyed all their army together in a mighty flood.

6 Our fathers were made aware of that night beforehand,

that, having sure knowledge, they might be cheered by the oaths which they had trusted.

7 Salvation of the righteous and destruction of the enemies was expected by your people.

8 For as you took vengeance on the adversaries,

by the same means, calling us to yourself, you glorified us.

9 For holy children of good men offered sacrifice in secret,

and with one consent they agreed to the covenant of the divine law,

that they would partake alike in the same good things and the same perils,

the fathers already leading the sacred songs of praise.

10 But the discordant cry of the enemies echoed back,

and a pitiful voice of lamentation for children was spread abroad.

11 Both servant and master were punished with the same just doom,

and the commoner suffering the same as king;

12 Yes, they all together, under one form of death,

had corpses without number.

For the living were not sufficient even to bury them,

Since at a single stroke, their most cherished offspring was consumed.

13 For while they were disbelieving all things by reason of the enchantments,

upon the destruction of the firstborn they confessed the people to be God’s children.

14 For while peaceful silence wrapped all things,

and night in her own swiftness was half spent,

15 your all-powerful word leaped from heaven, from the royal throne,

a stern warrior, into the midst of the doomed land,

16 bearing as a sharp sword your authentic commandment,

and standing, it filled all things with death,

and while it touched the heaven it stood upon the earth.

17 Then immediately apparitions in dreams terribly troubled them,

and unexpected fears came upon them.

18 And each, one thrown here half dead, another there,

made known why he was dying;

19 for the dreams, disturbing them, forewarned them of this,

that they might not perish without knowing why they were afflicted.

20 The experience of death also touched the righteous,

and a multitude were destroyed in the wilderness,

but the wrath didn’t last long.

21 For a blameless man hurried to be their champion,

bringing the weapon of his own ministry,

prayer, and the atoning sacrifice of incense.

He withstood the indignation and set an end to the calamity,

showing that he was your servant.

22 And he overcame the anger,

not by strength of body, not by force of weapons,

but by his word, he subdued the avenger

by bringing to remembrance oaths and covenants made with the fathers.

23 For when the dead had already fallen in heaps one upon another,

he intervened and stopped the wrath,

and cut off its way to the living.

24 For the whole world was pictured on his long robe,

and the glories of the fathers were upon the engraving of the four rows of precious stones,

and your majesty was upon the diadem on his head.

25 The destroyer yielded to these, and they feared;

for it was enough only to test the wrath.

19

1 But indignation without mercy came upon the ungodly to the end;

for God also foreknew their future,

2 how, having changed their minds to let your people go,

and having sped them eagerly on their way,

they would change their minds and pursue them.

3 For while they were yet in the midst of their mourning,

and lamenting at the graves of the dead,

they made another foolish decision,

and pursued as fugitives those whom they had begged to leave and driven out.

4 For the doom which they deserved was drawing them to this end,

and it made them forget the things that had happened to them,

that they might fill up the punishment which was yet lacking from their torments,

5 and that your people might journey on by a marvelous road,

but they themselves might find a strange death.

6 For the whole creation, each part in its diverse kind, was made new again,

complying with your commandments,

that your servants might be kept unharmed.

7 Then the cloud that overshadowed the camp was seen,

and dry land rising up out of what had been water,

out of the Red sea an unhindered highway,

and a grassy plain out of the violent surge,

8 by which they passed over with all their army,

these who were covered with your hand,

having seen strange marvels.

9 For like horses they roamed at large,

and they skipped about like lambs,

praising you, O Lord, who was their deliverer.

10 For they still remembered the things that happened in the time of their sojourning,

how instead of bearing cattle, the land brought forth lice,

and instead of fish, the river spewed out a multitude of frogs.

11 But afterwards, they also saw a new kind of birds,

when, led on by desire, they asked for luxurious dainties;

12 for, to comfort them, quails came up for them from the sea.

13 Punishments came upon the sinners,

not without the signs that were given beforehand by the violence of the thunder,

for they justly suffered through their own wickednesses,

for the hatred which they practiced toward guests was grievous indeed.

14 For while the others didn’t receive the strangers when they came to them,

the Egyptians made slaves of guests who were their benefactors.

15 And not only so, but while punishment of some sort will come upon the former,

since they received as enemies those who were aliens;

16 because these first welcomed with feastings,

and then afflicted with dreadful toils,

those who had already shared with them in the same rights.

17 And moreover they were stricken with loss of sight

(even as were those others at the righteous man’s doors),

when, being surrounded with yawning darkness,

they each looked for the passage through his own door.

18 For as the notes of a lute vary the character of the rhythm,

even so the elements, changing their order one with another,

continuing always in its sound,

as may clearly be conjectured from the sight of the things that have happened.

19 For creatures of the dry land were turned into creatures of the waters,

and creatures that swim moved upon the land.

20 Fire kept the mastery of its own power in water,

and water forgot its quenching nature.

21 On the contrary, flames didn’t consume flesh of perishable creatures that walked among them,

neither did they melt the crystalline grains of ambrosial food that were melted easily.

22 For in all things, O Lord, you magnified your people,

and you glorified them and didn’t lightly regard them,

standing by their side in every time and place.

* 1:1 Gr. in goodness.

† 1:6 Some authorities read the spirit of wisdom is loving to man.

‡ 1:6 Or, reviler

§ 1:7 Gr. the inhabited earth.

* 1:8 Some authorities read nor indeed.

† 1:14 Or, all the races of creatures in the world

‡ 1:14 Or, a royal house

§ 1:16 Or, Hades Gr. him.

* 1:16 Or, were consumed with love of him

* 2:1 Or, among

† 2:1 Or, returned out of Hades

‡ 2:4 Gr. weighed down.

§ 2:5 Or, comes again

* 3:9 Or, Those who are faithful through love will live with him

* 4:2 Gr. in the age.

* 5:7 See Proverbs 14:14.

† 5:14 Gr. like foam chased to thinness: or, as thin foam chased.

‡ 5:14 Most Greek authorities read hoar frost: some authorities, perhaps rightly, a spider’s web.

* 6:2 Or, in the multitudes of your nations

* 7:1 Many authorities read a mortal man.

† 7:20 Or, spirits

* 8:6 Gr. she.

† 8:7 Gr. Her labors are.

* 9:4 Or, children

† 9:8 Or, a place of sacrifice

‡ 9:12 Gr. thrones.

* 10:1 Gr. She.

† 10:5 Gr. She

‡ 10:6 Gr. she

§ 10:10 Gr. she.

* 10:13 Gr. she.

† 10:15 Gr. she.

* 11:4 See Deuteronomy 8:15; Psalm 114:8.

* 12:5 The words rendered slaughters and impious in verses 5 and 6 differ but slightly from the readings of the Greek text, which here yield no sense.

† 12:7 Or, children

‡ 12:8 Or, wasps

§ 12:17 The Greek text here is perhaps corrupt.

* 12:20 Or, children

† 12:24 Gr. living creatures: and so elsewhere in this book.

* 13:5 Gr. is the first maker of them seen.

† 13:11 Gr. carpenter who is a woodcutter.

* 14:6 The Greek text here may be corrupt.

✡ 14:27 Exodus 23:13; Psalm 16:4; Hosea 2:17; Wisdom 14:21

* 15:3 Gr. entire.

† 15:5 Some authorities read reproach.

‡ 15:8 Or, life

§ 15:9 Or, copper

* 15:11 Gr. a soul that moves to activity.

† 15:11 Or, life

‡ 15:12 Some authorities read they accounted.

§ 15:12 Or, way of life

Zechariah

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10

11
12
13
14

The Book of

Zechariah

1

1 In the eighth month, in the second year of Darius, Yahweh’s[*] word came to the prophet Zechariah the son of Berechiah, the son of Iddo, saying, 2 “Yahweh was very displeased with your fathers. 3 Therefore tell them, Yahweh of Armies says: ‘Return to me,’ says Yahweh of Armies, ‘and I will return to you,’ says Yahweh of Armies. 4 Don’t you be like your fathers, to whom the former prophets proclaimed, saying: Yahweh of Armies says, ‘Return now from your evil ways and from your evil doings;’ but they didn’t hear nor listen to me, says Yahweh. 5 Your fathers, where are they? And the prophets, do they live forever? 6 But my words and my decrees, which I commanded my servants the prophets, didn’t they overtake your fathers?

“Then they repented and said, ‘Just as Yahweh of Armies determined to do to us, according to our ways and according to our practices, so he has dealt with us.’ ”

7 On the twenty-fourth day of the eleventh month, which is the month Shebat, in the second year of Darius, Yahweh’s word came to the prophet Zechariah the son of Berechiah, the son of Iddo, saying, 8 “I had a vision in the night, and behold,[†] a man riding on a red horse, and he stood among the myrtle trees that were in a ravine; and behind him there were red, brown, and white horses. 9 Then I asked, ‘My lord, what are these?’ ”

The angel who talked with me said to me, “I will show you what these are.”

10 The man who stood among the myrtle trees answered, “They are the ones Yahweh has sent to go back and forth through the earth.”

11 They reported to Yahweh’s angel who stood among the myrtle trees, and said, “We have walked back and forth through the earth, and behold, all the earth is at rest and in peace.”

12 Then Yahweh’s angel replied, “O Yahweh of Armies, how long will you not have mercy on Jerusalem and on the cities of Judah, against which you have had indignation these seventy years?”

13 Yahweh answered the angel who talked with me with kind and comforting words. 14 So the angel who talked with me said to me, “Proclaim, saying, ‘Yahweh of Armies says: “I am jealous for Jerusalem and for Zion with a great jealousy. 15 I am very angry with the nations that are at ease; for I was but a little displeased, but they added to the calamity.” 16 Therefore Yahweh says: “I have returned to Jerusalem with mercy. My house shall be built in it,” says Yahweh of Armies, “and a line shall be stretched out over Jerusalem.” ’

17 “Proclaim further, saying, ‘Yahweh of Armies says: “My cities will again overflow with prosperity, and Yahweh will again comfort Zion, and will again choose Jerusalem.” ’ ”

18 I lifted up my eyes and saw, and behold, four horns. 19 I asked the angel who talked with me, “What are these?”

He answered me, “These are the horns which have scattered Judah, Israel, and Jerusalem.”

20 Yahweh showed me four craftsmen. 21 Then I asked, “What are these coming to do?”

He said, “These are the horns which scattered Judah, so that no man lifted up his head; but these have come to terrify them, to cast down the horns of the nations that lifted up their horn against the land of Judah to scatter it.”

2

1 I lifted up my eyes, and saw, and behold, a man with a measuring line in his hand. 2 Then I asked, “Where are you going?”

He said to me, “To measure Jerusalem, to see what is its width and what is its length.”

3 Behold, the angel who talked with me went out, and another angel went out to meet him, 4 and said to him, “Run, speak to this young man, saying, ‘Jerusalem will be inhabited as villages without walls, because of the multitude of men and livestock in it. 5 For I,’ says Yahweh, ‘will be to her a wall of fire around it, and I will be the glory in the middle of her.

6 Come! Come! Flee from the land of the north,’ says Yahweh; ‘for I have spread you abroad as the four winds of the sky,’ says Yahweh. 7 ‘Come, Zion! Escape, you who dwell with the daughter of Babylon.’ 8 For Yahweh of Armies says: ‘For honor he has sent me to the nations which plundered you; for he who touches you touches the apple of his eye. 9 For, behold, I will shake my hand over them, and they will be a plunder to those who served them; and you will know that Yahweh of Armies has sent me. 10 Sing and rejoice, daughter of Zion! For behold, I come and I will dwell within you,’ says Yahweh. 11 Many nations shall join themselves to Yahweh in that day, and shall be my people; and I will dwell among you, and you shall know that Yahweh of Armies has sent me to you. 12 Yahweh will inherit Judah as his portion in the holy land, and will again choose Jerusalem. 13 Be silent, all flesh, before Yahweh; for he has roused himself from his holy habitation!”

3

1 He showed me Joshua the high priest standing before Yahweh’s angel, and Satan standing at his right hand to be his adversary. 2 Yahweh said to Satan, “Yahweh rebuke you, Satan! Yes, Yahweh who has chosen Jerusalem rebuke you! Isn’t this a burning stick plucked out of the fire?”

3 Now Joshua was clothed with filthy garments, and was standing before the angel. 4 He answered and spoke to those who stood before him, saying, “Take the filthy garments off him.” To him he said, “Behold, I have caused your iniquity to pass from you, and I will clothe you with rich clothing.”

5 I said, “Let them set a clean turban on his head.”

So they set a clean turban on his head, and clothed him; and Yahweh’s angel was standing by.

6 Yahweh’s angel solomnly assured Joshua, saying, 7 “Yahweh of Armies says: ‘If you will walk in my ways, and if you will follow my instructions, then you also shall judge my house, and shall also keep my courts, and I will give you a place of access among these who stand by. 8 Hear now, Joshua the high priest, you and your fellows who sit before you, for they are men who are a sign; for, behold, I will bring out my servant, the Branch. 9 For, behold, the stone that I have set before Joshua: on one stone are seven eyes; behold, I will engrave its inscription,’ says Yahweh of Armies, ‘and I will remove the iniquity of that land in one day. 10 In that day,’ says Yahweh of Armies, ‘you will invite every man his neighbor under the vine and under the fig tree.’ ”

4

1 The angel who talked with me came again and wakened me, as a man who is wakened out of his sleep. 2 He said to me, “What do you see?”

I said, “I have seen, and behold, a lamp stand all of gold, with its bowl on the top of it, and its seven lamps on it; there are seven pipes to each of the lamps which are on the top of it; 3 and two olive trees by it, one on the right side of the bowl, and the other on the left side of it.”

4 I answered and spoke to the angel who talked with me, saying, “What are these, my lord?”

5 Then the angel who talked with me answered me, “Don’t you know what these are?”

I said, “No, my lord.”

6 Then he answered and spoke to me, saying, “This is Yahweh’s word to Zerubbabel, saying, ‘Not by might, nor by power, but by my Spirit,’ says Yahweh of Armies. 7 Who are you, great mountain? Before Zerubbabel you are a plain; and he will bring out the capstone with shouts of ‘Grace, grace, to it!’ ”

8 Moreover Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 9 “The hands of Zerubbabel have laid the foundation of this house. His hands shall also finish it; and you will know that Yahweh of Armies has sent me to you. 10 Indeed, who despises the day of small things? For these seven shall rejoice, and shall see the plumb line in the hand of Zerubbabel. These are Yahweh’s eyes, which run back and forth through the whole earth.”

11 Then I asked him, “What are these two olive trees on the right side of the lamp stand and on the left side of it?”

12 I asked him the second time, “What are these two olive branches, which are beside the two golden spouts that pour the golden oil out of themselves?”

13 He answered me, “Don’t you know what these are?”

I said, “No, my lord.”

14 Then he said, “These are the two anointed ones who stand by the Lord[*] of the whole earth.”

5

1 Then again I lifted up my eyes and saw, and behold, a flying scroll. 2 He said to me, “What do you see?”

I answered, “I see a flying scroll; its length is twenty cubits,[*] and its width ten cubits.”

3 Then he said to me, “This is the curse that goes out over the surface of the whole land, for everyone who steals shall be cut off according to it on the one side; and everyone who swears falsely shall be cut off according to it on the other side. 4 I will cause it to go out,” says Yahweh of Armies, “and it will enter into the house of the thief, and into the house of him who swears falsely by my name; and it will remain in the middle of his house, and will destroy it with its timber and its stones.”

5 Then the angel who talked with me came forward and said to me, “Lift up now your eyes and see what this is that is appearing.”

6 I said, “What is it?”

He said, “This is the ephah[†] basket that is appearing.” He said moreover, “This is their appearance in all the land— 7 and behold, a lead cover weighing one talent[‡] was lifted up—and there was a woman sitting in the middle of the ephah[§] basket.” 8 He said, “This is Wickedness;” and he threw her down into the middle of the ephah basket; and he threw the lead weight on its mouth.

9 Then I lifted up my eyes and saw, and behold, there were two women; and the wind was in their wings. Now they had wings like the wings of a stork, and they lifted up the ephah basket between earth and the sky. 10 Then I said to the angel who talked with me, “Where are these carrying the ephah basket?”

11 He said to me, “To build her a house in the land of Shinar. When it is prepared, she will be set there in her own place.”

6

1 Again I lifted up my eyes, and saw, and behold, four chariots came out from between two mountains; and the mountains were mountains of bronze. 2 In the first chariot were red horses. In the second chariot were black horses. 3 In the third chariot were white horses. In the fourth chariot were dappled horses, all of them powerful. 4 Then I asked the angel who talked with me, “What are these, my lord?”

5 The angel answered me, “These are the four winds of the sky, which go out from standing before the Lord of all the earth. 6 The one with the black horses goes out toward the north country; and the white went out after them; and the dappled went out toward the south country.” 7 The strong went out, and sought to go that they might walk back and forth through the earth. He said, “Go around and through the earth!” So they walked back and forth through the earth.

8 Then he called to me, and spoke to me, saying, “Behold, those who go toward the north country have quieted my spirit in the north country.”

9 Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 10 “Take of them of the captivity, even of Heldai, of Tobijah, and of Jedaiah; and come the same day, and go into the house of Josiah the son of Zephaniah, where they have come from Babylon. 11 Yes, take silver and gold, and make crowns, and set them on the head of Joshua the son of Jehozadak, the high priest; 12 and speak to him, saying, ‘Yahweh of Armies says, “Behold, the man whose name is the Branch! He will grow up out of his place; and he will build Yahweh’s temple. 13 He will build Yahweh’s temple. He will bear the glory, and will sit and rule on his throne. He will be a priest on his throne. The counsel of peace will be between them both. 14 The crowns shall be to Helem, to Tobijah, to Jedaiah, and to Hen the son of Zephaniah, for a memorial in Yahweh’s temple.

15 Those who are far off shall come and build in Yahweh’s temple; and you shall know that Yahweh of Armies has sent me to you. This will happen, if you will diligently obey Yahweh your God’s voice.” ’ ”[*]

7

1 In the fourth year of king Darius, Yahweh’s word came to Zechariah in the fourth day of the ninth month, the month of Chislev. 2 The people of Bethel sent Sharezer and Regem Melech and their men to entreat Yahweh’s favor, 3 and to speak to the priests of the house of Yahweh of Armies and to the prophets, saying, “Should I weep in the fifth month, separating myself, as I have done these so many years?”

4 Then the word of Yahweh of Armies came to me, saying, 5 “Speak to all the people of the land and to the priests, saying, ‘When you fasted and mourned in the fifth and in the seventh month for these seventy years, did you at all fast to me, really to me? 6 When you eat and when you drink, don’t you eat for yourselves and drink for yourselves? 7 Aren’t these the words which Yahweh proclaimed by the former prophets when Jerusalem was inhabited and in prosperity, and its cities around her, and the South and the lowland were inhabited?’ ”

8 Yahweh’s word came to Zechariah, saying, 9 “Thus has Yahweh of Armies spoken, saying, ‘Execute true judgment, and show kindness and compassion every man to his brother. 10 Don’t oppress the widow, the fatherless, the foreigner, nor the poor; and let none of you devise evil against his brother in your heart.’ 11 But they refused to listen, and turned their backs, and stopped their ears, that they might not hear. 12 Yes, they made their hearts as hard as flint, lest they might hear the law and the words which Yahweh of Armies had sent by his Spirit by the former prophets. Therefore great wrath came from Yahweh of Armies. 13 It has come to pass that, as he called and they refused to listen, so they will call and I will not listen,” said Yahweh of Armies; 14 “but I will scatter them with a whirlwind among all the nations which they have not known. Thus the land was desolate after them, so that no man passed through nor returned; for they made the pleasant land desolate.”

8

1 The word of Yahweh of Armies came to me. 2 Yahweh of Armies says: “I am jealous for Zion with great jealousy, and I am jealous for her with great wrath.”

3 Yahweh says: “I have returned to Zion, and will dwell in the middle of Jerusalem. Jerusalem shall be called ‘The City of Truth;’ and the mountain of Yahweh of Armies, ‘The Holy Mountain.’ ”

4 Yahweh of Armies says: “Old men and old women will again dwell in the streets of Jerusalem, every man with his staff in his hand because of their old age. 5 The streets of the city will be full of boys and girls playing in its streets.”

6 Yahweh of Armies says: “If it is marvelous in the eyes of the remnant of this people in those days, should it also be marvelous in my eyes?” says Yahweh of Armies.

7 Yahweh of Armies says: “Behold, I will save my people from the east country and from the west country. 8 I will bring them, and they will dwell within Jerusalem. They will be my people, and I will be their God, in truth and in righteousness.”

9 Yahweh of Armies says: “Let your hands be strong, you who hear in these days these words from the mouth of the prophets who were in the day that the foundation of the house of Yahweh of Armies was laid, even the temple, that it might be built. 10 For before those days there was no wages for man nor any wages for an animal, neither was there any peace to him who went out or came in, because of the adversary. For I set all men everyone against his neighbor. 11 But now I will not be to the remnant of this people as in the former days,” says Yahweh of Armies. 12 “For the seed of peace and the vine will yield its fruit, and the ground will give its increase, and the heavens will give their dew. I will cause the remnant of this people to inherit all these things. 13 It shall come to pass that, as you were a curse among the nations, house of Judah and house of Israel, so I will save you, and you shall be a blessing. Don’t be afraid. Let your hands be strong.”

14 For Yahweh of Armies says: “As I thought to do evil to you when your fathers provoked me to wrath,” says Yahweh of Armies, “and I didn’t repent, 15 so again I have thought in these days to do good to Jerusalem and to the house of Judah. Don’t be afraid. 16 These are the things that you shall do: speak every man the truth with his neighbor. Execute the judgment of truth and peace in your gates, 17 and let none of you devise evil in your hearts against his neighbor, and love no false oath; for all these are things that I hate,” says Yahweh.

18 The word of Yahweh of Armies came to me. 19 Yahweh of Armies says: “The fasts of the fourth, fifth, seventh, and tenth months shall be for the house of Judah joy, gladness, and cheerful feasts. Therefore love truth and peace.”

20 Yahweh of Armies says: “Many peoples and the inhabitants of many cities will yet come. 21 The inhabitants of one will go to another, saying, ‘Let’s go speedily to entreat the favor of Yahweh, and to seek Yahweh of Armies. I will go also.’ 22 Yes, many peoples and strong nations will come to seek Yahweh of Armies in Jerusalem and to entreat the favor of Yahweh.” 23 Yahweh of Armies says: “In those days, ten men out of all the languages of the nations will take hold of the skirt of him who is a Jew, saying, ‘We will go with you, for we have heard that God is with you.’ ”

9

1 A revelation.

Yahweh’s word is against the land of Hadrach,

and will rest upon Damascus—

for the eye of man

and of all the tribes of Israel is toward Yahweh—

2 and Hamath, also, which borders on it,

Tyre and Sidon, because they are very wise.

3 Tyre built herself a stronghold,

and heaped up silver like the dust,

and fine gold like the mire of the streets.

4 Behold, the Lord will dispossess her,

and he will strike her power in the sea;

and she will be devoured with fire.

5 Ashkelon will see it, and fear;

Gaza also, and will writhe in agony;

as will Ekron, for her expectation will be disappointed;

and the king will perish from Gaza,

and Ashkelon will not be inhabited.

6 Foreigners will dwell in Ashdod,

and I will cut off the pride of the Philistines.

7 I will take away his blood out of his mouth,

and his abominations from between his teeth;

and he also will be a remnant for our God;

and he will be as a chieftain in Judah,

and Ekron as a Jebusite.

8 I will encamp around my house against the army,

that no one pass through or return;

and no oppressor will pass through them any more:

for now I have seen with my eyes.

9 Rejoice greatly, daughter of Zion!

Shout, daughter of Jerusalem!

Behold, your King comes to you!

He is righteous, and having salvation;

lowly, and riding on a donkey,

even on a colt, the foal of a donkey.

10 I will cut off the chariot from Ephraim

and the horse from Jerusalem.

The battle bow will be cut off;

and he will speak peace to the nations.

His dominion will be from sea to sea,

and from the River to the ends of the earth.

11 As for you also,

because of the blood of your covenant,

I have set free your prisoners from the pit in which is no water.

12 Turn to the stronghold, you prisoners of hope!

Even today I declare that I will restore double to you.

13 For indeed I bend Judah as a bow for me.

I have loaded the bow with Ephraim.

I will stir up your sons, Zion,

against your sons, Greece,

and will make you like the sword of a mighty man.

14 Yahweh will be seen over them.

His arrow will flash like lightning.

The Lord Yahweh will blow the trumpet,

and will go with whirlwinds of the south.

15 Yahweh of Armies will defend them.

They will destroy and overcome with sling stones.

They will drink, and roar as through wine.

They will be filled like bowls,

like the corners of the altar.

16 Yahweh their God will save them in that day as the flock of his people;

for they are like the jewels of a crown,

lifted on high over his land.

17 For how great is his goodness,

and how great is his beauty!

Grain will make the young men flourish,

and new wine the virgins.

10

1 Ask of Yahweh rain in the spring time,

Yahweh who makes storm clouds,

and he gives rain showers to everyone for the plants in the field.

2 For the teraphim[*] have spoken vanity,

and the diviners have seen a lie;

and they have told false dreams.

They comfort in vain.

Therefore they go their way like sheep.

They are oppressed, because there is no shepherd.

3 My anger is kindled against the shepherds,

and I will punish the male goats,

for Yahweh of Armies has visited his flock, the house of Judah,

and will make them as his majestic horse in the battle.

4 From him will come the cornerstone,

from him the tent peg,

from him the battle bow,

from him every ruler together.

5 They will be as mighty men,

treading down muddy streets in the battle.

They will fight, because Yahweh is with them.

The riders on horses will be confounded.

6 “I will strengthen the house of Judah,

and I will save the house of Joseph.

I will bring them back,

for I have mercy on them.

They will be as though I had not cast them off,

for I am Yahweh their God, and I will hear them.

7 Ephraim will be like a mighty man,

and their heart will rejoice as through wine.

Yes, their children will see it and rejoice.

Their heart will be glad in Yahweh.

8 I will signal for them and gather them,

for I have redeemed them.

They will increase as they were before.

9 I will sow them among the peoples.

They will remember me in far countries.

They will live with their children and will return.

10 I will bring them again also out of the land of Egypt,

and gather them out of Assyria.

I will bring them into the land of Gilead and Lebanon;

and there won’t be room enough for them.

11 He will pass through the sea of affliction,

and will strike the waves in the sea,

and all the depths of the Nile will dry up;

and the pride of Assyria will be brought down,

and the scepter of Egypt will depart.

12 I will strengthen them in Yahweh.

They will walk up and down in his name,” says Yahweh.

11

1 Open your doors, Lebanon,

that the fire may devour your cedars.

2 Wail, cypress tree, for the cedar has fallen,

because the stately ones are destroyed.

Wail, you oaks of Bashan,

for the strong forest has come down.

3 A voice of the wailing of the shepherds!

For their glory is destroyed—a voice of the roaring of young lions!

For the pride of the Jordan is ruined.

4 Yahweh my God says: “Feed the flock of slaughter. 5 Their buyers slaughter them and go unpunished. Those who sell them say, ‘Blessed be Yahweh, for I am rich;’ and their own shepherds don’t pity them. 6 For I will no more pity the inhabitants of the land,” says Yahweh; “but, behold, I will deliver every one of the men into his neighbor’s hand and into the hand of his king. They will strike the land, and out of their hand I will not deliver them.”

7 So I fed the flock to be slaughtered, especially the oppressed of the flock. I took for myself two staffs. The one I called “Favor” and the other I called “Union”, and I fed the flock. 8 I cut off the three shepherds in one month; for my soul was weary of them, and their soul also loathed me. 9 Then I said, “I will not feed you. That which dies, let it die; and that which is to be cut off, let it be cut off; and let those who are left eat each other’s flesh.” 10 I took my staff Favor and cut it apart, that I might break my covenant that I had made with all the peoples. 11 It was broken in that day; and thus the poor of the flock that listened to me knew that it was Yahweh’s word. 12 I said to them, “If you think it best, give me my wages; and if not, keep them.” So they weighed for my wages thirty pieces of silver. 13 Yahweh said to me, “Throw it to the potter—the handsome price that I was valued at by them!” I took the thirty pieces of silver and threw them to the potter in Yahweh’s house. 14 Then I cut apart my other staff, Union, that I might break the brotherhood between Judah and Israel.

15 Yahweh said to me, “Take for yourself yet again the equipment of a foolish shepherd. 16 For, behold, I will raise up a shepherd in the land who will not visit those who are cut off, neither will seek those who are scattered, nor heal that which is broken, nor feed that which is sound; but he will eat the meat of the fat sheep, and will tear their hoofs in pieces. 17 Woe to the worthless shepherd who leaves the flock! The sword will strike his arm and his right eye. His arm will be completely withered, and his right eye will be totally blinded!”

12

1 A revelation of Yahweh’s word concerning Israel: Yahweh, who stretches out the heavens and lays the foundation of the earth, and forms the spirit of man within him says: 2 “Behold, I will make Jerusalem a cup of reeling to all the surrounding peoples, and it will also be on Judah in the siege against Jerusalem. 3 It will happen in that day that I will make Jerusalem a burdensome stone for all the peoples. All who burden themselves with it will be severely wounded, and all the nations of the earth will be gathered together against it. 4 In that day,” says Yahweh, “I will strike every horse with terror and his rider with madness. I will open my eyes on the house of Judah, and will strike every horse of the peoples with blindness. 5 The chieftains of Judah will say in their heart, ‘The inhabitants of Jerusalem are my strength in Yahweh of Armies their God.’

6 In that day I will make the chieftains of Judah like a pan of fire among wood, and like a flaming torch among sheaves. They will devour all the surrounding peoples on the right hand and on the left; and Jerusalem will yet again dwell in their own place, even in Jerusalem.

7 Yahweh also will save the tents of Judah first, that the glory of David’s house and the glory of the inhabitants of Jerusalem not be magnified above Judah. 8 In that day Yahweh will defend the inhabitants of Jerusalem. He who is feeble among them at that day will be like David, and David’s house will be like God, like Yahweh’s angel before them. 9 It will happen in that day, that I will seek to destroy all the nations that come against Jerusalem.

10 I will pour on David’s house and on the inhabitants of Jerusalem the spirit of grace and of supplication. They will look to me[*] whom they have pierced; and they shall mourn for him as one mourns for his only son, and will grieve bitterly for him as one grieves for his firstborn. 11 In that day there will be a great mourning in Jerusalem, like the mourning of Hadadrimmon in the valley of Megiddo. 12 The land will mourn, every family apart; the family of David’s house apart, and their wives apart; the family of the house of Nathan apart, and their wives apart; 13 the family of the house of Levi apart, and their wives apart; the family of the Shimeites apart, and their wives apart; 14 all the families who remain, every family apart, and their wives apart.

13

1 “In that day there will be a fountain opened to David’s house and to the inhabitants of Jerusalem, for sin and for uncleanness.

2 It will come to pass in that day, says Yahweh of Armies, that I will cut off the names of the idols out of the land, and they will be remembered no more. I will also cause the prophets and the spirit of impurity to pass out of the land. 3 It will happen that when anyone still prophesies, then his father and his mother who bore him will tell him, ‘You must die, because you speak lies in Yahweh’s name;’ and his father and his mother who bore him will stab him when he prophesies. 4 It will happen in that day that the prophets will each be ashamed of his vision when he prophesies; they won’t wear a hairy mantle to deceive, 5 but he will say, ‘I am no prophet, I am a tiller of the ground; for I have been made a bondservant from my youth.’ 6 One will say to him, ‘What are these wounds between your arms?’ Then he will answer, ‘Those with which I was wounded in the house of my friends.’

7 “Awake, sword, against my shepherd,

and against the man who is close to me,” says Yahweh of Armies.

“Strike the shepherd, and the sheep will be scattered;

and I will turn my hand against the little ones.

8 It shall happen that in all the land,” says Yahweh,

“two parts in it will be cut off and die;

but the third will be left in it.

9 I will bring the third part into the fire,

and will refine them as silver is refined,

and will test them like gold is tested.

They will call on my name, and I will hear them.

I will say, ‘It is my people;’

and they will say, ‘Yahweh is my God.’ ”

14

1 Behold, a day of Yahweh comes, when your plunder will be divided within you. 2 For I will gather all nations against Jerusalem to battle; and the city will be taken, the houses rifled, and the women ravished. Half of the city will go out into captivity, and the rest of the people will not be cut off from the city. 3 Then Yahweh will go out and fight against those nations, as when he fought in the day of battle. 4 His feet will stand in that day on the Mount of Olives, which is before Jerusalem on the east; and the Mount of Olives will be split in two from east to west, making a very great valley. Half of the mountain will move toward the north, and half of it toward the south. 5 You shall flee by the valley of my mountains, for the valley of the mountains shall reach to Azel. Yes, you shall flee, just like you fled from before the earthquake in the days of Uzziah king of Judah. Yahweh my God will come, and all the holy ones with you.[*]

6 It will happen in that day that there will not be light, cold, or frost. 7 It will be a unique day which is known to Yahweh—not day, and not night; but it will come to pass that at evening time there will be light.

8 It will happen in that day that living waters will go out from Jerusalem, half of them toward the eastern sea, and half of them toward the western sea. It will be so in summer and in winter.

9 Yahweh will be King over all the earth. In that day Yahweh will be one, and his name one.

10 All the land will be made like the Arabah, from Geba to Rimmon south of Jerusalem; and she will be lifted up and will dwell in her place, from Benjamin’s gate to the place of the first gate, to the corner gate, and from the tower of Hananel to the king’s wine presses. 11 Men will dwell therein, and there will be no more curse; but Jerusalem will dwell safely.

12 This will be the plague with which Yahweh will strike all the peoples who have fought against Jerusalem: their flesh will consume away while they stand on their feet, and their eyes will consume away in their sockets, and their tongue will consume away in their mouth. 13 It will happen in that day that a great panic from Yahweh will be among them; and they will each seize the hand of his neighbor, and his hand will rise up against the hand of his neighbor. 14 Judah also will fight at Jerusalem; and the wealth of all the surrounding nations will be gathered together: gold, silver, and clothing, in great abundance.

15 A plague like this will fall on the horse, on the mule, on the camel, on the donkey, and on all the animals that will be in those camps.

16 It will happen that everyone who is left of all the nations that came against Jerusalem will go up from year to year to worship the King, Yahweh of Armies, and to keep the feast of booths. 17 It will be that whoever of all the families of the earth doesn’t go up to Jerusalem to worship the King, Yahweh of Armies, on them there will be no rain. 18 If the family of Egypt doesn’t go up and doesn’t come, neither will it rain on them. This will be the plague with which Yahweh will strike the nations that don’t go up to keep the feast of booths. 19 This will be the punishment of Egypt and the punishment of all the nations that don’t go up to keep the feast of booths.

20 In that day there will be inscribed on the bells of the horses, “HOLY TO YAHWEH”; and the pots in Yahweh’s house will be like the bowls before the altar. 21 Yes, every pot in Jerusalem and in Judah will be holy to Yahweh of Armies; and all those who sacrifice will come and take of them, and cook in them. In that day there will no longer be a Canaanite[†] in the house of Yahweh of Armies.

* 1:1 “Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

† 1:8 “Behold”, from “הִנֵּה”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.

* 4:14 The word translated “Lord” is “Adonai.”

* 5:2 A cubit is the length from the tip of the middle finger to the elbow on a man’s arm, or about 18 inches or 46 centimeters.

† 5:6 An ephah is a measure of volume of about 22 liters, 5.8 U. S. gallons, or about 2/3 of a bushel.

‡ 5:7 A talent is about 30 kilograms or 66 pounds.

§ 5:7 1 ephah is about 22 liters or about 2/3 of a bushel

* 6:15 The Hebrew word rendered “God” is “אֱלֹהִ֑ים” (Elohim).

* 10:2 teraphim were household idols that may have been associated with inheritance rights to the household property.

* 12:10 After “me”, the Hebrew has the two letters “Aleph Tav” (the first and last letters of the Hebrew alphabet), not as a word, but as a grammatical marker.

* 14:5 Septuagint reads “him” instead of “you”.

† 14:21 or, merchant